<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<?xml-model href="file:/V:/Digital%20Editing/HSP%20digital%20project%20schemas/HSPDigitalProjectsSchema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">


    <teiHeader xml:lang="English">

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">TEI transcription of The Last Ditch of the Chivalry, or a
                    President in Petticoats</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp key="art">Artist</resp>
                    <persName key="ENT.000000553"/>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp key="trc">Transcribed by</resp>
                    <persName key="ENT.000003368"/>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp key="mrk">Encoded by</resp>
                    <persName key="ENT.000003368"/>
                </respStmt>

            </titleStmt>

            <editionStmt>
                <p>First edition, <date when="2015">2015</date></p>
            </editionStmt>

            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher><orgName key="ENT.000002473">Historical Society of
                    Pennsylvania</orgName></publisher>
                <pubPlace>1300 Locust Street, Philadelphia, PA</pubPlace>
                <idno type="filename">11827</idno>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright 2015, Historical Society of Pennsylvania. HSP makes a claim of
                        copyright only to original contributions made by the Historic Images, New
                        Technologies (HINT) Project participants and other staff. HSP makes no claim
                        of copyright to the original text. Permission is granted to download,
                        transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the text
                        contributions to this work claimed by HSP for non-profit educational
                        purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                        inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Historical Society of
                        Pennsylvania. HSP retains the rights of all images unless otherwise noted.
                        Possession of an HSP digital image does not constitute permission to use or
                        publish it. Requests for digital imaging, other reproduction services, and
                        the intended use of reproductions must be made in writing to the Rights and
                        Reproductions Coordinator at rnr@hsp.org.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2015"/>
            </publicationStmt>

            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project" key="CARTOONS"/>
            </seriesStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository key="ENT.000002473"/>
                        <collection key="3133"/>
                        <idno type="citation">
                            <idno type="box">6</idno>
                            <idno type="folder">10</idno>
                        </idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <bibl>
                                <date from="1865-01-01" to="1865-12-31">1865</date>
                                <extent>1 loose sheet</extent>
                                <listRelation>
                                    <relation name="depicted" active="ENT.000001041"/>
                                    <!-- Davis -->
                                </listRelation>
                            </bibl>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>

                    <history>
                        <acquisition>This is an artificial collection created over time by HSP staff
                            mostly through donations and purchases of individual prints. It also
                            incorporates previously uncataloged materials collected by the Balch
                            Institute for Ethnic Studies. Some of the 20th century cartoons and
                            drawings were removed from the J. Hampton Moore papers (Collection
                            1541).</acquisition>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp key="art">Artist</resp>
                            <persName key="ENT.000000553"/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <title type="main" level="m">The Last Ditch of the Chivalry, or a President
                            in Petticoats</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher><orgName key="ENT.000000844">Currier &amp;
                                Ives</orgName></publisher>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <date from="1865-01-01" to="1865-12-31">1865</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Historic Images, New Technologies (HINT) project aims to enhance description
                    and discovery of the Historical Society of Pennsylvania's graphics materials and
                    promote the linking and sharing of content among institutions and scholars. The
                    project will result in an update to HSP's digital image viewer and an online
                    digital history exhibit that will demonstrate the new viewer's capabilities and
                    provide interpretive and contextual materials to encourage users to interact
                    with historical images in new ways. This project was funded by a grant from the
                    National Historical Publications and Records Commission's (NHPRC) Innovation in
                    Archives and Documentary Editing program.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="4">
                <p>This electronic file was created using manual keying following the
                    recommendations for Level 4 of "Best Practices for TEI in Libraries" guidelines
                    v3.0.</p>
                <p>This xml file uses unique entity identifiers, media file identifiers, and
                    collection identifiers in HSP's Digital Library, available at
                    http://digitallibrary.hsp.org.</p>

            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="italics">font-style: italic</rendition>
                <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="bold">font-weight: bold</rendition>
                <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="underline">text-decoration: underline</rendition>
                <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="crossed-through">text-decoration:
                    line-through</rendition>
                <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="printed"/>
                <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="typescript"/>
                <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="handwritten"/>
                <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="handwritten-underlined"/>
                <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="handwritten-circled"/>
                <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="handwritten-crossed-through"/>
                <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="double-underline"/>
                <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="stamp"/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef target="cartoons_genres.xml#lithographs"/>
                <catRef target="cartoons_genres.xml#political_cartoons"/>
                <catRef target="cartoons_taxonomies.xml#civil_war"/>
                <catRef target="cartoons_taxonomies.xml#lesson_plan"/>
                <catRef target="cartoons_taxonomies.xml#gender"/>
                <catRef target="cartoons_taxonomies.xml#war"/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>

        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="RachelMoloshok" when="2015-04-22">Featured encoding (for lesson plan cartoon)</change>
            <change who="RachelMoloshok" when="2015-04-22">Basic encoding</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <facsimile>
        <surface ulx="" uly="" lrx="" lry="">
            <graphic url="FIL.000089719"/>
            <zone n="1" xml:id="title"/>
            <zone n="2" xml:id="soldier1"/>
            <zone n="3" xml:id="soldier2"/>
            <zone n="4" xml:id="soldier3"/>
            <zone n="5" xml:id="woman"/>
            <zone n="6" xml:id="davis"/>
            <zone n="7" xml:id="sack"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>

    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="editorial_desc">
                <p>At the right of the page, Confederate president Jefferson Davis, disguised in
                    women's clothing, is shown running away from soldiers of the US Army. Davis is
                    wearing a dress, and a woman's bonnet, attached to his neck by a ribbon, has
                    just fallen off of his head; underneath the dress, he is wearing men's riding
                    boots with spurs. He holds a sack of gold under his right arm and clutches a
                    dagger in his right hand. In pursuit are four Union soldiers with swords and
                    pistols drawn. They call out to Davis to surrender, telling him that they see
                    through his disguise. Davis, still pretending to be a woman, cries out "Let me
                    alone, you bloodthirsty villains: I thought your government more magnanimous
                    than to hunt down women and children!" Behind Davis, a Confederate woman tries
                    to defend the Confederate president against the Union soldiers, telling them
                    "Look out, you vile Yankees, if you make him mad, he will hurt some of you!"
                    This cartoon is a sensationalized depiction of the capture of Jefferson Davis on
                    the morning of May 10, 1865, near Irwinville, Georgia. Following his capture,
                    rumors circulated that Davis had been found attempting to escape while disguised
                    as a woman. According to Davis, as the troops closed in he had hurriedly put on
                    the first coat he could find (his wife's raincoat), and his wife thew her shawl
                    over his head for further protection. Cartoonists seized on the opportunity to
                    make fun of the former president of the Confederacy by portraying him
                    masquerading in full female dress, complete with hoop skirts, petticoats, and
                    bonnets.</p>
            </div>
        </front>

        <body>
            <div type="image_transcription" n="1" facs="#title">
                <head><supplied resp="editorial">Title and imprint</supplied></head>
                <p><hi rendition="#bold">THE LAST DITCH OF THE CHIVALRY, OR A PRESIDENT IN
                        PETTICOATS.</hi></p>
                <p>Published by <orgName key="ENT.000000844">Currier &amp; Ives</orgName>, 152
                    Nassau St N.Y.</p>
                <p>Entered according to act of Congress <date when="1865">AD 1865</date>. by Currier
                    &amp; Ives, in the Clerk's Office of the District Court of the United States,
                    for the Southern District of N.Y.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="image_transcription" n="2" facs="#soldier1">
                <head><supplied resp="editorial">Soldier 1</supplied></head>
                <p>Give in Old Chap, we have got a $100,000 on you!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="image_transcription" n="3" facs="#soldier2">
                <head><supplied resp="editorial">Soldier 2 (waving hat and pistol)</supplied></head>
                <p>It's no use trying that shift <persName key="ENT.000001041">Jeff</persName>, we
                    see your boots!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="image_transcription" n="4" facs="#soldier3">
                <head><supplied resp="editorial">Soldier 3 (pointing pistol at <persName
                            key="ENT.000001041">Davis</persName>)</supplied></head>
                <p>Surrender Old Fellow, or we will let daylight into you; you have reached your
                    last ditch!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="image_transcription" n="5" facs="#woman">
                <head><supplied resp="editorial">Woman</supplied></head>
                <p>Look out you vile Yankees, if you make him mad he will hurt some of you!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="image_transcription" n="6" facs="#davis">
                <head><supplied resp="editorial"><persName key="ENT.000001041">Jefferson
                            Davis</persName> (disguised as woman)</supplied></head>
                <p>Let me alone you blood thirsty villains: __ I thought your government more
                    magnanimous than to hunt down women and children!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="image_transcription" n="7" facs="#sack">
                <head><supplied resp="editorial">Sack</supplied></head>
                <p>GOLD.</p>
            </div>
        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
