<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<?xml-model href="file:/V:/Digital%20Editing/HSP%20digital%20project%20schemas/HSPDigitalProjectsSchema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader xml:lang="English">

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">TEI transcription of The Modern Laocoon</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp key="art">Artist</resp>
                    <persName key="ENT.000003781">Brackmere</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp key="trc">Transcribed by</resp>
                    <persName key="ENT.000003368"/>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp key="mrk">Encoded by</resp>
                    <persName key="ENT.000003368"/>
                </respStmt>

            </titleStmt>

            <editionStmt>
                <p>First edition, <date when="2015">2015</date></p>
            </editionStmt>

            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher><orgName key="ENT.000002473">Historical Society of
                    Pennsylvania</orgName></publisher>
                <pubPlace>1300 Locust Street, Philadelphia, PA</pubPlace>
                <idno type="filename">12273</idno>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright 2015, Historical Society of Pennsylvania. HSP makes a claim of
                        copyright only to original contributions made by the Historic Images, New
                        Technologies (HINT) Project participants and other staff. HSP makes no claim
                        of copyright to the original text. Permission is granted to download,
                        transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the text
                        contributions to this work claimed by HSP for non-profit educational
                        purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                        inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Historical Society of
                        Pennsylvania. HSP retains the rights of all images unless otherwise noted.
                        Possession of an HSP digital image does not constitute permission to use or
                        publish it. Requests for digital imaging, other reproduction services, and
                        the intended use of reproductions must be made in writing to the Rights and
                        Reproductions Coordinator at rnr@hsp.org.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2015"/>
            </publicationStmt>

            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project" key="CARTOONS"/>
            </seriesStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository key="ENT.000002473"/>
                        <collection key="3133"/>
                        <idno type="citation">
                            <idno type="box">2</idno>
                            <idno type="folder">4</idno>
                        </idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <bibl>
                                <date from="1871-10-07">October 7, 1871</date>
                                <extent>1 newspaper page</extent>
                                <listRelation>
                                    <relation name="depicted" active="ENT.000003638"/>
                                    <!-- tweed -->
                                    <relation name="depicted" active="ENT.000003782"/>
                                    <!-- hall -->
                                    <relation name="depicted" active="ENT.000003783"/>
                                    <!-- connolly -->
                                    <relation name="depicted" active="ENT.000003784"/>
                                    <!-- sweeney -->
                                    <relation name="mentioned" active="ENT.000003785"/>
                                    <!-- roosevelt -->
                                    <relation name="mentioned" active="ENT.000003328"/>
                                    <!-- ny times -->
                                    <relation name="mentioned" active="ENT.000003139"/>
                                    <!-- harper's -->
                                    <relation name="mentioned" active="ENT.000000251"/>
                                    <!-- nast -->
                                    <relation name="mentioned" active="ENT.000000941"/>
                                    <!-- grant -->
                                </listRelation>
                            </bibl>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>

                    <history>
                        <acquisition>This is an artificial collection created over time by HSP staff
                            mostly through donations and purchases of individual prints. It also
                            incorporates previously uncataloged materials collected by the Balch
                            Institute for Ethnic Studies. Some of the 20th century cartoons and
                            drawings were removed from the J. Hampton Moore papers (Collection
                            1541).</acquisition>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp key="art">Artist</resp>
                            <persName key="ENT.000003781">Brackmere</persName>
                        </respStmt>
                        <title type="main" level="a">The Modern Laocoon</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title type="marc245a" level="j"><orgName key="ENT.000003139">Harper's
                                Weekly</orgName></title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher><orgName key="ENT.000003540">Harper &amp;
                                Brothers</orgName></publisher>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <date from="1871-10-07">October 7, 1871</date>
                            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
                            <biblScope unit="issue">177</biblScope>
                            <biblScope unit="page">945</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Historic Images, New Technologies (HINT) project aims to enhance description
                    and discovery of the Historical Society of Pennsylvania's graphics materials and
                    promote the linking and sharing of content among institutions and scholars. The
                    project will result in an update to HSP's digital image viewer and an online
                    digital history exhibit that will demonstrate the new viewer's capabilities and
                    provide interpretive and contextual materials to encourage users to interact
                    with historical images in new ways. This project was funded by a grant from the
                    National Historical Publications and Records Commission's (NHPRC) Innovation in
                    Archives and Documentary Editing program.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="4">
                <p>This electronic file was created using manual keying following the
                    recommendations for Level 4 of "Best Practices for TEI in Libraries" guidelines
                    v3.0.</p>
                <p>This xml file uses unique entity identifiers, media file identifiers, and
                    collection identifiers in HSP's Digital Library, available at
                    http://digitallibrary.hsp.org.</p>

            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="italics">font-style: italic</rendition>
                <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="bold">font-weight: bold</rendition>
                <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="underline">text-decoration: underline</rendition>
                <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="crossed-through">text-decoration:
                    line-through</rendition>
                <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="printed"/>
                <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="typescript"/>
                <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="handwritten"/>
                <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="handwritten-underlined"/>
                <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="handwritten-circled"/>
                <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="handwritten-crossed-through"/>
                <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="double-underline"/>
                <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="stamp"/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef target="cartoons_genres.xml#clippings"/>
                <catRef target="cartoons_genres.xml#wood_engravings"/>
                <catRef target="cartoons_genres.xml#political_cartoons"/>
                <catRef target="cartoons_taxonomies.xml#reconstruction"/>
                <catRef target="cartoons_taxonomies.xml#press"/>
                <catRef target="cartoons_taxonomies.xml#culture"/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>

        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="RachelMoloshok" when="2015-06-03">Basic encoding</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <facsimile>
        <surface ulx="" uly="" lrx="" lry="">
            <graphic url="FIL.000094433"/>
            <zone n="1" xml:id="snakes"/>
            <zone n="2" xml:id="quote"/>
            <zone n="3" xml:id="signature"/>
            <zone n="4" xml:id="article"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>

    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="editorial_desc">
                <p>"Laocoön and His Sons" is a work of classical sculpture depicting the Greek
                    Trojan priest Laocoön and his two adolescent sons being attacked by deadly
                    snakes. This cartoon parodies the famous sculpture by substituting William
                    "Boss" Tweed (at center) as Laocoön and members of the infamous "Tweed Ring"
                    (New York City Mayor A. Oakey Hall at left and Richard B. Connolly and Peter B.
                    Sweeny at right) as his sons. The snakes encircling their bodies are labeled
                    "The Press." An accompanying article printed below the cartoons congratulates
                    the role of the press, especially the reporting of the <hi rendition="#italics"
                        >New York Times</hi> and the cartoons of Thomas Nast, published in <hi
                        rendition="#italics">Harper's Weekly</hi>, in exposing the corruption of the
                    Tweed Ring and bringing the wrongdoers to justice. This cartoon was published in
                    the October 7, 1871, supplement to <hi rendition="#italics">Harper's
                    Weekly</hi>.</p>
            </div>
        </front>

        <body>
            <div type="image_transcription" n="1" facs="#snakes">
                <head><supplied resp="editorial">Snakes</supplied></head>
                <p>THE PRESS</p>
                <p>THE PRESS</p>
                <p>THE PRESS</p>
            </div>
            <div type="image_transcription" n="2" facs="#quote">
                <head><supplied resp="editorial">Quote</supplied></head>
                <p><hi rendition="#italics">"They have stolen our ballots, have falsified the will
                        of the people, and have pulled away the very key-stone of the arch of
                        liberty."</hi>—ROBERT B. ROOSEVELT'S SPEECH, September 4, 1871, as reported
                    by the New York <hi rendition="#italics">Times.</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="image_transcription" n="3" facs="#signature">
                <head><supplied resp="editorial">Artist's signature</supplied></head>
                <p>BRACKMERE</p>
                <p>recit</p>
            </div>
            <div type="image_transcription" n="4" facs="#article">
                <head><supplied resp="editorial">Article</supplied></head>
                <p>"AMAZEMENT SEIZED ALL. THE GENERAL VOICE PROCLAIMED <hi rendition="#italics">THE
                        RING</hi> JUSTLY DOOMED TO DIE, SINCE IT HAD WITHSTOOD THE WILL OF THE <hi
                        rendition="#italics">GODDESS OF JUSTICE.</hi>"—VIRGIL ADAPTED.</p>
                <p>THE MODERN LAOCOON.</p>
                <p>Our artist has made an adaptation of the famous group of statuary in the Vatican
                    representing Laocoön and his sons struggling in the serpents' coils, as an apt
                    and striking illustration of the power of the newspaper press, displayed in
                    crushing the infamous Ring which has so long hold almost undisputed control of
                    New York. It is only a short time—it seems but yesterday—since the "Boss," as he
                    was called by his admirers, insolently defied public opinion, and when complaint
                    was made of his conduct, coolly remarked, "Well, what are you going to do about
                    it?" He would probably like to know, about this time, what <hi
                        rendition="#italics">he</hi> is "going to do about it!" For what public
                    opinion and the courts have failed to do has been accomplished by a vigorous
                    crusade by a portion of the press of this city against the intrenched
                    corruptionists of the Tammany Ring.</p>
                <p>There is no more signal instance in modern history of the power of moral
                    influence exerted through the columns of an honest and independent press. When
                    every other means had failed, when honest men of all parties had lost all hope
                    of shaking off the shackles of the Ring for years to come, a single bold
                    onslaught carried dismay and discomfiture into their ranks. Men who appeared to
                    have lost all sense of shame, as well as even the remembrance of public virtue,
                    quailed before the exposure of their villainies. The facts were so much worse
                    than the report, so patent and undeniable, that even the effrontery of the Ring
                    was at a loss. At first they affected to treat the whole matter as a joke, as
                    something that would soon "blow over." Then they gave out that an easy
                    explanation would soon appear, which would show that the exposures were no
                    exposures at all. But week after week went by without bringing forth the
                    promised explanation, and it became apparent that the guilty parties were only
                    waiting in hopes that the storm <hi rendition="#italics">would</hi> blow over as
                    they had prophesied. They imagined that a system of masterly inactivity would
                    accomplish their ends, and pleased themselves with the delusion that nothing
                    practical would come of it.</p>
                <p>The honest press of the city seeing, however, that its opportunity had come at
                    last, let no chance escape for dealing a blow at the Ring. Roused at length to
                    the necessity of action, the Tammany magnates exhibited all the madness that
                    usually characterizes those whom the gods wish to destroy. Their most foolish
                    movement was the attempt to frighten one of their chief assailants among the
                    newspapers by threatening to despoil its owners of their property—an attempt
                    which met with the ignominious failure it deserved. Then came the "burglary" of
                    the vouchers, the nice little plan to have Controller CONNOLLY sacrifice himself
                    to save his confederates, and finally Mayor HALL'S futile effort to counteract
                    the Controller's defensive strategy, by which the duties and responsibilities of
                    his office were transferred to one whose name represents what has for years been
                    the "rarest work of God" about the City Hall—an honest man.</p>
                <p>This great work, this achievement of reform in the very citadel of corruption, is
                    due entirely to the efforts of the honest press of New York, and it may well
                    feel proud of its triumph. It is due to the New York <hi rendition="#italics"
                        >Times</hi> to say that it was the first among the daily newspapers to
                    grapple with the enemy; and though able auxiliaries afterward joined in the
                    conflict, and rendered signal service in the common cause, it for some time
                    stood alone. In connection with this subject we may be permitted to refer with
                    pardonable pride to the effective cartoons of NAST and others, whose keen shafts
                    have been directed against Tammany from the vantage-ground of <hi
                        rendition="#italics">Harper's Weekly</hi>. We may safely say that they have
                    not proved the least effective weapons directed against the "unholy alliance,"
                    otherwise known as the Ring. Indeed, Mr. TWEED has been heard to affirm that he
                    didn't care half so much for what was written as what was drawn about him. In
                    conjunction, these allies have proved too strong for him and his confederates,
                    and have driven them discomfited from the field to their intrenchments, where
                    they will probably soon be clamoring for terms; but the only terms they will get
                    will be those offered by GRANT to the commander at Fort Donelson—"unconditional
                    surrender."</p>
            </div>

        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
