<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>

  <teiHeader xml:lang="English">

    <fileDesc>

      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">TEI transcription of letter from Leon Lewis to stockholders of Bank of
          Philadelphia and Trust Company</title>
        <author><persName>Lewis, Leon A.</persName></author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp key="trc">Transcribed by</resp>
          <persName>Dorman, Dana</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp key="pfr">Proofread by</resp>
          <persName>Charlton, Faith</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>

      <editionStmt>
        <p>First edition, <date when="2012">2012</date></p>
      </editionStmt>

      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Historical Society of Pennsylvania</publisher>
        <pubPlace>1300 Locust Street, Philadelphia, PA</pubPlace>
        <idno type="filename">5284-1959_b140f2_7_TEI.xml</idno>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Copyright 2012, The Historical Society of Pennsylvania. HSP makes a claim of copyright
            only to original contributions made by the Greenfield Digital Project participants and
            other staff. HSP makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is granted
            to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the text
            contributions to this work claimed by HSP for non-profit educational purposes, provided
            that this header is included in its entirety. For inquiries about commercial uses,
            please contact the Historical Society of Pennsylvania. HSP retains the rights of all
            images unless otherwise noted. Possession of an HSP digital image does not constitute
            permission to use or publish it. Requests for digital imaging, other reproduction
            services, and the intended use of reproductions must be made in writing to the Rights
            and Reproductions Coordinator at rnr@hsp.org.</p>
        </availability>
        <date when="2012"/>
      </publicationStmt>

      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="s" type="project">Greenfield Digital Project</title>
      </seriesStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository>The Historical Society of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA</repository>
            <collection>Albert M. Greenfield papers (Collection 1959)</collection>
            <idno type="citation">Box 140, Folder 2 "Bankers Trust Co. Correspondence, 1930"</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <msItem>
              <author><persName ref="Greenfield_project_people.xml#Lewis_Leon">Lewis, Leon
                  A.</persName></author>
              <gdp:recipient>Stockholders of <orgName
                  ref="Greenfield_project_organizations.xml#Bank_of_Phila">Bank of Philadelphia and
                  Trust Company</orgName></gdp:recipient>
              <title type="main" level="u">Letter from Leon Lewis to stockholders of Bank of
                Philadelphia and Trust Company</title>
              <bibl>
                <date from="1930-07-21">July 21, 1930</date>
                <extent>1 loose page</extent></bibl>
            </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <history>
            <acquisition>Gift of Albert M. Greenfield, 1968</acquisition>
          </history>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Greenfield Digital Project interprets the story of Bankers Trust Company, a large
          Philadelphia bank that failed in 1930, through a selection of primary source documents,
          contextual essays, and teacher resources. The project is part of a larger effort funded by
          the Albert M. Greenfield Foundation to make HSP's 20th-century holdings more
          accessible.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>This electronic file was created using manual keying following the recommendations for
          Level 4 of "Best Practices for TEI in Libraries" guidelines v3.0.</p>
        <p>We have generally encoded entire documents/texts, not excerpts. We have encoded page
          breaks. We have also preserved original spelling, typographical errors, missing text, and
          original capitalization. For clippings from newspapers or other publications, we have
          transcribed just the text related to the article, ignoring other text or markings on the
          page that were purposefully or inadvertently included during clipping. We have regularized
          spacing between words and sentences to replace double (or triple) spaces to a single
          space.</p>
        <p>We have not coded line breaks, end-of-line hyphenation, visual rendition of layout, font
          changes, or text alignment (left, right, center).</p>
        <p>Annotation on people and organizations coded in this document can be found in
          Greenfield_project_people.xml and Greenfield_project_organizations.xml.</p>
        <p>See project web site at www.hsp.org for full description of the editorial practices in
          the Greenfield Digital Project.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="italics">font-style: italic</rendition>
        <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="bold">font-weight: bold</rendition>
        <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="underline">text-decoration: underline</rendition>
        <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="crossed-through">text-decoration: line-through</rendition>
        <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="printed"/>
        <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="typescript"/>
        <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="handwritten"/>
        <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="handwritten-underlined"/>
        <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="handwritten-circled"/>
        <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="handwritten-crossed-through"/>
        <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="double-underline"/>
        <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="stamp"/>
        <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
        </namespace>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="Greenfield_project_genres.xml#correspondence"/>
        <catRef target="Greenfield_project_taxonomies.xml#trouble"/>
        <catRef target="Greenfield_project_taxonomies.xml#boom"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="DanaDorman" when="2012-11-12">Made proofreading changes, including updating
        schema.</change>
      <change who="FaithCharlton" when="2012-04-23">Updated to match schema revised 4/12/12, using
        Greenfield_schema7.xml.</change>
      <change who="DanaDorman" when="2011-08-03">Updated file to list DAMS file name
        details.</change>
      <change who="DanaDorman" when="2011-07-20">Updated file to link to revised schema,
        Greenfield_schema6.rnc.</change>
      <change who="DanaDorman" when="2011-06-07">Updated to match new schema,
        Greenfield_schema5.xml.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <facsimile>
    <graphic url="90;5284-1959_b140f2_7.tif"/>
  </facsimile>

  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="letterhead" rendition="#printed" n="1">
        <list>
          <item><persName ref="Greenfield_project_people.xml#Beury_Charles">DR. C. E.
              BEURY</persName>, CHAIRMAN OF THE BOARD</item>
          <item><persName ref="Greenfield_project_people.xml#Lewis_Leon">L. A. LEWIS</persName>,
            PRESIDENT</item>
          <item><persName ref="Greenfield_project_people.xml#Bull_TW">T. W. BULL</persName>,
            VICE-PRES. &amp; TREAS.</item>
        </list>
        <list>
          <item>CAPITAL $2,300,000</item>
          <item>SURPLUS $2,300,000</item>
        </list>
        <p><orgName ref="Greenfield_project_organizations.xml#Bank_of_Phila">BANK OF PHILADELPHIA
              <hi rendition="#underline">AND</hi> TRUST COMPANY</orgName></p>
        <p>PHILADELPHIA, PA.</p>
      </div>

      <div type="letter" rendition="#typescript" n="2">
        <opener><dateline><date when="1930-07-21">July 21, 1930</date>.</dateline>
          <salute>TO OUR STOCKHOLDERS:</salute></opener>

        <p>I am attaching copies of letters which have gone out to our depositors, as these letters
          best explain the step that has been taken, as of this date, by unanimous vote of your
          Board of Directors.<note type="editorial" n="1">Lewis and <persName
              ref="Greenfield_project_people.xml#Barker_Samuel">Samuel Barker</persName> sent a <ref
              target="5284-1959_b140f2_6_TEI.xml">letter on this date</ref> to depositors of both
            banks announcing the consolidation. Lewis also sent a <ref
              target="5284-1959_b140f2_5_TEI.xml">personal letter</ref> to "depositors and
            customers" explaining why he thought the consolidation made sense.</note></p>

        <p>To those of our stockholders who are not acquainted with the strength and favorable
          position of <orgName ref="Greenfield_project_organizations.xml#Bankers_Trust">Bankers
            Trust Company</orgName>, I would add that Bankers Trust Company has Capital, Surplus and
          Undivided Profits of approximately $7,500,000. This consolidation makes the deposits
          $50,000,000., and will bring the number of depositors to 138,000. We will be among the
          first ten banks in Philadelphia. Two offices of Bankers Trust Company will be discontinued
          and other economies will be possible, with resultant advantage to stockholders.</p>

        <p>Your officers and directors feel that the terms of consolidation will prove equitable for
          our stockholders and are in their best interest. When the figures are worked out, our
          stockholders will have the opportunity of exchanging the net worth of their stockholdings
          in Bank of Philadelphia for stock in Bankers Trust Company on the basis of the
            <sic>the</sic> then book value of the latter. Our interests are all with the
          consolidated institution. Our stockholders should follow the lead of their directors and
          give the consolidation unanimous support. More than that, we should endeavor to build into
          this great financial institution which is resulting from the consolidation, all the good
          will and value that can come from our earnest support. Bankers Trust Company of
          Philadelphia is splendidly equipped to handle every phase of modern banking business.</p>

        <p>I trust stockholders will particularly make it a point to call at our offices, which you
          will find even more attractive under this enlarged management, and strengthen by word and
          by action the good will which we desire this consolidation to carry. You will find
          enclosed a formal notice of the meeting of stockholders which is called for <date
            when="1930-08-12">August 12th</date>, but will be adjourned to and held on <date
            when="1930-08-18">August 18th</date>, to formally approve of the agreement of
          consolidation. Holders of a majority of the stock have already signified such approval. If
          you do not intend to be personally present, please return the enclosed proxy promptly.</p>

        <closer><salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
          <signed rendition="#handwritten">L. A. Lewis</signed></closer>

      </div>
    </body>

    <back/>
  </text>
</TEI>
