<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>

  <teiHeader xml:lang="English">

    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">TEI transcription of memo regarding liquidation of Bank of Philadelphia
          and Trust Company</title>
        <author>
          <persName>Unknown</persName></author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp key="trc">Transcribed by</resp>
          <persName>Dorman, Dana</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp key="pfr">Proofread by</resp>
          <persName>Charlton, Faith></persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>

      <editionStmt>
        <p>First edition, <date when="2012">2012</date></p>
      </editionStmt>

      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Historical Society of Pennsylvania</publisher>
        <pubPlace>1300 Locust Street, Philadelphia, PA</pubPlace>
        <idno type="filename">5284-1959_b140f2_4_TEI.xml</idno>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Copyright 2012, The Historical Society of Pennsylvania. HSP makes a claim of copyright
            only to original contributions made by the Greenfield Digital Project participants and
            other staff. HSP makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is granted
            to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the text
            contributions to this work claimed by HSP for non-profit educational purposes, provided
            that this header is included in its entirety. For inquiries about commercial uses,
            please contact the Historical Society of Pennsylvania. HSP retains the rights of all
            images unless otherwise noted. Possession of an HSP digital image does not constitute
            permission to use or publish it. Requests for digital imaging, other reproduction
            services, and the intended use of reproductions must be made in writing to the Rights
            and Reproductions Coordinator at rnr@hsp.org.</p>
        </availability>
        <date when="2012"/>
      </publicationStmt>

      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="s" type="project">Greenfield Digital Project</title>
      </seriesStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository>The Historical Society of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA</repository>
            <collection>Albert M. Greenfield papers (Collection 1959)</collection>
            <idno type="citation">Box 140, Folder 2 "Bankers Trust Co. Correspondence, 1930"</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <msItem>
              <author><persName>Unknown</persName></author>
              <title type="main" level="u">Memo regarding liquidation of Bank of Philadelphia and
                Trust Company</title>
              <bibl>
                <date from="1930-12-19">December 19, 1930</date>
                <extent>1 loose page</extent></bibl>
            </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <history>
            <acquisition>Gift of Albert M. Greenfield, 1968</acquisition>
          </history>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Greenfield Digital Project interprets the story of Bankers Trust Company, a large
          Philadelphia bank that failed in 1930, through a selection of primary source documents,
          contextual essays, and teacher resources. The project is part of a larger effort funded by
          the Albert M. Greenfield Foundation to make HSP's 20th-century holdings more
          accessible.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>This electronic file was created using manual keying following the recommendations for
          Level 4 of "Best Practices for TEI in Libraries" guidelines v3.0.</p>
        <p>We have generally encoded entire documents/texts, not excerpts. We have encoded page
          breaks. We have also preserved original spelling, typographical errors, missing text, and
          original capitalization. For clippings from newspapers or other publications, we have
          transcribed just the text related to the article, ignoring other text or markings on the
          page that were purposefully or inadvertently included during clipping. We have regularized
          spacing between words and sentences to replace double (or triple) spaces to a single
          space.</p>
        <p>We have not coded line breaks, end-of-line hyphenation, visual rendition of layout, font
          changes, or text alignment (left, right, center).</p>
        <p>Annotation on people and organizations coded in this document can be found in
          Greenfield_project_people.xml and Greenfield_project_organizations.xml.</p>
        <p>See project web site at www.hsp.org for full description of the editorial practices in
          the Greenfield Digital Project.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="italics">font-style: italic</rendition>
        <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="bold">font-weight: bold</rendition>
        <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="underline">text-decoration: underline</rendition>
        <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="crossed-through">text-decoration: line-through</rendition>
        <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="printed"/>
        <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="typescript"/>
        <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="handwritten"/>
        <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="handwritten-underlined"/>
        <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="handwritten-circled"/>
        <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="handwritten-crossed-through"/>
        <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="double-underline"/>
        <rendition scheme="other" xml:id="stamp"/>
        <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
        </namespace>
      </tagsDecl>

    </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="Greenfield_project_genres.xml#documents"/>
        <catRef target="Greenfield_project_taxonomies.xml#trouble"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="DanaDorman" when="2012-11-12">Made proofreading changes, including updating
        schema.</change>
      <change who="FaithCharlton" when="2012-04-23">Updated to match schema revised 4/12/12, using
        Greenfield_schema7.xml.</change>
      <change who="DanaDorman" when="2011-07-19">Updated to match new schema,
        Greenfield_schema6.xml.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <facsimile>
    <graphic url="90;5284-1959_b140f2_4.tif"/>
  </facsimile>

  <text>
    <body>

      <div type="memorandum" rendition="#typescript">

        <note><add rendition="#handwritten">From the <orgName
              ref="Greenfield_project_organizations.xml#Jewish_World">Jewish World</orgName> issue
            of <date when="1930-12-19">12/19/30</date></add></note>
        <head rendition="#underline">EXPLANATION WITH REGARDS TO THE LIQUIDATION OF THE <orgName
            ref="Greenfield_project_organizations.xml#Bank_of_Phila">BANK OF PHILADELPHIA AND TRUST
            COMPANY</orgName>.</head>

        <p>Through a regrettable Printer's error that crept into an article of news that appeared
            <sic>in <date when="1930-12-17">day before yesterday</date>'s</sic> issue of the "Jewish
          World" regarding the "Bank of Philadelphia and Trust Company", a mis-statement was made in
          connection with that Bank. It is, therefore, of great importance that the false statement
          that appeared in the news be corrected.</p>

        <p><date when="1930-07">July last</date>, the <orgName
            ref="Greenfield_project_organizations.xml#Bankers_Trust">Bankers Trust
          Company</orgName>, one of the largest Banks in Philadelphia, took over the job of
          liquidating all the resources of the Bank of Philadelphia and Trust Company, turning it
          into cash so that the Stockholders of the Bank of Philadelphia and Trust Company would
          receive the largest amount of cash for their stock. A short time ago the Bankers Trust
          Company sent a letter to the Stockholders of the Bank of Philadelphia and Trust Company
          advising them of the progress that was being made. The letter read as follows:</p>

        <p>"To the Stockholders of the Bank of Philadelphia and Trust Company:-</p>

        <p>The liquidation of the Bank of Philadelphia and Trust Company as it is being arranged and
          carried out by the Bankers Trust Company for your benefit, has reached a stage that it is
          now possible to give you information to which you are entitled.</p>

        <p>On <date when="1930-07-21">July 21st, 1930</date>, when your Bank ceased doing business,
          the Bankers Trust Company, in accordance with the agreement, paid the debts which your
          Bank owed to other Banks and also assumed the liability for all deposits that were then in
          your Bank. Your Bank at that time received from the Bankers Trust Company a loan of
          $17,962,247.82, for which amount the Bank of Philadelphia and Trust Company put up as
          security their assets worth $23,655,727.20. This loan represented a sum of money equal to
          the amount of money the Bank of Philadelphia and Trust Company owed to other Banks and to
          their depositors.</p>

        <p>Since then the assets of the Bank of Philadelphia and Trust Company, which were deposited
          with us, were turned into cash, the result being that your Bank has already paid us off
          $10,113,895.17 of the loan.</p>

        <p>The book worth of other assets of your Bank that still remain with us is $15,186,995.55,
          which consists of Securities, Loans on Collateral, Mortgages, Real Estate and Commercial
          Paper. Even though the biggest portion of these assets are good, however, a goodly part of
          the same are of doubtful worth, and it will require some time to liquidate in order to
          obtain the most cash <sic>therefor</sic>.</p>

        <p>After the liquidating process has been completed and your Bank pays us off the balance of
          our loan and all their other debts are paid, the balance will be turned back to you as
          Stockholders. How large your share will be cannot be known until the liquidation has been
          completed; however, taking into consideration what has already been accomplished, and from
          what information we have regarding Real Estate Appraisements and Loans, we can now say
          that you, the Stockholders, will receive much more than it was thought you could possibly
          receive some time ago.</p>

        <p>(Signed) <persName ref="Greenfield_project_people.xml#Barker_Samuel">SAMUEL H.
            BARKER</persName>, President, Bankers Trust Co. of Philadelphia."</p>

        <p>Naturally, the depositors,as well as the Stockholders of the Bank of Philadelphia and
          Trust Company, were highly satisfied that the Bankers Trust Company, one of the largest
          Banks of Philadelphia and a member of the <orgName
            ref="Greenfield_project_organizations.xml#Clearing_House">Clearing House
            Association</orgName>, undertook the above job, offering itself as a <sic>bulkwark</sic>
          of security for the best interests of all.</p>

      </div>
    </body>

    <back/>
  </text>
</TEI>
