<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="../../../../HSP%20digital%20project%20schemas/HSPDigitalProjectsSchema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">TEI description of organizations mentioned and depicted in the
                    Historic Images, New Technologies (HINT) Project</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ENT.000003526">Moloshok, Rachel</persName>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ENT.000003352">Newhouse, Sarah</persName>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ENT.000003528">Dorman, Dana</persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>

            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher><orgName key="ENT.000002473">Historical Society of
                    Pennsylvania</orgName></publisher>
                <pubPlace>1300 Locust Street, Philadelphia, PA</pubPlace>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright 2014, The Historical Society of Pennsylvania. HSP makes a claim of
                        copyright only to original contributions made by the Historic Images, New
                        Technologies (HINT) Project participants and other staff. Permission is
                        granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display
                        the text contributions to this work claimed by HSP for non-profit
                        educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.
                        For inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Historical Society
                        of Pennsylvania. HSP retains the rights of all images unless otherwise
                        noted. Possession of an HSP digital image does not constitute permission to
                        use or publish it. Requests for digital imaging, other reproduction
                        services, and the intended use of reproductions must be made in writing to
                        the Rights and Reproductions Coordinator at rnr@hsp.org.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2014"/>
            </publicationStmt>

            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project" key="CARTOONS">Historic Images, New Technologies
                    (HINT) Project</title>
            </seriesStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Historic Images, New Technologies (HINT) project aims to enhance description
                    and discovery of the Historical Society of Pennsylvania's graphics materials and
                    promote the linking and sharing of content among institutions and scholars. The
                    project will result in an update to HSP's digital image viewer and an online
                    digital history exhibit, featuring 500 encoded political cartoons, that will
                    demonstrate the new viewer's capabilities and provide interpretive and
                    contextual materials to encourage users to interact with historical images in
                    new ways. This project was funded by a grant from the National Historical
                    Publications and Records Commission's (NHPRC) Innovation in Archives and
                    Documentary Editing program.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="HSP" when="2014-08-26">Exported from Collective Access.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="ography">
                <listOrg>


                    <org xml:id="Congress">
                        <orgName key="ENT.000001431">U.S. Congress</orgName>
                    </org>

                    <org xml:id="Courier_NY">
                        <orgName key="ENT.000003317">New York Courier and Enquirer</orgName>

                    </org>

                    <org xml:id="Currier_Ives">
                        <orgName key="ENT.000000844">Currier and Ives</orgName>

                    </org>

                    <org xml:id="DP">
                        <orgName key="ENT.000003318">Democratic Party</orgName>
                    </org>

                    <org xml:id="EIC">
                        <orgName key="ENT.000000637">East India Company</orgName>
                    </org>

                    <org xml:id="Freedmens_Bureau">
                        <orgName key="ENT.000003319">Freedmen's Bureau</orgName>
                        <orgName type="alt">Bureau of Refugees, Freedmen, and Abandoned
                            Lands</orgName>
                        <note type="org"><p><persName ref="cartoons_people.xml#Lincoln_Abraham"
                                    >Abraham Lincoln</persName> established the Freedmen's Bureau
                                (also known as the Bureau of Refugees, Freedmen, and Abandoned
                                Lands), in <date when="1865">1865</date>, via the passing of the
                                Freedmen's Bureau Bill.</p></note>
                        <bibl>Wikipedia. "Freedmen's Bureau." <ref
                                target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freedmen's_Bureau"
                                >http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freedmen's_Bureau</ref> (accessed June
                            2, 2014).</bibl>
                    </org>

                    <org xml:id="HSP">
                        <orgName key="ENT.000002473">Historical Society of Pennsylvania</orgName>
                    </org>



                </listOrg>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
