<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="../../../TEI_exercise%20on%20ODDs/HSPDigitalProjectsSchema2.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:gdp="http://www.hsp.org/ns/nonTEI">

  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">TEI description of interpretive taxonomies for the NHPRC Cartoons Digital
          History Project Project</title>
        <author>
          <persName>Moloshok, Rachel</persName>
          <persName>Newhouse, Sarah</persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>

      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Historical Society of Pennsylvania</publisher>
        <pubPlace>1300 Locust Street, Philadelphia, PA</pubPlace>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Copyright 2013, The Historical Society of Pennsylvania. HSP makes a claim of copyright
            only to original contributions made by the NHPRC Political Cartoons Digital History
            Project participants and other staff. Permission is granted to download, transmit or
            otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the text contributions to this work claimed
            by HSP for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its
            entirety. For inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Historical Society of
            Pennsylvania. HSP retains the rights of all images unless otherwise noted. Possession of
            an HSP digital image does not constitute permission to use or publish it. Requests for
            digital imaging, other reproduction services, and the intended use of reproductions must
            be made in writing to the Rights and Reproductions Coordinator at rnr@hsp.org.</p>
        </availability>
        <date when="2013"/>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Historic Images, New Technologies (HINT) project aims to enhance description and
          discovery of the Historical Society of Pennsylvania's graphics materials and promote the
          linking and sharing of content among institutions and scholars. The project will result in
          an update to HSP's digital image viewer and an online digital history exhibit, featuring
          500 encoded political cartoons, that will demonstrate the new viewer's capabilities and
          provide interpretive and contextual materials to encourage users to interact with
          historical images in new ways. This project was funded by a grant from the National
          Historical Publications and Records Commission's (NHPRC) Innovation in Archives and
          Documentary Editing program.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="Cartoons_topics">

          <category xml:id="sh85106475">
            <catDesc>Presidents--United States--Election</catDesc>
            <!-- this should be subdivided by year. do we want to bother with that? -SN -->
          </category>
          <category xml:id="sh2010108614">
            <catDesc> Prohibition--United States--History</catDesc>
          </category>

          <category xml:id="sh2008110339">
            <catDesc>Racism--United States</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="sh85123326">
            <catDesc>Slavery--United States</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="n88126576">
            <catDesc> Stamp Act Congress (1765 : New York, N.Y.)</catDesc>
            <!-- best I could find for the Stamp Act -SN -->
          </category>
          <category xml:id="sh86007006">
            <catDesc>Temperance--United States</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="sh85140058">
            <catDesc>United States--Foreign relations</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="sh85140205">
            <catDesc>United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865</catDesc>
            <!-- http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85140205.html -->
          </category>
          <category xml:id="sh85140194">
            <catDesc>United States--History--War of 1812</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="sh85140410">
            <catDesc>United States--Politics and government</catDesc>
          </category>

        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <body>
      <p/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>