<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="file:/V:/Digital%20Editing/HSP%20digital%20project%20schemas/HSPDigitalProjectsSchema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">TEI description of organizations mentioned and depicted in the Historic
          Images, New Technologies (HINT) Project</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="ENT.000003526">Moloshok, Rachel</persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName key="ENT.000003352">Newhouse, Sarah</persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName key="ENT.000003528">Dorman, Dana</persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>

      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher><orgName key="ENT.000002473">Historical Society of
          Pennsylvania</orgName></publisher>
        <pubPlace>1300 Locust Street, Philadelphia, PA</pubPlace>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Copyright 2014, The Historical Society of Pennsylvania. HSP makes a claim of copyright
            only to original contributions made by the Historic Images, New Technologies (HINT)
            Project participants and other staff. Permission is granted to download, transmit or
            otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the text contributions to this work claimed
            by HSP for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its
            entirety. For inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Historical Society of
            Pennsylvania. HSP retains the rights of all images unless otherwise noted. Possession of
            an HSP digital image does not constitute permission to use or publish it. Requests for
            digital imaging, other reproduction services, and the intended use of reproductions must
            be made in writing to the Rights and Reproductions Coordinator at rnr@hsp.org.</p>
        </availability>
        <date when="2014"/>
      </publicationStmt>

      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="s" type="project" key="CARTOONS">Historic Images, New Technologies (HINT)
          Project</title>
      </seriesStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Historic Images, New Technologies (HINT) project aims to enhance description and
          discovery of the Historical Society of Pennsylvania's graphics materials and promote the
          linking and sharing of content among institutions and scholars. The project will result in
          an update to HSP's digital image viewer and an online digital history exhibit, featuring
          500 encoded political cartoons, that will demonstrate the new viewer's capabilities and
          provide interpretive and contextual materials to encourage users to interact with
          historical images in new ways. This project was funded by a grant from the National
          Historical Publications and Records Commission's (NHPRC) Innovation in Archives and
          Documentary Editing program.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="HSP" when="2015-04-22">Exported from Collective Access.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="ography">
        <listOrg>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003574">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003574">Albany Gazette</orgName>
            <note type="org"><p>Founded by brothers Alexander and James Robertson in November 1771,
                the <hi rendition="#italics">Albany Gazette</hi> was the first newspaper published
                in the New York colony outside of New York City. The Robertson brothers printed the
                Gazette for less than a year, as difficulties obtaining supplies, distributing the
                paper, and a lack of subscriptions overwhelmed the small operation; their last issue
                was published in August 1772. The brothers began their publication ambivalent about
                the impending conflict for American independence and their paper was largely devoid
                of content relating to political tensions. The <hi rendition="#italics">Albany
                  Gazette</hi> was resurrected after the Revolution in 1784 by another pair of
                brothers, Charles and George Webster. Under their direction, the <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Albany Gazette</hi> largely matched the general New York
                political leanings toward Federalism, and they reprinted 12 of the 85 Federalist
                papers in 1788. The <hi rendition="#italics">Albany Gazette</hi> ceased printing in
                1817.</p></note>
            <bibl><bibl>“About The Albany Gazette. (Albany, N.Y.) 1784-1817 Chronicling America
                Library of Congress.” Accessed April 20, 2015.
                http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030894/.</bibl>
              <bibl>Brennan, Denis P., "Open to All Parties: Alexander and James Robertson, Albany
                Printers, 1771-1777," <hi rendition="#italics">The Hudson Valley Regional
                  Review</hi> (March 1993), 25-39.
                http://www.hudsonrivervalley.org/review/pdfs/hvrr_10pt1_brennan.pdf</bibl>
              <bibl>“Charles R. Webster, New York State Museum.” Accessed April 20, 2015.
                http://www.nysm.nysed.gov/albany/bios/w/crwebster6841.html.</bibl>
              <bibl>“Publius in the Provinces: Where Was ‘The Federalist’ Reprinted Outside New York
                City? On JSTOR.” Accessed April 20, 2015.
                http://www.jstor.org/stable/1923310?seq=1#page_scan_tab_contents.</bibl>
              <bibl>Thomas, I., &amp; McCorison, M. A. (1970). <hi rendition="#italics">The history
                  of printing in America: With a biography of printers &amp; an account of
                  newspapers.</hi> New York: Weathervane Books.</bibl>
            </bibl>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003691">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003691">Arkell Publishing Company</orgName>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003326">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003326">Bank of the United States (1816-1836)<orgName type="alt"
                >Second Bank of the United States</orgName></orgName>
            <note type="org">The Second Bank of the United States was chartered by Congress in1816
              to perform essentially the same duties as the First Bank: to stabilize and unify the
              country’s economy. In its first eight years it was plagued by mismanagement,
              instability, and fraud. In 1823, Nicholas Biddle became the President of the Bank and
              gained control over a large portion of its functionality. However, Andrew Jackson was
              elected as President in 1828 on a largely anti-Bank platform, arguing that the Bank of
              the United States violated republican ideals. He vetoed the Bank’s early charter
              renewal in 1832, and it expired in 1836; most of its funds were moved to state banks,
              although Biddle converted the Bank to a state-chartered corporation in Pennsylvania
              just before its expiration. The Bank was eventually totally liquidated in 1841. The
              building of the Second Bank of the United States was designed by William Strickland,
              modeled on the Greek Parthenon. </note>
            <bibl><bibl> “American History From Revolution To Reconstruction and beyond, Second Bank
                of the United States (1816-1836) A Brief History of Central Banking in the United
                States - Edward Flaherty.” Accessed April 17, 2015.
                http://www.let.rug.nl/usa/essays/general/a-brief-history-of-central-banking/second-bank-of-the-united-states-(1816-1836).php.</bibl>
              <bibl> “Second Bank of the United States - Independence National Historical Park (U.S.
                National Park Service).” Accessed April 17, 2015.
                http://www.nps.gov/inde/learn/historyculture/places-secondbank.htm. </bibl></bibl>
            <note type="internal">depicted 11508;
              http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50082233.html</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003575">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003575">Boston Courier</orgName>
            <note type="org"><p>The <hi rendition="#italics">Boston Courier</hi> was the first daily
                newspaper printed in Boston, with its first issue published on March 2, 1824. The
                  <hi rendition="#italics">Boston Courier</hi> was founded, published, and edited by
                prominent Boston conservative Joseph T. Buckingham, who had gained notoriety for
                publishing the New England Galaxy and Masonic Magazine. The <hi rendition="#italics"
                  >Boston Courier</hi> was an early mouthpiece of the Whig Party and before that,
                the National Republicans; the paper spent a large portion of its early issues
                publishing pro-tariff editorial letters written by Buckingham. The newspaper was
                also notable for its “Geoponics” columns, published every Saturday, which gave
                readers useful information about farming practices and tools. The columns were
                distinct for a paper based in a large city. </p>
              <p>Buckingham sold out his shares in the paper in 1848, and his sons, Joseph H.
                Buckingham and Edwin Buckingham, who had been involved with the editing and
                publishing the paper since 1831, also abandoned the project to their longtime
                partner E.B. Foster. The paper changed hands and political profiles several times in
                the years leading up to the Civil War, becoming a conservative weekly paper in 1871.
              </p></note>
            <bibl><bibl>“About Boston Courier. ([Boston, Mass.]) 1824-1851, Chronicling America,
                Library of Congress.” Accessed April 20, 2015.
                http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84023099/.</bibl>
              <bibl>Buckingham, Joseph T. 1779-1861. <hi rendition="#italics">Personal Memoirs and
                  Recollections of Editorial Life</hi>. Boston: Ticknor, Reed, and Fields,
                1852.</bibl>
              <bibl>Hudson, Frederic. <hi rendition="#italics">Journalism in the United States From
                  1690 to 1872</hi>. New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1969.</bibl>
              <bibl>Thomas, I., &amp; McCorison, M. A. (1970). <hi rendition="#italics">The History
                  of Printing in America: With a biography of Printers &amp; an Account of
                  Newspapers</hi>. New York: Weathervane Books.</bibl></bibl>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003598">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003598">Cincinnati Gazette</orgName>
            <note type="org"><p>The <hi rendition="#italics">Cincinnati Gazette</hi> was founded as
                a weekly paper in July 1815 by publisher Thomas Palmer. Later that year, the <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Gazette</hi> merged with another newly-founded paper, <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Liberty Hall</hi> and <hi rendition="#italics">Cincinnati
                  Mercury</hi>, to publish as <hi rendition="#italics">Cincinnati Gazette and
                  Liberty Hall</hi>, and was owned and operated by Wesley Smead and S.S.
                L’Hommedieu. The paper published only weekly until 1827, when it became Cincinnati’s
                first daily paper, boasting new and modern printing technologies. Under the new and
                prominent editor Charles Hammond, the <hi rendition="#italics">Cincinnati
                  Gazette</hi> was published daily, and the <hi rendition="#italics">Cincinnati
                  Gazette and Liberty Hall</hi> continued to be published weekly. The <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Gazette</hi> was printed until late 1881. </p>
            </note>
            <bibl>“History of Cincinnati, Ohio, with Illustrations and Biographical Sketches : Ford,
              Henry A., Comp : Internet Archive.” Accessed March 25, 2015.
              https://archive.org/details/cu31924032193520.</bibl>
            <note type="internal">Chronicling america:
              http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85034482/</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003600">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003600">Colored Orphan Asylum and Association for the Benefit of
              Colored Orphans (New York, N.Y.)</orgName>
            <note type="org"><p>Founded by three white Quaker women in 1836, the New York Colored
                Orphan’s Asylum housed destitute African American orphans. Founders Anna and Hanna
                Shotwell and Mary Murry purchased a small building at 12th Street and Fifth Avenue
                in Manhattan, and began housing 11 black orphans rescued from almshouses. In 1843,
                the organization moved to larger house at 43rd and Fifth Avenue, which had a much
                larger capacity. </p>
              <p> In the summer of 1863, New York City saw the largest armed insurrection outside of
                the Civil War: the New York Draft Riots. The riots were fueled by underlying racial
                and class tensions in the city, and broke out after Congress passed new laws
                allowing men to pay $300 to hire a replacement. Beginning on July 13th a white,
                majority-Irish mob took to the streets and began burning buildings, smashing
                windows, and pulling up cobblestones in the streets. A mob seized the Orphan’s
                Asylum at around 4 PM, stealing everything of value, including donated infant's
                clothing, before setting the building ablaze. Overall in the draft riots that week,
                there were 120 deaths and 2000 people injured.</p>
              <p>All 233 children and in-house staff survived the attack, and the organization was
                forced to begin again on Randall’s Island (now Roosevelt Island), after all its
                assets were destroyed in the fire, an estimated loss of $80,000. The Asylum opened a
                new home in Harlem in 1867, and then relocated again to Riverdale, in the Bronx, in
                1907. It continues to exist today as Harlem-Dowling Children’s Services. </p></note>
            <bibl><bibl> “The Burning of the Colored Orphan Asylum, NYC | Jeffrey Kraus Antique
                Photographics.” Accessed March 25, 2015.
                http://antiquephotographics.com/the-colored-orphan-asylum-nyc/.</bibl>
              <bibl>“MAAP | Place Detail: Colored Orphan Asylum.” Accessed March 25, 2015.
                http://maap.columbia.edu/place/35.</bibl>
              <bibl> “The New York Draft Riots and the Burning of the Colored Orphan Asylum New-York
                Historical Society -.” Accessed March 25, 2015.
                http://blog.nyhistory.org/burning-of-orphan-asylum/.</bibl></bibl>
            <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2005009223.html. Est. 1836,
              burned during NYC draft riots of 1863; depicted in 11820</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003577">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003577">Columbian Centinel</orgName>
            <note type="org"><p>The <hi rendition="#italics">Columbian Centinel</hi> was a
                continuation of the <hi rendition="#italics">Massachusetts Centinel</hi> and the <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Republican Journal</hi>, first published by Benjamin Russell
                and William Warden in Boston, 1784. The publishers changed the paper’s name to <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Columbian Centinel</hi> to reflect their project taking on
                more national news, rather than Massachusetts-specific content; the first issue
                under that title was published on June 16, 1790. The <hi rendition="#italics"
                  >Columbian Centinel</hi> was fiercely Federalist and feuded with its rival, the
                anti-Federalist Boston Chronicle from 1790 to 1793. The <hi rendition="#italics"
                  >Columbian Centinel</hi> had the largest subscription base of any newspaper in
                Boston in the years after the Revolution, and successfully reported on the
                Napoleonic Wars in Europe as well as national and local news. </p>
              <p>As Federalism dissolved with the election of James Monroe in 1816, the influence of
                the <hi rendition="#italics">Columbian Centinel</hi> waned. It merged with the <hi
                  rendition="#italics">New England Palladium</hi> in 1830, and then again in 1836
                with the <hi rendition="#italics">Boston Gazette</hi>. It was finally bought out by
                the <hi rendition="#italics">Boston Daily Advertiser</hi> in 1840. </p>
            </note>
            <bibl><bibl>Hudson, Frederic. <hi rendition="#italics">Journalism in the United States
                  From 1690 to 1872</hi>. New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1969.</bibl></bibl>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003570">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003570">Commercial Advertiser</orgName>
            <note type="org"><p>Originally published by Noah Webster under the title <hi
                  rendition="#italics">American Minerva</hi>, the paper began as the <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Commercial Advertiser</hi> in September 1797 after a series
                of intermediate name changes. Webster ceased his work with the paper in 1803, and
                Zachariah Lewis took over as publisher. Under its two first publishers the <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Commercial Advertiser</hi> was strongly Federalist, and when
                Lewis sold the paper to William Stone (editor) and Francis Hall (publisher) in April
                1820, it remained loyal to DeWitt Clinton and the Federalist project to construct
                the Erie Canal. With Stone and Hall, the paper became known for publishing
                cutting-edge literary works by Robert Charles Sands, Lucretia and Margaret Davidson,
                and other prominent poets. </p>
              <p> In the election of 1828, the <hi rendition="#italics">Commercial Advertiser</hi>
                supported National Republican candidate John Quincy Adams, who lost to Andrew
                Jackson; even with a losing endorsement, the paper remained popular and moved to
                support the newly forming Whig Party. During these years, the <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Commercial Advertiser</hi> also gained notoriety for publicly
                feuding with novelist James Fennimore Cooper; along with a number of other papers,
                Cooper sued the paper in 1840 for libel over reviews of his books <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Home as Found</hi> and <hi rendition="#italics">History of
                  the Navy in the United States</hi>. Early in 1844, Stone left his editorship due
                to illness and died soon after; Francis Hall assumed his position. Leadership of the
                paper changed hands several times over the next decades, until the <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Commercial Advertiser</hi> was rebranded in 1904 as <hi
                  rendition="#italics">The Globe and Commercial Advertiser</hi>, popularly known as
                the <hi rendition="#italics">New York Globe</hi>. In 1923, Frank Munsey bought the
                paper and merged it with the <hi rendition="#italics">New York Sun</hi>. </p>
            </note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000000844">
            <orgName key="ENT.000000844">Currier &amp; Ives</orgName>
            <note type="org">
              <p>Perhaps the most famous and prolific lithography house, Currier and Ives was
                founded on Nassau Street in New York City in 1834 by Nathaniel Currier. Currier
                operated this print shop, with its factory around the corner on Spruce Street, for
                70 years. Currier enlisted self-trained artist James Merritt Ives in 1857 to create
                images for the firm. Under the new partnership, the business thrived; Currier and
                Ives innovated an assembly line-like factory floor, with a work flowing from
                artists, to lithographers, to letterers, to colorists in an efficient pattern.</p>
              <p>By the time the firm closed in 1907, they had a working catalog of over 7,000
                images in a variety of genres: popular news illustrations, political cartoons,
                celebrity portraits, sentimental images of families, children, and animals, as well
                as some copies of famous paintings. In the years after the Civil War, Currier and
                Ives also began printing “darktown comics,” cartoons depicting racist stereotypes of
                African-Americans. </p>
              <p>Business slowed for the firm at the turn of the 20th century, as costs dropped on
                photography and chromolithography, and hand-colored lithographs began to fall out of
                style. Currier and Ives had also suffered a myriad of personal tragedies over their
                careers and began to slow down. Just over a decade after the shop closed, after
                World War I, Currier and Ives prints came to be regarded as important pieces of
                Americana and became collectors’ items. </p></note>
            <bibl><bibl>“Currier And Ives Dark Town, Currier &amp; Ives America Could Be a Dark
                Place Art: Printmakers Gave Us Shiny, Happy Scenes of the Bucolic Life of the Haves,
                but Moralizing, Hatred Were There, Too,” Baltimore Sun, accessed March 3, 2015,
                http://articles.baltimoresun.com/1997-06-26/features/1997177066_1_currier-ives-ives-print-unintentionally-funny</bibl>
              <bibl>“Currier &amp; Ives, Printmakers to the American People,” accessed March 3,
                2015, http://www.tfaoi.com/aa/2aa/2aa36.htm</bibl></bibl>
            <note type="internal">LOC: http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126271</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003554">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003554">E. C. MacFarlane &amp; Co.<orgName type="alt">E. C.
                MacFarlane and Company</orgName></orgName>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000000637">
            <orgName key="ENT.000000637">East India Company</orgName>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003578">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003578">Evening Star</orgName>
            <note type="org"><p>Founded by Mordecai Manuel Noah in September 1833, the <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Evening Star</hi> was published in New York until August
                1840. Noah invited Thomas Gill, previously the business manager for <hi
                  rendition="#italics">The Evening Post</hi>, to handle the financial end of the <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Evening Star</hi>. Founded after Noah had a serious falling
                out with his once-ally President Jackson, the paper was an early promoter of Whig
                politics. It endorsed William Henry Harrison for President in 1836 through his loss
                to Martin Van Buren, and again in 1840, likely heavily influencing the outcome for
                Harrison in New York.</p>
              <p>Just after the 1840 elections, Gill passed away, and Noah was left unequipped to
                handle the paper’s business alone. He sold it to the Commercial Advertiser in late
                1840. </p></note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003667">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003667">Evening public ledger, 1914-1942 <orgName type="alt"
                >Evening public ledger and the evening telegraph </orgName></orgName>
            <note type="internal">Description in Chronicling Am:
              http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045211/</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003653">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003653">Evening telegraph </orgName>
            <note type="internal">Chronicling America:
              http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83025925/ </note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003683">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003683">Frank Leslie's Budget of Fun</orgName>
            <note type="internal">19th-century illustrated humor magazine, published by Frank
              Leslie.</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003053">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003053">Frank Leslie's illustrated newspaper</orgName>
            <note type="org">
              <p>Frank Leslie began his weekly illustrated newspaper in 1855, first edited by John
                Y. Foster. Printed on large quarto sized paper, each issue was 16 pages, and ran a
                mix of stories relating to war, politics, exploration, literature, and art,
                interspersed with detailed woodblock prints. As print and imaging technology
                progressed throughout the late 19th and early 20th century, <hi rendition="#italics"
                  >Leslie’s Illustrated</hi> began using daguerreotypes, and later, more advanced
                forms of photography for their illustrations. The paper became known for its images
                from the battlefields of the Civil War, and ran stories by prominent authors
                including Louisa May Alcott, Irving Hancock, Helen R. Martin, and Ellis Parker
                Butler. Its content was largely hawkish and patriotic, but was also followed for its
                coverage for other national events like the Klondike gold rush in 1897.</p>
              <p>Leslie died in 1880, and his wife, Miriam Florence Leslie took over the paper. In
                1902 she severed ties to <hi rendition="#italics">Leslie’s Illustrated</hi>,
                although it kept the Leslie name, as it was a long-established brand. <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Leslie’s Illustrated</hi> cycled through a series of names,
                all variations on the original—it became <hi rendition="#italics">Frank Leslie’s
                  Illustrated Weekly</hi> in 1891, <hi rendition="#italics">Leslie’s Illustrated
                  Weekly</hi> in 1894, <hi rendition="#italics">Leslie’s Weekly</hi> in 1901, back
                to <hi rendition="#italics">Leslie’s Illustrated Weekly</hi> in 1907, <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Leslie's</hi> in 1912, <hi rendition="#italics">Leslie’s
                  Illustrated Weekly Newspaper</hi> in 1914, and finally back to <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Leslie's</hi> in 1920, before it ceased publication in 1922.
              </p></note>
            <bibl><bibl>“About Frank Leslie’s Illustrated Newspaper. (New York, N.Y.) 1855-1891,
                Chronicling America Library of Congress.” Accessed April 8, 2015.
                http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86090491/.</bibl>
              <bibl>“Frank Leslie’s Weekly 1852-1922.” Accessed April 8, 2015.
                http://www.accessible-archives.com/collections/frank-leslies-weekly/.</bibl></bibl>
            <note type="internal">publisher of 11683</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003657">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003657">Gazette Times</orgName>
            <note type="internal">Chronicling Am:
              http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84024549/</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003540">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003540">Harper &amp; Brothers</orgName>
            <note type="org"><p> Harper &amp; Brothers was a publishing house founded as J.J. Harper
                in 1817. In 1833, the company changed its name to Harper &amp; Brothers, to Harper
                &amp; Row in 1962, and Harper Collins in 1990. Harper &amp; Brothers was
                headquartered on Pearl Street in Manhattan, New York, and began publishing <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Harper’s New Monthly Magazine</hi> in 1850. The company
                gradually added more publications, beginning with <hi rendition="#italics">Harper’s
                  Weekly</hi> in 1857, then <hi rendition="#italics">Harper’s Bazar</hi> in 1867,
                and <hi rendition="#italics">Harper’s Young People</hi> in 1879. Throughout its
                period of expanding periodical publication, Harper &amp; Brothers continued to
                publish books. </p>
              <p>In 1899, George B.M. Harvey became president of Harper &amp; Brothers. William
                Randolph Hearst bought <hi rendition="#italics">Harper’s Bazaar</hi> in 1913.
              </p></note>
            <bibl><bibl>“HARPER and BROS. REORGANIZE. - G.B.M. Harvey, Editor and Proprietor of The
                North American Review, Elected President of the Firm. - Front Page - NYTimes.com.”
                Accessed March 25, 2015.
                http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9505E2DB1530E132A25754C1A9679D94689ED7CF.</bibl></bibl>
            <note type="internal">Publishers of Harper's Weekly;
              http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50041511.html</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003611">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003611">J. Ottman Lithographic Company<orgName type="alt">Ottman
                Lithographic Company</orgName></orgName>
            <note type="internal">LOC: http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr95031115 LOC name
              authority record spells Ottman with one "n", but in the cartoon "If-The Inaugural
              Dinner at the White House" (DAMS 11687), it is spelled "Ottmann."</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003581">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003581">Journal of Commerce</orgName>
            <note type="org">
              <p>First printed in September 1827, New York City’s <hi rendition="#italics">Journal
                  of Commerce</hi> made its name intercepting incoming shipping vessels far off the
                shore in a schooner, taking note of their stock, and bringing the news to the harbor
                before it reached other papers so that merchants could prepare their bids. The <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Journal of Commerce</hi> was founded by Arthur Tappan, a silk
                merchant and prominent abolitionist. In 1840, Tappan turned control over the paper
                to Gereard Hallock and David Hale, editor and business manager respectively.</p>
              <p>The <hi rendition="#italics">Journal of Commerce</hi> was unique in its coverage of
                the Amistad case in 1839, as Tappan was spearheading the revolters’ defense; the
                paper is largely credited with keeping the incident central to the national news
                media’s focus. In 1840, it merged with the <hi rendition="#italics">New York
                  Gazette</hi> to gain stronger circulation base.</p>
              <p>Leading up to the Civil War, mirroring Hallock’s personal politics, the <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Journal of Commerce</hi> advocated for the abolition of
                slavery by legal means, taking a strong anti-war and states’ rights stance. Many
                Republicans who had previously supported the paper were angered, and under the
                Lincoln administration in 1861, Hallock was indicted for publishing material
                supportive of the Confederacy; additionally the Postmaster General refused to
                distribute the paper by mail. In order to placate the federal government, Hallock
                retired, selling his shares in the paper to David M. Stone and William Cowper Prime. </p>
              <p>The paper faced financial difficulties as printing technologies changed rapidly
                after the Civil War and commerce and business news increasingly came from the new
                Western states and territories, rather than New York Harbor. But the paper persists
                into the 21st century having undergone a series of mergers, and is now published
                daily as an online subscription-only paper.</p>
            </note>
            <bibl><bibl>Leach, Peter T. “Turning Back the Years.” <hi rendition="#italics">The
                  Journal of Commerce</hi>. United Business Media, 2005. 30 January 2015.
              </bibl></bibl>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003690">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003690">Judge</orgName>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003618">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003618">Kentucky Gazette, 1787-1848<orgName type="alt">Kentucke
                Gazette</orgName></orgName>
            <note type="org"><p><hi rendition="#italics">The Kentucke Gazette</hi> (later changed to
                  <hi rendition="#italics">Kentucky Gazette</hi>) was established in Lexington by
                John Bradford in 1787. It was the first newspaper printed in the Kentucky colony. In
                its early days, Bradford labored on the publication virtually alone, writing the
                content, setting the type, and printing it by hand, only later hiring an editorial
                and printing staff including his son, Daniel Bradford, in 1802. The paper’s early
                issues were often commented on the colony’s bid for independent statehood from
                Virginia, which it achieved in 1792; Bradford was then appointed the first public
                printer of the new state. Throughout his tenure on the paper, Bradford published
                “personal journalism,” commenting on his own experiences on the paper and in
                Lexington, and printed columns written by local personalities. Ownership of the <hi
                  rendition="#italics">The Kentucke Gazette</hi> was passed down through the
                Bradford family until it went defunct in 1848. </p></note>
            <bibl><bibl>Evans, Herndon J. <hi rendition="#italics">The Newspaper Press in
                  Kentucky</hi>. Lexington: The University Press of Kentucky, 1976.</bibl></bibl>
            <note type="internal">Also known as "Kentucke Gazette".</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003163">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003163">Keppler &amp; Schwarzmann<orgName type="alt">Keppler and
                Schwarzmann</orgName></orgName>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000000961">
            <orgName key="ENT.000000961">King &amp; Baird<orgName type="alt">King und
                Baird</orgName></orgName>
            <note type="org"><p>Founded in 1838 at 607 Sansom Street in Philadelphia, King and Baird
                Printers were among the largest print shops in the city. In its early years, Robert
                P. King and Alexander Baird were the only two employees of the firm, King working as
                compositor, solicitor, bookkeeper, foreman, proofreader, and purchaser, while Baird
                operated a single hand press. By the time of Baird’s death in 1868, the business had
                grown to include over 120 employees and 20 presses, some powered by steam. The firm
                was well known for publishing in German and other foreign languages including
                Swedish and Norwegian, as well as printing in the Cherokee syllabary, and in Grebo,
                a West African language. </p></note>
            <bibl><bibl>“American Dictionary of Printing and Bookmaking,” Google Books, accessed
                March 3, 2015,
                https://books.google.com/books?id=nuc-AAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA316&amp;lpg=PA316&amp;dq=robert+p.+king+philadelphia+printer&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=oeBSFr9nzJ&amp;sig=YUxvIrLUnU-FsvdjrFHUQpMXkw4&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=8dnwVJ7pAomjgwTZ0oFg&amp;ved=0CEEQ6AEwBw#v=onepage&amp;q=alexander
                baird&amp;f=false</bibl>
              <bibl>“Robert P King (1815 - 1868),” Find A Grave Photos, accessed March 3, 2015,
                http://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=pv&amp;GRid=68901464&amp;PIpi=41532436</bibl>
            </bibl>
            <note type="internal">LOC: http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr91044076.html</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003599">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003599">Ku Klux Klan<orgName type="alt">KKK</orgName></orgName>
            <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80076146.html (for
              19th-century KKK); depicted in 11820</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003557">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003557">Life</orgName>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003677">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003677">Lincoln Young Men's Wide Awake Club<orgName type="alt">Wide
                Awakes</orgName></orgName>
            <note type="internal">depicted in 12332;
              http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n99049259.html</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003582">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003582">Lithography of Imbert</orgName>
            <note type="org"><p> Anthony Imbert began a lithography company on Murray Street in New
                York City in 1825, and gained notoriety for producing the plates for <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Memoir</hi>, a commemorative book by Cadwallader D. Colden
                celebrating the completion of the Erie Canal. The 35 plates in <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Memoir</hi> showed a variety of new lithographic techniques,
                and the book’s text proclaimed Imbert’s relatively new lithography business “the
                most prominent in New York,” which was very likely an exaggeration. Imbert gained
                notoriety as a lithographer of landscapes, and flourished as the Hudson River School
                style and interest in New York scenes gained notoriety.</p>
              <p> Imbert began lithographing music scores in 1827, and caricatures and satirical
                images in 1828; between 1828 and his death in 1834 he issued 19 cartoons, more than
                double that of any other publisher in the country. </p></note>
            <bibl><bibl>Colden, Cadwallader D. <hi rendition="#italics">Memoir, prepared at the
                  request of a committee of the Common Council of the city of New York, and
                  presented to the mayor of the city, at the celebration of the completion of the
                  New York canals.</hi> New York: Corp. of New York, 1825. </bibl>
              <bibl>Gross, Robert A. and Mary Kelly.<hi rendition="#italics"> An Extensive Republic:
                  Print, Culture, and Society in the New Nation, 1790-1840.</hi> Chapel Hill: UNC
                Press Books, 2010. </bibl>
              <bibl>Tatham, David. <hi rendition="#italics">Prints and Printmakers of New York
                  State, 1825-1940.</hi> Syracuse: Syracuse University Press, 1986. </bibl></bibl>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003620">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003620">Meridian (MS) Mercury</orgName>
            <note type="org"><p> The <hi rendition="#italics">Meridian Mercury</hi> was a paper
                published in Meridian, Mississippi by Colonel Alexander Grice Horn. He began the <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Mississippi Star</hi> in 1836, another eastern Mississippi
                paper, before founding the Mercury. Horn was the editor and primary writer for the
                paper, and was a staunch Democrat, unwaveringly supportive of the Confederate cause
                during the Civil War. Horn also allegedly had ties to the Ku Klux Klan, and was
                arrested on charges of riot, riotous homicide, and arson during the 1871 Meridian
                race riots, although he was never indicted or charged.</p>
              <p>Horn did not allow the financial department to have any bearing on editorial
                content of the Mercury, and when he died in 1886, the paper followed, apparently
                unable to become sustainable.</p>
            </note>
            <bibl><bibl>“Ancestors of Colonel Alexander Grice Horn Sr.” Accessed March 25, 2015.
                http://freepages.genealogy.rootsweb.ancestry.com/~talbotfamilyhistory/3657.htm.</bibl>
              <bibl>“Editors I Have Known Since the Civil War: rewritten and Reprinted from Robert
                Hiram Henry - Google Books.” Accessed March 25, 2015.
                https://books.google.com/books?id=PFEOAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA55&amp;lpg=PA55&amp;dq=colonel+ag+horn&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=JoocvDq62Tsig=K-1Zh2XQeI-0HDsb9tsXIcD1xFA&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=MEQMVZDOMsWhNuGjgMAH&amp;ved=0CCQQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=colonel
                ag horn&amp;f=false.</bibl>
            </bibl>
            <note type="internal">Mentioned in 11820;
              http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85034453/; Newspaper published in Meridian,
              Mississippi</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003597">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003597">National Advocate<orgName type="alt">The National advocate,
                for the country</orgName></orgName>
            <note type="internal">Early newspaper referenced in 11738. See
              http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030516/</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003619">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003619">National Gazette, 1791-1793</orgName>
            <note type="org"><p>Founded in Philadelphia by poet and printer Philip Freneau, the <hi
                  rendition="#italics">National Gazette</hi> began publishing in October 1791. The
                paper was conceived of by Thomas Jefferson and his Democratic-Republican colleagues
                to combat the <hi rendition="#italics">Federalist Gazette</hi> of the United States.
                From the start, the paper was purely an organ of the Democratic - Republican Party;
                Freneau was a college friend of James Madison’s, and the paper was almost totally
                bankrolled by Jefferson. Additionally, George Washington and his administration,
                along with Alexander Hamilton, repeatedly accused of Jefferson dictating the paper’s
                content, although Freneau denied these allegations under oath. Madison himself wrote
                numerous essays published by the Gazette anonymously. The paper was virulent in
                attacking Adams and the Federalists, including Washington whenever he sided with
                Federalists in a debate, repeatedly accusing the party of Toryism, and warning of
                monarchical tendencies. Freneau went as far as to call Washington’s 61st birthday
                party “a forerunner of other monarchical vices.” The <hi rendition="#italics"
                  >National Gazette</hi> informally ceased printing in October 1793, during the
                Yellow Fever epidemic in Philadelphia. A few months later, Jefferson resigned from
                his position as Washington’s Secretary of State, dissipating Freneau’s funding for
                the paper. </p>
            </note>
            <bibl><bibl>Hudson, Frederic. <hi rendition="#italics">Journalism in the United
                  States</hi>. New York: Harper &amp; Brothers, 1873. </bibl>
              <bibl>“National Gazette” <hi rendition="#italics">George Washington’s Mount
                  Vernon</hi>, accessed February 23, 2015,
                http://www.mountvernon.org/research-collections/digital-encyclopedia/article/national-gazette/.</bibl></bibl>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003628">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003628">National Intelligencer</orgName>
            <note type="org"><p>Following the <hi rendition="#italics">Independent Gazetteer</hi> of
                Philadelphia, the <hi rendition="#italics">National Intelligencer</hi> was founded
                in 1800, when the federal government moved from Philadelphia to Washington D.C. It
                was first owned by Samuel Harrison Smith, who was soon replaced by Joseph Gales and
                William Winston Seaton. Under Seaton and Gales, the Intelligencer became a
                stenographic paper, recording and publishing debates taking place on the floor of
                Congress and the House of Representatives. The paper remained popular through the
                Madison administration, but its offices were partially destroyed during the British
                occupation of Washington in the War of 1812; however, this only spurred the paper on
                to more patriotic popularity.</p>
              <p> The <hi rendition="#italics">Intelligencer</hi> operated as the organ of all of
                the federal administrations until Andrew Jackson’s election in 1828, when it sided
                with the Whig party, and featured essays and columns written by the strongest voices
                of the opposition: Henry Clay, Daniel Webster, and even John Calhoun, Jackson’s Vice
                President. However, as a partisan paper, the <hi rendition="#italics"
                  >Intelligencer</hi> steadily declined in popularity; it was debt-ridden by the end
                of the Civil War, and was bought by Alexander del Mar in 1869. He then merged it
                with the <hi rendition="#italics">Washington Express</hi>.</p></note>
            <bibl><bibl>“Geo. P. Rowell &amp; Co’s American Newspaper Directory, Containing Accurate
                Lists of All the Newspapers and Periodicals Published in the United States and
                Territories, and the Dominion of Canada, and British Colonies of North America;
                Together with a Description of the Towns and Cities in Which They Are Published,
                1872, Page: 518” UNT Digital Library, accessed March 3, 2015,
                http://digital.library.unt.edu/ark:/67531/metadc9262/m1/517/ </bibl>
              <bibl>Hudson, Frederic. <hi rendition="#italics">Journalism in the United States</hi>.
                New York: Harper &amp; Brothers, 1873.</bibl>
            </bibl>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003317">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003317">New York Courier and Enquirer</orgName>
            <note type="org"><p>The <hi rendition="#italics">New York Courier and Enquirer</hi>
                formed in 1829 with the merger of James Watson Webb’s <hi rendition="#italics">New
                  York Morning Courier</hi> and the <hi rendition="#italics">New-York Enquirer</hi>,
                edited by Mordecai Noah. Webb assumed editorship over the new paper, and after
                hiring associate editor James Gordon Bennett, it became an early mouthpiece of the
                Democratic Party. The <hi rendition="#italics">New York Courier and Enquirer</hi>
                gained fame in 1830 for setting up a pony express system to bring memos from
                Washington D.C. to the New York City newspapers. </p>
              <p>However, as Jacksonian populism lost steam with the growing business class in New
                York, the paper began to support Henry Clay’s burgeoning National Republicanism.
                Webb and the <hi rendition="#italics">New York Courier and Enquirer</hi> were
                founding tenets of the new party, and the paper became one of the most powerful in
                the country. As part of the party machine, it sparked ferocious debate in the U.S.
                House of Representatives in its 1837-1838 sessions: Kentucky congressman William J.
                Graves challenged a Maine Democratic congressman, Jonathan Cilley, to a duel after
                Cilly criticized the Courier and Enquirer on the House floor. It ended with Graves
                shooting Cilley to death. </p>
              <p>The <hi rendition="#italics">New York Courier and Enquirer</hi> went into decline
                with the Whig party, as the country moved towards greater unrest. The paper, which
                had always supported slavery, fell out of favor as many New Yorkers and other
                Northerners began to become more earnestly interested in abolition. With the
                election of President Lincoln in 1861 and the onset of the Civil War, the paper
                merged with the <hi rendition="#italics">New York World</hi>. </p></note>
            <note type="internal">published by James Watson Webb; mentioned in 11561; possibly
              mentioned in 11738</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003541">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003541">New York Herald</orgName>
            <note type="org"><p> The <hi rendition="#italics">New York Herald</hi> was first
                published on May 6th 1835, by James Gordon Bennett Sr., a former schoolteacher and
                Scottish immigrant. After years as a journalist in New York City, he rose to become
                the assistant editor of the <hi rendition="#italics">New York Courier</hi> and <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Enquirer</hi> in 1823, and then quickly founded his own
                paper. The <hi rendition="#italics">New York Herald</hi> became known for its
                salacious subject matter, which some critics found to be lowbrow; Bennett himself
                asserted that the paper’s mission was “not to instruct but to startle.” The paper
                was sold at a lower price than its competitors, and was edited to be consumed by the
                general public. It became the highest circulated and most profitable paper in the
                country. </p>
              <p>Bennett’s <hi rendition="#italics">Herald</hi>, was pioneering in several areas,
                running the first newspaper interview ever, which was in conjunction with the <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Herald</hi>’s high-profile coverage of the murder of Helen
                Jewett. He also conducted the first ever exclusive interview with a US
                President—Martin Van Buren. Additionally, Bennett was the first to use the industry
                standard of taking cash from advertisers in advance, rather than waiting for their
                adverts to run. </p>
              <p>Bennett’s politics were essentially conservative—he was a Democrat and
                anti-abolitionist, anti-Catholic, and anti-immigrant. The paper remained supportive
                of the Democratic Party throughout the Civil War, but backed the Union cause.</p>
              <p>In 1866, Bennett’s son, James Gordon Bennett Jr., assumed control of the paper.
                Bennett Jr. used the <hi rendition="#italics">Herald</hi> to finance several
                high-profile trans-continental explorations, including Henry Morton Stanley’s
                expeditions to Africa in 1871, and George W. DeLong’s expedition to the arctic. He
                also infamously ran the New York Zoo hoax in 1874, in which almost an entire day’s
                paper was devoted to a wholly fabricated story about wild animals escaping from the
                Central Park Zoo and goring several people. Fine print at the end of the issue
                stated that the story was a fiction, and Bennett tried to assuage critics by arguing
                that the issue was meant to highlight inadequate safety precautions at the zoo. </p>
              <p>The <hi rendition="#italics">New York Herald</hi> acquired its smaller rival, the
                  <hi rendition="#italics">New York Tribune</hi>, after Bennett Jr.’s death in 1924,
                and published as the <hi rendition="#italics">New York Herald-Tribune</hi>. It
                ceased publication in 1966.</p></note>
            <bibl><bibl>“Abraham Lincoln and New York - James Gordon Bennett (1795-1872).” Accessed
                April 8, 2015.
                http://www.mrlincolnandnewyork.org/inside.asp?ID=32&amp;subjectID=3.</bibl>
              <bibl>“Bennett’s New York Herald and the Rise of the Popular Press - 1989, Page Iii by
                James L. Crouthamel. | Online Research Library: Questia.” Accessed April 8, 2015.
                https://www.questia.com/read/22960927/bennett-s-new-york-herald-and-the-rise-of-the-popular.</bibl>
              <bibl> “HarpWeek Abraham Lincoln Cartoons.” Accessed April 8, 2015.
                http://www.abrahamlincolncartoons.info/SubPages/Biography.php?UniqueID=7.</bibl></bibl>
            <note type="internal">depicted in 11578.xml&#13;
              http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2002162950.html</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003328">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003328">New York Times</orgName>
            <note type="internal">depicted in 11578.xml; changed display name from "The New York
              Times" to "New York Times" to aid alphabetical indexing in HINT project digital
              exhibit</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003329">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003329">New York Tribune</orgName>
            <note type="internal">mentioned in 11561.xml; 11564.xml; depicted 11578 (as
              giraffe)</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003596">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003596">New-York American<orgName type="alt">The American, for the
                country</orgName></orgName>
            <note type="internal">Newspapers "NY American" and "American" referenced in
              Jacksonian-era political cartoons 11508 and 11738. See
              http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030019/ for details on this title and
              preceeding/succeeding iterations.</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003556">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003556">North American</orgName>
            <note type="internal">http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84024584/</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000001300">
            <orgName key="ENT.000001300">Pennsylvania Gazette</orgName>
            <note type="org"><p>This prominent Pennsylvania newspaper was first published on
                Christmas Eve 1728 by Samuel Keimer as <hi rendition="#italics">The Universal
                  Instructor in all Arts and Sciences: and Pennsylvania Gazette</hi>. Keimer’s
                original intent was to print a page of <hi rendition="#italics">Ephraim Chambers’
                  Cyclopaedia</hi>, or <hi rendition="#italics">Universal Dictionary of Arts and
                  Sciences</hi> in every issue; however, after nine months of printing he had less
                than 100 subscribers. On October 2, 1729, Benjamin Franklin and Hugh Meredith bought
                the paper and shortened the name to the Pennsylvania Gazette. Franklin and Meredith
                gained a reputation and a large subscriber base, and after Franklin was appointed
                postmaster, the paper overtook Bradford’s Mercury for the largest circulation in
                Philadelphia. </p>
              <p>The partners separated in 1732, and Franklin began to publish the paper once a week
                rather than bi-weekly. The <hi rendition="#italics">Pennsylvania Gazette</hi>
                published the first American political cartoon on May 9, 1754, with the iconic Join
                or Die image of a snake cut into pieces, referencing the colonies need to unite in
                the face of European power in the midst of the Seven Years War. The paper remained
                prominent in Philadelphia and is best known for its coverage of the precluding
                sentiment to the American Revolution, as well as its reporting on the war itself.
                The <hi rendition="#italics">Pennsylvania Gazette</hi> ceased publication in 1800,
                ten years after Franklin’s death.</p></note>
            <bibl><bibl>Hudson, Frederic. <hi rendition="#italics">Journalism in the United
                  States</hi>. New York: Harper &amp; Brothers, 1873. </bibl>
              <bibl>“The Pennsylvania Gazette 1728-1800.” Accessed April 17, 2015.
                http://www.accessible-archives.com/collections/the-pennsylvania-gazette/.</bibl></bibl>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003671">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003671">Pennsylvanian</orgName>
            <note type="internal">newspaper that existed in 1833; mentioned in 11508</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000000572">
            <orgName key="ENT.000000572">Philadelphia Inquirer</orgName>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000000435">
            <orgName key="ENT.000000435">Philadelphia Public Ledger</orgName>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000000437">
            <orgName key="ENT.000000437">Philadelphia Record</orgName>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003655">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003655">Phunny Phellow</orgName>
            <note type="org"><p>Founded in 1859 by popular New York publishers Street &amp; Smith,
                  <hi rendition="#italics">Phunny Phellow</hi> was an inexpensive and popular comic
                magazine, known for printing a high volume of cartoons. It distinguished itself from
                rivals by running half of its pages with woodcut cartoons, while similar papers
                relied on prose jokes. <hi rendition="#italics">Phunny Phellow</hi> was known for
                running on low-quality paper, its poor engravings, and plagiarized jokes, but it was
                the first to regularly run cartoons by Thomas Nast, who was simultaneously but
                intermittently submitting cartoons to high-brow publications like <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Harper’s Weekly</hi>. Nast was contracted to illustrate <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Phunny Phellow</hi>’s front page, back page, and center
                spread each month, although he did not sign his illustrations for the publication,
                explaining that he didn’t want to be associated with its poor engraving quality.
                Still, Nast was allowed ample room at <hi rendition="#italics">Phunny Phellow</hi>
                to develop his skills as a cartoonist. Nast terminated his contract at the comic
                magazine when he was offered on at <hi rendition="#italics">Harper’s Weekly</hi> in
                1873. <hi rendition="#italics">Phunny Phellow</hi> ceased publication in
              1879.</p></note>
            <bibl><bibl>“A History of American Magazines, 1850-1865 - Frank Luther Mott - Google
                Books.” Accessed April 8, 2015.
                https://books.google.com/books?id=lm7rSZ2BoK8C&amp;pg=PA184&amp;lpg=PA184&amp;dq="phunny+phellow"+street+and+smith&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=5obNPtzf9Q&amp;sig=0nabWc7CZ0_21sWb3vM39e8_KWc&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=QHkZVaq6BYyZgwT3k4Ao&amp;ved=0CDEQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q="phunny
                phellow" street and smith&amp;f=false.</bibl>
              <bibl>“Cartoonist Thomas Nast vs. Candidate Horace Greeley Content Page.” Accessed
                April 8, 2015.
                http://nastandgreeley.harpweek.com/subpages/cartoon-1872-MediumA.asp?UniqueID=1&amp;Year=background.</bibl>
              <bibl>“Illustrated Civil War Newspapers &amp; Magazines.” Accessed April 8, 2015.
                http://www.lincolnandthecivilwar.com/SubLevelPages/PhunnyPhellow.asp.</bibl></bibl>
            <note type="internal">illustrated humor magazine, 1859-1876; publisher of 12347. Thomas
              Nast was a cartoonist (anonymous and unsigned)</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003658">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003658">Pittsburgh Commercial Gazette Inc.</orgName>
            <note type="internal">http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84024549/&#13; &#13;
              publisher of Gazette Times</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003668">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003668">Public Ledger Co.</orgName>
            <note type="internal">publisher of evening public ledger. cartoon Dams ID 12262</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000000384">
            <orgName key="ENT.000000384">Puck</orgName>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003323">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003323">Punch, or the London Charivari</orgName>
            <note type="org"><p>One of the most famous and long-running satirical magazines of all
                time, <hi rendition="#italics">Punch</hi> was founded in London by Ebenezer Landells
                and Henry Mayhew in 1841. Early on, the magazine modeled itself on the French paper
                  <hi rendition="#italics">Le Charivari</hi>, and with the desire to be less bitter
                and more literary than contemporary British humor magazines. <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Punch</hi> initially struggled with subscriptions, until it
                began to publish with the prominent Bradbury and Evans house. At the start of its
                heyday, it was a politically radical, supporting labor and critical of the upper
                class. But as the 1860s progressed, it earned its conservative reputation by keeping
                consistent with the values of the rising middle class and expanding British Empire
                under Queen Victoria. </p>
              <p><hi rendition="#italics">Punch</hi> employed the most prominent British cartoonists
                of the day, including Leech, Keene, du Maurier, and Tenniel, and the staff developed
                a particular culture and method of producing the magazine. Perhaps the most famous
                aspect of the staff culture was the “Punch Table”—a large oblong table at which the
                staff would eat decadent lunches, drink wine, and smoke cigars. Only after the meal
                was thoroughly enjoyed did the editor convene the meeting by yelling out,
                “Gentleman, the cartoon!” Artists would then begin pitching their ideas.</p>
              <p><hi rendition="#italics">Punch</hi> is credited with coining the word “cartoon”
                itself, in 1843.</p>
              <p>Circulation was at its highest in 1940 with 175,000 subscribers. <hi
                  rendition="#italics">Punch</hi> only began to stagnate in the 1970s, with
                circulation dropping to desperate levels in the ‘80s. It closed in 1992, and came to
                a brief revival from 1996-2002, but was eventually closed again due to a poor
                subscription base. </p></note>
            <bibl><bibl> “About Punch Magazine, Punch Cartoons, Cartoon History,” Punch Magazine
                Cartoon Archive,” accessed March 3, 2015, http://www.punch.co.uk/about/</bibl>
              <bibl>“Whack! Whack! Whack! Reborn Punch Pounded,” NYTimes.com, accessed March 3,
                2015,
                http://www.nytimes.com/1996/09/18/world/whack-whack-whack-reborn-punch-pounded.html
              </bibl></bibl>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003635">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003635">Punchinello</orgName>
            <note type="org"><p><hi rendition="#italics">Punchinello</hi> was a short-lived national
                American satirical magazine, founded in New York City April, 1870 by the former
                editors of <hi rendition="#italics">Vanity Fair</hi>—Henry Louis Stephens and
                William Allen Stephens. In early 1870, they received financial backing from Jay
                Gould, Jim Fisk, William M. “Boss” Tweed, and Peter B. Sweeny, all men involved in
                Tammany Hall politics and corruption in New York City. <hi rendition="#italics"
                  >Punchinello's</hi> financial backers remained anonymous, but because of their
                involvement, the comedy magazine couldn’t print material explicitly mocking or
                derisive of the most prominent and powerful New Yorkers, rendering the magazine
                somewhat politically impotent. </p>
              <p>Much like the British <hi rendition="#italics">Punch</hi>, for which it was
                explicitly modeled and named, <hi rendition="#italics">Punchinello</hi> was a
                sixteen-page quarto magazine featuring one full page cartoon. Probably because of
                its inability to be totally politically relevant, <hi rendition="#italics"
                  >Punchinello</hi> folded after 9 months of printing due to poor sales, in December
                of 1870.</p>
            </note>
            <bibl><bibl>“A History of American Magazines, 1865-1885 - Frank L. Mott - Google Books.”
                Accessed April 9, 2015.
                http://books.google.com/books?id=zt1V-ISXFsoC&amp;pg=PA440#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false.</bibl></bibl>
            <note type="internal">illustrated comic magazine; publisher of 11747</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003672">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003672">Punchinello Publishing Company</orgName>
            <note type="org"><p>Punchinello Publishing Company was founded in April 1870 alongside
                the only magazine it published, <hi rendition="#italics">Punchinello</hi>. The
                publisher was located at 83 Nassau Street, New York City, and likely folded with the
                magazine about 9 months after its inception, in December 1870. </p></note>
            <bibl><bibl>“Plymouth Pulpit: A Weekly Publication of Sermons Preached by Henry Ward
                Beecher - Henry Ward Beecher - Google Books.” Accessed April 9, 2015.
                https://books.google.com/books?id=wLnRAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA153&amp;lpg=PA153&amp;dq="punchinello+publishing+co"&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=sFVOTilpmk&amp;sig=gAeS77_owaOtBFyizrI5oHaK1rA&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=MkokVdPaPIK4ggTBhIHQCA&amp;ved=0CEMQ6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q="punchinello
                publishing co"&amp;f=false.</bibl>
              <bibl>“The Project Gutenberg eBook of Punchinello Vol. 2, No. 27.” Accessed April 9,
                2015. http://www.gutenberg.org/files/10035/10035-h/10035-h.htm.</bibl></bibl>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003621">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003621">Richmond Whig</orgName>
            <note type="org"><p>Founded in Richmond, Virginia in 1842, the <hi rendition="#italics"
                  >Richmond Whig</hi> was the primary organ of the Whig Party in Virginia. It was
                one of four daily papers in the city and remained loyal to the Whigs during
                secession, although the party was largely defunct. The paper was therefore more
                critical of Jefferson Davis and his administration from the get-go of the
                Confederacy, perceiving Davis’ mistrust of Whigs in the Confederate army and
                elsewhere.</p>
              <p>The<hi rendition="#italics">Richmond Whig</hi> continued to print in several
                different iterations through the end of the Civil War and Reconstruction; it ceased
                publication in 1888. </p></note>
            <bibl><bibl> “About Richmond Daily Whig. (Richmond, Va.) 1842-1861 « Chronicling America
                « Library of Congress.” Accessed April 9, 2015.
                http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84024656/. </bibl>
              <bibl> “About Daily Richmond Whig. (Richmond, Va.) 1861-1862 « Chronicling America
                « Library of Congress.” Accessed April 9, 2015.
                http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86071866/.</bibl>
              <bibl>“About Richmond Whig. (Richmond, Va.) 1862-1865 « Chronicling America « Library
                of Congress.” Accessed April 9, 2015.
                http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84024669/. </bibl>
              <bibl> “About Daily Richmond Whig. (Richmond, Va.) 1865-1869 « Chronicling America
                « Library of Congress.” Accessed April 9, 2015.
                http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84024660/.</bibl>
              <bibl>“About Richmond Daily Whig. (Richmond, Va.) 1869-1885 « Chronicling America
                « Library of Congress.” Accessed April 9, 2015.
                http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84024668/.</bibl>
              <bibl>“About Richmond Whig. (Richmond, Va.) 1886-1888 « Chronicling America « Library
                of Congress.” Accessed April 9, 2015.
                http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86071867/. </bibl>
              <bibl>“Newspapers in Virginia During the Civil War, Confederate.” Accessed April 9,
                2015.
                http://www.encyclopediavirginia.org/Newspapers_in_Virginia_During_the_Civil_War_Confederate.</bibl></bibl>
            <note type="internal">Newspaper published in Richmond, VA, mentioned in 11820; see
              chroniclingamerica.loc.gov for details</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003688">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003688">Sackett &amp; Wilhelms Litho. &amp; Prt. Co.<orgName
                type="alt">Sackett &amp; Wilhelms Lithographing Corporation</orgName></orgName>
            <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no00092199</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003327">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003327">Sons of Liberty</orgName>
            <note type="internal">depicted 2562-Bb612L615_1_TEI.xml (Liberty Triumphant) &#13;
              http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50071988.html</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003626">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003626">Standard Oil Company</orgName>
            <note type="internal">LOC: http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79053083</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003627">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003627">Swain, Abell &amp; Simmons</orgName>
            <note type="internal"> http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr2003020764 </note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003639">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003639">The Illustrated American</orgName>
            <note type="internal">Published cartoon, "The Silence of Matt Quay" (DAMS #11737),
              unable to find much information about this publication. See
              http://www.worldcat.org/title/illustrated-american-magazine/oclc/10048433.</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003640">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003640">The Illustrated American Publishing Company</orgName>
            <note type="internal">Published "The Illustrated American," which featured the cartoon,
              "The Silence of Matt Quay" (DAMS #11737), unable to find much information about this
              publication. See
              http://www.worldcat.org/title/illustrated-american-magazine/oclc/10048433.</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003622">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003622">The Jefferson (TX)</orgName>
            <note type="internal">Jefferson (TX) newspaper, mentioned in 11820; could be "Jefferson
              Jimplecute," "Jefferson News," or various other local publications.</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003604">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003604">United States Gazette</orgName>
            <note type="org">
              <p>The <hi rendition="#italics">United States Gazette</hi> was a daily newspaper
                (except Sunday) published in Philadelphia from 1823-1847. The paper underwent a
                series of ownership and editorship changes in the decades leading up to its merger
                with the <hi rendition="#italics">North American</hi>, another prominent
                Philadelphia newspaper, to become, in 1847, the <hi rendition="#italics">North
                  American and United States Gazette</hi>.</p>
            </note>
            <bibl><bibl>“About The United States Gazette. (Philadelphia [Pa.]) 1823-1847,
                Chronicling America  Library of Congress,” accessed February 11, 2015,
                http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84026283/.</bibl></bibl>
            <note type="internal">See chronicling america:
              chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84026283/</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000000382">
            <orgName key="ENT.000000382">Wasp (San Francisco, Calif.)<orgName type="alt">San
                Francisco Illustrated Wasp</orgName></orgName>
            <note type="internal">LOC: http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2007069903</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003632">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003632">Wevill &amp; Hammar</orgName>
            <note type="org"><p>George Wevill and George Hammar (alt. Hammer) were a wood engraving
                partnership in New York City at 208 Broadway. The business flourished in the
                1870s.</p>
            </note>
            <bibl>
              <bibl>“Punchinello - Google Books.” Accessed April 9, 2015.
                https://books.google.com/books?id=56tDAQAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA130&amp;lpg=PA130&amp;dq=wevill+&amp;+Hammar+wood+engravers&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=yCkDQYK2BS&amp;sig=FOybkKoOZe3NTBX3TbloDCk04i4&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=2DEkVaLWGsursAWDpoDwDQ&amp;ved=0CCUQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=wevill
                &amp; Hammar wood engravers&amp;f=false.</bibl></bibl>
            <note type="internal">engravers of 11747; wood engraving firm of George D. Hammar and
              George Wevill)</note>
          </org>
          <org xml:id="ENT.000003608">
            <orgName key="ENT.000003608">World (New York, N.Y. : 1860-1931)<orgName type="alt">New
                York World</orgName></orgName>
            <note type="internal">mentioned in 11820</note>
          </org>
        </listOrg>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
