<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<?xml-model href="../../../../HSP%20digital%20project%20schemas/HSPDigitalProjectsSchema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">TEI description of people mentioned and depicted in the Historic
                    Images, New Technologies (HINT) Project</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ENT.000003526">Moloshok, Rachel</persName>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ENT.000003352">Newhouse, Sarah</persName>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ENT.000003528">Dorman, Dana</persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>

            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher><orgName key="ENT.000002473">Historical Society of
                    Pennsylvania</orgName></publisher>
                <pubPlace>1300 Locust Street, Philadelphia, PA</pubPlace>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright 2014, The Historical Society of Pennsylvania. HSP makes a claim of
                        copyright only to original contributions made by the Historic Images, New
                        Technologies (HINT) Project participants and other staff. Permission is
                        granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display
                        the text contributions to this work claimed by HSP for non-profit
                        educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.
                        For inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Historical Society
                        of Pennsylvania. HSP retains the rights of all images unless otherwise
                        noted. Possession of an HSP digital image does not constitute permission to
                        use or publish it. Requests for digital imaging, other reproduction
                        services, and the intended use of reproductions must be made in writing to
                        the Rights and Reproductions Coordinator at rnr@hsp.org.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2014"/>
            </publicationStmt>

            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project" key="CARTOONS">Historic Images, New Technologies
                    (HINT) Project</title>
            </seriesStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Historic Images, New Technologies (HINT) project aims to enhance description
                    and discovery of the Historical Society of Pennsylvania's graphics materials and
                    promote the linking and sharing of content among institutions and scholars. The
                    project will result in an update to HSP's digital image viewer and an online
                    digital history exhibit, featuring 500 encoded political cartoons, that will
                    demonstrate the new viewer's capabilities and provide interpretive and
                    contextual materials to encourage users to interact with historical images in
                    new ways. This project was funded by a grant from the National Historical
                    Publications and Records Commission's (NHPRC) Innovation in Archives and
                    Documentary Editing program.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="HSP" when="2014-08-26">Exported from Collective Access.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="ography">
                <listPerson>


                    <person xml:id="ENT.000003331">
                        <persName>
                            <forename type="first">John</forename>
                            <surname>Bell</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1796">1796</birth>
                        <death when="1869">1869</death>
                    </person>


                    <person xml:id="ENT.000000447">
                        <persName>
                            <forename type="first">Abraham</forename>
                            <surname>Lincoln</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1809">1809</birth>
                        <death when="1865">1865</death>
                        <note type="biography">
                            <p>Abraham Lincoln served as president of the United States from 1861
                                until his assassination in 1865. He married <persName
                                    ref="cartoons_people.xml#Lincoln_Mary_Todd">Mary Todd
                                    Lincoln</persName> in <date when="1842">1842</date>.</p>
                        </note>
                    </person>

                    <person xml:id="ENT.000000011">
                        <!-- this is for testing online; not actually part of the HINT project -->
                        <persName><forename type="first"
                            >William</forename><surname>Still</surname></persName>
                        <sex>M</sex>
                        <birth when="1821">1821</birth>
                        <death when="1902">1902</death>
                        <note type="biography"><p>William Still was born in Burlington County, New
                                Jersey, near Medford. His parents were both former slaves who
                                escaped from their masters before William was born. Much of his
                                childhood and young adult life was spent as a farmhand in New Jersey
                                before he moved to Philadelphia in <date when="1844">1844</date>.
                                There he took on odd jobs until he finally established himself as a
                                clerk for the Pennsylvania Anti-Slavery Society in <date when="1847"
                                    >1847</date>.</p>
                            <p>Also in <date when="1847">1847</date>, William married Letitia George
                                and they had four children. Letitia was a dressmaker who, for
                                additional income, took boarders into the Still home in
                                Philadelphia. She was a strong supporter of her husband's
                                anti-slavery work and eventually witnessed and oversaw the
                                transformation of her household from a home and boarding house into
                                a frequent stop for fugitive slaves on the Underground Railroad in
                                Philadelphia. The famous Henry "Box" Brown, for example, spent two
                                nights in the Still home. By the latter half of the nineteenth
                                century, however, Letitia's primary occupation concerned the
                                business of running her household as the need to provide shelter for
                                escaped slaves waned and the Still family was, by then, wealthy (one
                                writer indicates that Still's "personal fortune was nearly $1
                                million" at the time of his death in <date when="1902">1902</date>).
                                The Still children likewise benefited from the family's financial
                                security and their parents' ambition and dedication to social
                                causes. Caroline Still, the eldest of the Still children, attended
                                Oberlin College in Ohio and went on to become one of the first
                                African American female physicians in Pennsylvania. She was an
                                advocate for temperance, education, and the improvement of the
                                conditions of the poor among other causes.</p>
                            <p>Though William Still himself was mostly self-educated, he excelled as
                                a clerk at the Pennsylvania Anti-Slavery Society, was eventually
                                appointed secretary and chairman of the Vigilance Committee in <date
                                    when="1852">1852</date>, and kept meticulous records of that
                                committee's efforts throughout the 1850s. His book, <hi
                                    rendition="#italics">The Underground Rail Road</hi>, published
                                in <date when="1872">1872</date>, and his "Journal C" (which
                                included records of the committee's finances), are the definitive
                                sources regarding the Vigilance Committee's efforts. During his time
                                working with the Pennsylvania Anti-Slavery Society, William was
                                reunited with his brother, Peter, who had been kidnapped and sold
                                into slavery forty years before the brothers' reunion. William
                                Still's work, then, connected him with his own family, thousands of
                                fugitive slaves, abolitionists, and many of the most prominent
                                figures in Philadelphia, and, indeed, the United States.</p>
                            <p>Despite his ambitious work on the Underground Railroad and for the
                                Vigilance Committee, Still took on additional causes and occupations
                                beyond abolition. He protested against racial discrimination in
                                Philadelphia's railroad cars, organized a Young Men's Christian
                                Association (YMCA) for young blacks, and served on the Freedman's
                                Aid Commission which offered assistance to newly-freed African
                                Americans after the U.S. Civil War. After ending his employment with
                                the Pennsylvania Anti-Slavery Society in <date when="1861"
                                    >1861</date>, Still also sold stoves and coal in Philadelphia
                                and was, by his later years and until his death in <date when="1902"
                                    >1902</date>, a successful businessman.</p>
                        </note>
                        <bibl>Calarco, Tom. <hi rendition="#italics">People of the Underground
                                Railroad: A Biographical Dictionary</hi>. Westport, CT and London:
                            Greenwood Press, 2008.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Temple University Libraries. "William Still: An African-American
                            Abolitionist." <ref
                                target="http://stillfamily.library.temple.edu/people-and-places/still-william"
                                >http://stillfamily.library.temple.edu/people-and-places/still-william</ref>
                            (accessed 11/4/2013).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Temple University Libraries. "Biography of Caroline Still Anderson."
                                <ref
                                target="http://stillfamily.library.temple.edu/historical-perspective/biography-caroline-still-ander"
                                >http://stillfamily.library.temple.edu/historical-perspective/biography-caroline-still-ander</ref>
                            (accessed 11/4/2013).</bibl>
                    </person>

                    <person xml:id="ENT.000003382">
                        <persName>
                            <forename type="first">John</forename>
                            <surname>Stuart</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName type="alt">
                            <addName type="honorific">Third Earl of Bute</addName>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1713">1713</birth>
                        <death when="1792">1792</death>
                    </person>


                </listPerson>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
