<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="file:/V:/Digital%20Editing/HSP%20digital%20project%20schemas/HSPDigitalProjectsSchema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">TEI description of people mentioned and depicted in the Historic
                    Images, New Technologies (HINT) Project</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ENT.000003526">Moloshok, Rachel</persName>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ENT.000003352">Newhouse, Sarah</persName>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ENT.000003528">Dorman, Dana</persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>

            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher><orgName key="ENT.000002473">Historical Society of
                    Pennsylvania</orgName></publisher>
                <pubPlace>1300 Locust Street, Philadelphia, PA</pubPlace>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright 2014, The Historical Society of Pennsylvania. HSP makes a claim of
                        copyright only to original contributions made by the Historic Images, New
                        Technologies (HINT) Project participants and other staff. Permission is
                        granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display
                        the text contributions to this work claimed by HSP for non-profit
                        educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.
                        For inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Historical Society
                        of Pennsylvania. HSP retains the rights of all images unless otherwise
                        noted. Possession of an HSP digital image does not constitute permission to
                        use or publish it. Requests for digital imaging, other reproduction
                        services, and the intended use of reproductions must be made in writing to
                        the Rights and Reproductions Coordinator at rnr@hsp.org.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2014"/>
            </publicationStmt>

            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project" key="CARTOONS">Historic Images, New Technologies
                    (HINT) Project</title>
            </seriesStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Historic Images, New Technologies (HINT) project aims to enhance description
                    and discovery of the Historical Society of Pennsylvania's graphics materials and
                    promote the linking and sharing of content among institutions and scholars. The
                    project will result in an update to HSP's digital image viewer and an online
                    digital history exhibit, featuring 500 encoded political cartoons, that will
                    demonstrate the new viewer's capabilities and provide interpretive and
                    contextual materials to encourage users to interact with historical images in
                    new ways. This project was funded by a grant from the National Historical
                    Publications and Records Commission's (NHPRC) Innovation in Archives and
                    Documentary Editing program.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="HSP" when="2015-07-06">Exported from Collective Access.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="ography">
                <listPerson>
<person xml:id="ENT.000002503">
  <persName key="ENT.000002503">
    <forename type="first">John</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Quincy</forename>
    <surname type="last">Adams</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1767">1767</birth>
  <death when="1848">1848</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>John Quincy Adams was the 6th president of the United States, serving from 1825 to 1829. Born in Braintree, Massachusetts, he was the son of John Adams, the 2nd president of the United States, and Abigail Adams. A  multilingual, Harvard-educated attorney, diplomat, and legislator, John Quincy Adams served as US minister to the Netherlands and Prussia before being elected to the Massachusetts State and then the US Senate in 1803, serving until 1808. He then was appointed ambassador to Russia (1809-1814) by President Madison. Adams, furthermore, assisted Madison in negotiating the Treaty of Ghent, which brought about the end of the War of 1812. As secretary of state under President Monroe (1817-1825) Adams was instrumental in shaping the Monroe Doctrine, acquiring the Floridas from Spain, and negotiating joint US-British occupation of the Oregon territory.</p>
<p>In 1824, Adams was one of five contenders for the US presidency, running against Andrew Jackson, John Calhoun, William H. Crawford, and Henry Clay. Adams carried the Northeast, but Jackson beat Adams in both popular and electoral votes. No candidate, however, won a majority of electoral votes. Consequently, the US House of Representatives decided the election. Speaker of the House Henry Clay supported Adams, who won the presidency. Following his inauguration, Adams appointed Clay as secretary of state, prompting Jackson's supporters to accuse him of having struck a "corrupt bargain" in order to gain the presidency. In the subsequent presidential election of 1828, Adams lost to Jackson, becoming the first US president not to be elected to a second term. Adams retired briefly to farm life in Massachusetts but was elected to House of Representatives in 1830, where he served until his death in 1848, at age 80.</p></note>
  <bibl>"John Quincy Adams," biography at WhiteHouse.gov, accessed June 8, 2015. <ref target="https://www.whitehouse.gov/1600/presidents/johnquincyadams">Link</ref></bibl>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79140988.html; depicted in 11738</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000000729">
  <persName key="ENT.000000729">
    <forename type="first">James</forename>
    <surname type="last">Akin</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1773">1773</birth>
  <death when="1846">1846</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">Copperplate and wood engraver, miniaturist, caricaturist, profilist, and designer; worked primarily in Philadelphia, but also in Salem and Newburyport, Mass., 1804-1808.</note>
  <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File. <ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr94028751.html">Link</ref></bibl>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003707">
  <persName key="ENT.000003707">
    <surname type="last">Alexander III, Emperor of Russia</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1845">1845</birth>
  <death when="1894">1894</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in Hint cartoon #12151</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003680">
  <persName key="ENT.000003680">
    <forename type="first">Marcus</forename>
    <surname type="last">Antonius</surname>
    <addName type="alt">Mark Antony</addName>
  </persName>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">mentioned in 12338; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50051933.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003560">
  <persName key="ENT.000003560">
    <forename type="first">Chester</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Alan</forename>
    <surname type="last">Arthur</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1829">1829</birth>
  <death when="1886">1886</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">Chester Alan Arthur was a United States Vice President and President.  He was born on October 5, 1829 in Fairfield, Vermont.   He taught secondary school and later became a lawyer in New York City.  In 1871 President Ulysses S. Grant appointed Arthur to serve as Collector of the New York Customhouse.  In 1878 President Rutherford B. Hayes sought to reform the party and to end the practice of political patronage and so, he fired Arthur and accused the Customhouse of political corruption and patronage.   Two years later, the Republicans, seeking to gain support of the Stalwarts, nominated Arthur as James A. Garfield’s running mate.  After President Garfield was assassinated in 1881, Arthur became president, broke ties with Stalwarts, and began to enact civil service reform.   As President, Arthur worked to modernize the United States Navy and invested in the construction of steam-powered engines.  He also supported lower tariffs and signed the Tariff Act of 1883.  During Arthur’s Administration, the Chinese Exclusion Act of 1882 was enacted.  It denied citizenship to Chinese immigrants and banned them from entering the United States.  The law was finally repealed in 1943.  During his presidency, Arthur became ill with kidney disease and lost the Republican nomination for the 1884 election to James Blaine.  He died on November 18, 1886.</note>
  <bibl> <bibl>“21. Chester Alan Arthur-The Presidents. WGBH American Experience.  PBS.” Accessed May 5, 2015. <ref target="http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/americanexperience/features/biography/presidents-arthur/">Link</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl>“Presidents of the United States (POTUS).” Accessed May 5, 2015.  <ref target="http://www.ipl.org/div/potus/caarthur.html">Link</ref>
                </bibl>
<bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). <hi rendition="#italics"> Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age</hi>. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe.</bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50002601.html
</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003692">
  <persName key="ENT.000003692">
    <forename type="first">Joseph</forename>
    <forename type="middle">E.</forename>
    <surname type="last">Baker</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1837">1837</birth>
  <death when="1914">1914</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Joseph E. Baker was a lithographer and cartoonist, perhaps best known for his 1860 portrait of Abraham Lincoln drawn after his nomination as the Republican presidential candidate. Baker was born in about 1837 in Bangor, Maine, and moved to Boston by 1857, where he apprenticed at John H. Bufford’s lithographic firm. He became Bufford’s principal illustrator of sheet music. During the Civil War, Baker drew many political cartoons, primarily of the war itself. Baker worked for Bufford until Bufford’s death in 1870, while also working for other Boston firms. For Forbes and Company, Baker drew many playbills and advertisements. He eventually joined the firm of Armstrong &amp; Company. He remained active until 1888 and died in Danvers, Massachusetts in 1914.</p></note>
  <bibl> <bibl>Ancestry.com. <hi rendition="#italics">Massachusetts Marriage Records, 1840-1915</hi> [database online]. Provo, UT: Ancestry.com Operations, Inc., 2013</bibl>
                <bibl>Falk, Peter Hastings et al., eds. <hi rendition="#italics">Who Was Who in American Art, 1564-1975: 400 Years of Artists in America, vol. 1, A-F</hi>. Madison, CT: Sound View Press, 1999.</bibl>
                <bibl>1860 Federal Census, Boston, Ward 12, Suffolk, MA</bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">artist of 12331; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr92007310.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003561">
  <persName key="ENT.000003561">
    <forename type="first">Thomas </forename>
    <forename type="middle">Francis</forename>
    <surname type="last">Bayard</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1828">1828</birth>
  <death when="1898">1898</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Thomas Francis Bayard was born on October 29, 1828 in Wilmington, Delaware and was a diplomat and lawyer.  From 1863-1864 he served as the US attorney for Delaware.  In 1865 he represented Delaware in the US Senate, and then left his post in 1885 to become the Secretary of State during Grover Cleveland’s first administration.  During Cleveland’s second administration, Bayard was appointed Ambassador of Great Britain.  He died in Massachusetts on September 28, 1898. </p></note>
  <bibl> <bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). <hi rendition="#italics"> Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age</hi>. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe.</bibl>
                <bibl>“Thomas Francis Bayard, Office of the Historian.” Accessed May 5, 2015. <ref target="https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/people/bayard-thomas-francis"
                    >Link</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl>“Thomas Francis Bayard Biography, United States Statesman, Encyclopedia Britannica.” Accessed May 5, 2015. <ref target="http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/56741/Thomas-Francis-Bayard">Link</ref></bibl>
</bibl>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003729">
  <persName key="ENT.000003729">
    <forename type="first">Joseph</forename>
    <surname type="last">Bayley</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1775">1775</birth>
  <death when="1836">1836</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr2004036048.html; depicted 11824 (one of the doctors)</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003331">
  <persName key="ENT.000003331">
    <forename type="first">John</forename>
    <surname type="last">Bell</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1796">1796</birth>
  <death when="1869">1869</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>John Bell was a US Representative and Senator from Tennessee. Born near Nashville, Tennessee, in 1796, he worked as a lawyer in Franklin, Tennessee, and served as a member of the Tennessee State Senate before being elected to the US House of Representatives in 1827. He served seven terms in the House (1827-1841), during which time he served one term as Speaker of the House (1833-1835) and chaired the Committee on Indian Affairs and Committee on the Judiciary. Initially a Jacksonian Democrat, Bell switched his loyalties and joined the Whig party during the 1830s. He was appointed by President William Henry Harrison as Secretary of War in 1841 but resigned later that year, after John Tyler, who became president following Harrison's death, refused to adopt a Whig agenda. Bell was later elected to the US Senate, serving two terms (1847-1859) during which time he changed party affiliations repeatedly, serving as, respectively, a member of the Whig, Opposition, and Know-Nothing parties.</p>
<p>In 1860, Bell changed his party affiliation yet again, becoming the presidential candidate for the newly founded Constitutional Union Party. The Constitutional Union Party officially took no position on slavery, declaring that it endorsed "no political principle other than the Constitution . . . the Union . . . and the Enforcement of the Laws." Their slogan was "No North, no South, no East, no West. Nothing but the Union." Bell was a Southern slaveholder but had opposed the expansion of slavery in the 1850s and did not support secession, arguing that it was unnecessary because the US Constitution already protected slavery.
The Constitutional Unionists did not believe they could win the election outright; their strategy was to gain votes that might otherwise go to other, stronger candidates. If no candidate in the 1860 presidential race won the number of electoral votes necessary to win the election, the decision would go to members of the House of Representatives, giving Bell would have a stronger chance of success. Seeing Lincoln as the biggest threat, supporters of the Constitutional Union Party created "fusion tickets" that combined the non-Republican candidates (besides Bell, these were John C. Breckinridge of the Southern Democratic Party and Stephen Douglas of the Democratic Party) into a single-candidate ticket in some strategically important states. Most support for the Bell came from Southern states in which slavery was legal, and he carried the border states of Kentucky, Tennessee, and Virginia. Ultimately, Lincoln won the election.</p>
<p>Although he had initially opposed secession, Bell  supported the Confederacy after the outbreak of the Civil War. He died at his home near Cumberland Furnace, Tennessee, in 1869.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>"Bell, John, (1796-1869)," Biographical Directory of the United States Congress, 1774-Present, accessed June 8, 2015. <ref target="http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=B000340">Link</ref></bibl>
<bibl>National Park Service, "The Election of 1860: Constitutional Union Party," accessed June 8, 2015. <ref target="http://www.nps.gov/arho/upload/Constitutional-Union.pdf">Link</ref></bibl>
</bibl>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 11561; 11563; http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=B000340; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n87887395.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003636">
  <persName key="ENT.000003636">
    <forename type="first">Frank</forename>
    <surname type="last">Bellew</surname>
    <addName type="alt">Frank Henry Temple Bellew</addName>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1828-04-18">1828-04-18</birth>
  <death when="1888-06-29">1888-06-29</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">Frank Bellew was an illustrator and caricaturist who has been credited with the first graphic representation of "Uncle Sam" in the March 13, 1852, issue of the <hi rendition="#italics">New York Lantern</hi>. Born to an Irish captain and his British wife in India, Frank was educated in France, lived in England and Scotland, and migrated to the United States in about 1850, where he settled in New York City and became involved with the <hi rendition="#italics">Lantern</hi> and other comic papers. His cartoons were often signed with his trademark triangle, which often contained the initials "F.B.," but sometimes contained his last name or was left blank entirely. Many of his cartoons were in the style of the British magazine <hi rendition="#italics">Puck</hi>, where he published a few cartoons in 1860 during a return visit to England. Bellew's cartoons appeared in <hi rendition="#italics">Harper's Weekly</hi>, <hi rendition="#italics">Scribners Monthly</hi>, and <hi rendition="#italics">Harper's Monthly</hi>, among other papers. He also illustrated a number of books, including, in 1866, <hi rendition="#italics">The Art of Amusing</hi>, an illustrated volume on parlor games. Bellew had two children: a son, Frank, who was also an illustrator; and a daughter. He died on June 29, 1888, at his daughter’s home in New York.
</note>
  <bibl><bibl>"A Veteran Artist Dead. Frank Bellew’s Career of over Twenty Years." <hi rendition="#italics">New York Times</hi>, June 30, 1888.</bibl>
                
                <bibl><hi rendition="#italics">Dictionary of American Biography</hi>. New York: Charles Scribner’s Sons, 1938.</bibl>
                
                <bibl>Falk, Peter Hastings et al., eds. <hi rendition="#italics">Who Was Who in American Art, 1574-1975, vol. 1, A-F.</hi> Madison, CT: Sound View Press, 1999.</bibl>
                
                <bibl>"Uncle Sam." <hi rendition="#italics">Time</hi>, May 11, 1931.</bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n85352256.html - drew "Lincoln's Last Warning," DAMS #2188, page 2.</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003699">
  <persName key="ENT.000003699">
    <forename type="first">James Gordon</forename>
    <surname type="last">Bennett</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1841">1841</birth>
  <death when="1918">1918</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">Depicted in HINT cartoon #12155&#13;
editor of NY Herald</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003745">
  <persName key="ENT.000003745">
    <forename type="first">Clifford </forename>
    <forename type="middle">Kennedy</forename>
    <surname type="last">Berryman</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1869">1869</birth>
  <death when="1949">1949</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">artist of hint cartoon: 11953</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000000552">
  <persName key="ENT.000000552">
    <forename type="first">Nicholas</forename>
    <surname type="last">Biddle</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1786">1786</birth>
  <death when="1844">1844</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Nicholas Biddle was born in 1786 to a prominent Philadelphia. A child prodigy, Nicholas enrolled at the University of Pennsylvania at age 10 and completed his studies there by age 13—he was ineligible to receive a degree, however, due to his young age. He subsequently enrolled at Princeton, graduating as valedictorian at age 15, and began a law career.  In 1804, Biddle traveled to Europe as the secretary to US Minister to France John Armstrong and later served as secretary to James Monroe in England. In 1807 he returned to the United States, where he edited Port-Folio magazine, prepared the notes of the Lewis and Clark expedition for publication, opened his own law practice, and was elected to the Pennsylvania House of Representatives in 1810 and the Pennsylvania State Senate in 1814. As a state representative, Biddle helped to establish a Pennsylvania public school system and to renew the charter of the Bank of the United States, which expired in 1811. He married Jane M. Craig in 1811, which whom he had six children.</p>
<p>President James Monroe appointed Biddle the federal government director of the re-chartered Second Bank of the United States, and in 1822, Biddle became its president. In 1832, however, President Andrew Jackson, who had been a longtime opponent of the bank, vetoed renewal of its charter. He followed up by withdrawing the federal government's funds from the bank in 1833, in a highly controversial move with widespread repercussions for the US economy. The bank's charter expired in 1836, but it continued as a state-chartered bank of Pennsylvania. Biddle resigned as president of the bank in 1839; it finally failed in 1841. Biddle died in 1844 at age 58.</p>
</note>
  <bibl><bibl>Biddle Family Papers finding aid, University of Delaware Library, accessed June 9, 2015. <ref target="http://www.lib.udel.edu/ud/spec/findaids/biddle.htm">Link</ref></bibl>
<bibl>Biography at <hi rendition="#italics">The Roots of Lewis and Clark</hi> website, University of Virginia, accessed June 9, 2015. <ref target="http://www2.vcdh.virginia.edu/lewisandclark/biddle/biographies_html/biddle.html">Link</ref></bibl>
<bibl>William G. Shade, "Biddle, Nicholas," <hi rendition="#italics">American National Biography Online</hi> (February 2000), accessed June 9, 2015. <ref target="http://www.anb.org/articles/03/03-00039.html">Link</ref></bibl> 
</bibl>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003544">
  <persName key="ENT.000003544">
    <forename type="first">Diane</forename>
    <surname type="last">Biunno</surname>
  </persName>
  <note type="internal">HINT project staff</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003332">
  <persName key="ENT.000003332">
    <forename type="first">James</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Gillespie</forename>
    <surname type="last">Blaine</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1830">1830</birth>
  <death when="1893">1893</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">James Gillespie Blaine was born on January 31, 1830 in West Brownsville, Pennsylvania.  He served as Secretary of State during the Benjamin Harrison and James A. Garfield Administrations and was the 31st Speaker of the US House of Representatives.  Blaine graduated from Washington College in 1847 and worked as a newspaper editor.  In 1859 he was elected to serve in the Maine House of Representatives and later, in 1862, successfully ran for the US Congress.  In 1880 he lost the Republican Presidential nomination to James A. Garfield and, after the election, was chosen to serve as Secretary of State.  Four years later Republicans nominated him as their candidate, but he lost the presidential election to Grover Cleveland.  In 1888, Benjamin Harrison appointed him Secretary of State.  As Secretary of State, Blaine expanded trade with Latin America and served as chairman of the first Pan-American Conference.  Blaine resigned as Secretary of State on June 4, 1892.  He died on January 27, 1893 in Washington, DC.</note>
  <bibl><bibl>“James G. Blaine, Biography, American Politician, Encyclopedia Britannica.” Accessed May 6, 2015. <ref target="http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/68723/James-G-Blaine">Link</ref></bibl>
                
                <bibl>“James Gillespie Blaine, People, Department History, Office of the Historian.” Accessed May 6, 2015. <ref target="https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/people/blaine-james-gillespie">Link</ref></bibl>
                
                <bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). <hi rendition="#italics"> Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age</hi>. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe.</bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n82011612 ; depicted in 11585-Bc612P567_1_TEI.xml</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003602">
  <persName key="ENT.000003602">
    <forename type="first">Francis</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Preston</forename>
    <surname type="last">Blair</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1821">1821</birth>
  <death when="1875">1875</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n87895303.html; mentioned in 11820 (quoted); vice-presidential candidate (with running mate Horatio Seymour) in 1868</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003545">
  <persName key="ENT.000003545">
    <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
    <surname type="last">Borden</surname>
  </persName>
  <note type="internal">HINT project staff</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003781">
  <persName key="ENT.000003781">
    <surname type="last">Brackmere</surname>
  </persName>
  <note type="internal">artist of 12273</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003333">
  <persName key="ENT.000003333">
    <forename type="first">John</forename>
    <forename type="middle">C.</forename>
    <surname type="last">Breckinridge</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1821">1821</birth>
  <death when="1875">1875</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>John Cabell Breckinridge was the 14th vice president of the United States and the only vice president to take up arms against the United States. Breckinridge was born and raised in Kentucky, where his family had deep roots. He worked as a lawyer in Lexington before serving as an officer in the Mexican-American War, then returned to Kentucky, where he began his political career. In 1849, at the age of 28, he was elected to the Kentucky House of Representatives; in 1851, running as a Whig, he was elected to the US Senate, serving until 1855. Breckinridge argued fiercely in support of the Kansas-Nebraska Act of 1854, engaging in debates so rancorous that he nearly fought a duel with NY Representative Francis B. Cutting as a result. In 1856, Breckinridge was the running mate of presidential candidate James Buchanan, who won the election. At age 36, Breckinridge became the youngest vice president in US history.</p>
<p>He served as vice president from 1857-61 but had a strained relationship with Buchanan, who excluded Breckinridge from his administration and rarely communicated with him.</p>
<p>In 1860 the Democratic Party split when supporters of Stephen Douglas, the leading contender for the presidential nomination, refused to make support of slavery anywhere in the territories part of the party’s platform. Pro-slavery Democrats started their own Southern Democratic Party and chose Breckinridge as their presidential nominee. Breckinridge ran against Republican candidate Abraham Lincoln (whose wife, Mary Todd Lincoln, was a cousin of Breckinridge), Democratic candidate Stephen Douglas, and Constitutional Union Party candidate John Bell; ultimately, Lincoln won the election.</p>
<p>After the election Breckinridge briefly served in the US Senate (1861). He counseled against secession and, after several Southern states seceded from the Union, tried to convince his home state of Kentucky to remain neutral, rather than to take up arms against the Confederacy. Several months later, however, he volunteered to fight for the Confederacy, despite the fact that Kentucky remained part of the Union. He became the second vice president in US history (after Aaron Burr) to be accused of treason and was expelled from the Senate. Breckinridge rose from brigadier general  to major general in the Confederate Army, helped lead a Confederate raid on Washington, DC, in 1864, and, in 1865, became Jefferson Davis’s secretary of war. After the war ended, Breckinridge fled to Cuba and then to England, eventually settling in Toronto, Canada. Following President Andrew Johnson’s pardon of Confederates in 1868, Breckinridge returned to Kentucky, where he resided for the rest of his life. He died in 1875 at the age of 54.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>American President: James Buchanan, Miller Center, University of Virginia, accessed June 22, 2015. <ref target="http://millercenter.org/president/buchanan/essays/vicepresident/1857">Link</ref></bibl>
<bibl>Breckinridge, John Cabell, (1821-1875), Biographical Directory of the United States Congress, accessed June 22, 2015. <ref target="http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=b000789">Link</ref></bibl>
<bibl>John Cabell Breckinridge, 14th Vice President (1857-1861), United States Senate website, accessed June 22, 2015. <ref target="http://www.senate.gov/artandhistory/history/common/generic/VP_John_Breckinridge.htm">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 11561; 11562; 11563; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n85185549.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003334">
  <persName key="ENT.000003334">
    <forename type="first">Benjamin</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Helm</forename>
    <surname type="last">Bristow</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1832">1832</birth>
  <death when="1896">1896</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">Bristow was a lawyer, the first Solicitor General of the United States, and the 30th US Secretary of the Treasury.  He was born in Kentucky on June 20, 1832, and graduated from Jefferson College in Pennsylvania in 1851.  He fought as a Union Soldier in the Civil War, was seriously wounded at the Battle of Shiloh in Tennessee, became the lieutenant colonel of the 8th Kentucky Calvary, and assisted in the 1863 capture of the Confederate raider John Hunt Morgan.  On September 23, 1863 Bristow received an honorable discharge from the Union Army because he was selected to serve in the Kentucky senate.   Bristow was unaware that he had been elected and served only one term, until 1865.  One year later he became the US Attorney for the Kentucky District where he vigorously defended the Civil Rights Act of 1866.  From 1870-1872 he served as the first Solicitor General of the United States.  During his service, he argued issues related to Reconstruction and prosecuted thousands of Ku Klux Klan members.  In 1874, he became the United States Secretary of the Treasury and helped prosecute the Whisky Ring.  Following his resignation in 1876, he returned to New York to practice law and was later elected the second president of the American Bar Association.  He died in New York in 1896.</note>
  <bibl><bibl>"Butler, Benjamin Franklin.  Biographical Directory of the United States Congress."  Last Accessed February 3, 2015 <ref target="http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=b001174">Link</ref></bibl>
<bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). <hi rendition="#italics"> Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age</hi>. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe.</bibl>
                
                <bibl>"Solicitor General Benjamin H Bristow. The United States Department of Justice."  Accessed January 21, 2015 <ref target="http://www.justice.gov/osg/bio/benjamin-h-bristow">Link</ref></bibl>
</bibl>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n85158278.html ; depicted in 11585-Bc612P567_1_TEI.xml</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003742">
  <persName key="ENT.000003742">
    <forename type="first">Harold</forename>
    <surname type="last">Brown</surname>
  </persName>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">Artist of HINT cartoon #12379</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003335">
  <persName key="ENT.000003335">
    <forename type="first">William</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Jennings</forename>
    <surname type="last">Bryan</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1860">1860</birth>
  <death when="1925">1925</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>William Jennings Bryan was a congressman and Democratic leader.  He was born on March 19, 1860 in Illinois.  He studied law at Union College in Chicago and later moved to Nebraska.  In 1890 he became a US Representative from Nebraska.  After losing a campaign to become a US Senator in 1894, he became editor of the <hi rendition="#italics">Omaha World-Herald</hi> and gave lectures.  In 1896 he gave his famous “Cross of Gold” speech and was awarded the democratic nomination for president.  He lost the presidential election to Republican William McKinley.  He unsuccessfully ran again for president in 1900 and lost to McKinley.  He ran for the third and final time in 1908 and was defeated by Republican William Howard Taft.  President Woodrow Wilson appointed Bryan Secretary of State in 1912.  He died on July 26, 1925 in Tennessee.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>“William Jennings Bryan, American Politician.” <hi rendition="#italics">Encyclopedia Britannica</hi>. Accessed July 1, 2015. <ref target="http://www.britannica.com/biography/William-Jennings-Bryan">Link</ref></bibl>
      
      <bibl>“Bryan, William Jennings.” <hi rendition="#italics">Biographical Directory of the United States Congress</hi>. Accessed July 1, 2015.  <ref target="http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=b000995">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 11565-3133_b2f9_1_TEI.xml ; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80044871.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000001011">
  <persName key="ENT.000001011">
    <forename type="first">James</forename>
    <surname type="last">Buchanan</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1791">1791</birth>
  <death when="1868">1868</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>James Buchanan, sometimes referred to as “Old Buck,” was the 15th president of the United States, serving from 1857-61. He was the only president to hail from Pennsylvania as well as the only president never to marry.</p>
<p>Buchanan, one of 11 children, was born in 1791 outside of Mercersburg, Pennsylvania. He graduated from Dickinson College in 1809 and opened a law practice in Lancaster, then the capital of the state, in 1813. He served as a member of the state assembly from 1814 to 1815 before being elected to the US Congress, serving from 1821 to 1831, initially as a Federalist but eventually as a Jacksonian. From 1832-33, Buchanan served as US minister to Russia. In 1834, he was elected to the US Senate and served until 1845 before taking up the post of secretary of state under President James K. Polk, 1845-49.</p>
<p>In 1853, he became US minister to Great Britain. In this role, Buchanan was instrumental in drafting the controversial Ostend Manifesto, which justified taking Cuba from Spain. In 1856, shortly after returning from Great Britain, Buchanan was nominated for president by the Democratic Party and won the election. Before 1856, he had campaigned unsuccessfully for president in 1844, 1848, and 1858.</p>
<p>Buchanan’s presidency was defined by deepening controversy and division over issues of slavery. Two days after Buchanan was inaugurated, the US Supreme Court handed down its decision in the Dred Scott case, ruling that African Americans were not United States citizens and declaring unconstitutional the Missouri Compromise of 1820, which had limited the spread of slavery in the US’s northern and western territories. The Missouri Compromise had already been undermined by passage of the Kansas-Nebraska Act in 1854, which allowed settlers in these territories to decide via popular vote whether or not to permit slavery. In Kansas, this had led to bloody violence between pro- and anti-slavery forces, and conflict over questions of admitting it to the Union as a state. Buchanan advocated allowing Kansas into the Union as a slave state, encouraging adoption of the Lecompton Constitution, a proposed pro-slavery state constitution ultimately rejected by Kansas voters. Buchanan’s longtime ally Stephen Douglas, arguing that Kansas’s state constitution should be decided by legitimate popular vote, broke with Buchanan and left his administration, an event that led to the splitting of the Democratic Party. John Brown’s 1859 raid on Harpers Ferry further deepened national tensions.</p>
<p>In 1860, Buchanan’s Democratic Party, now split between pro-slavery Southern Democrats who backed candidate John C. Breckinridge and traditional or Northern Democrats who supported Stephen Douglas, lost the election to Republican candidate Abraham Lincoln. Buchanan had promised at his inauguration to serve only one term, and did not seek reelection. In reaction to Lincoln’s election, South Carolina seceded from the Union in December 1860, and other Southern states followed suit. When Buchanan left office, the country was on the brink of war.</p>
<p>Buchanan, under attack from across the political spectrum for his failure to avert civil war, retired to Wheatland, his estate in Lancaster, Pennsylvania, and died in 1868.</p>
</note>
  <bibl><bibl>James Buchanan papers (Collection 91), Historical Society of Pennsylvania. <ref target="http://www2.hsp.org/collections/manuscripts/b/Buchanan0091.html">Finding aid</ref></bibl>
<bibl>James Buchanan, biography at WhiteHouse.gov, accessed June 9, 2015. <ref target="https://whitehouse.gov/1600/presidents/jamesbuchanan">Link</ref></bibl>
<bibl>American President: James Buchanan, Miller Center, University of Virginia, accessed June 9, 2015. <ref target="http://millercenter.org/president/buchanan">Link</ref></bibl> </bibl>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 12332, 11730</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003382">
  <persName key="ENT.000003382">
    <forename type="first">John</forename>
    <surname type="last">Stuart</surname>
    <addName type="alt">Lord Bute</addName>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1713">1713</birth>
  <death when="1792">1792</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 2562-Bb612L615_1_TEI.xml (Liberty Triumphant) ; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n81035544.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003551">
  <persName key="ENT.000003551">
    <forename type="first">Benjamin</forename>
    <surname type="last">Butler</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1818">1818</birth>
  <death when="1893">1893</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">Benjamin Franklin Butler was a lawyer, member US House of Representatives, and Governor of Massachusetts.  He was born in 1818 in Deerfield, New Hampshire and in 1838 graduated from Waterville College in Maine.  Butler served in the Massachusetts House of Representatives in 1853 and later in 1859 in the State senate.  He became a representative in the US House of Representatives in 1867, and in 1868 served as one of the managers in the Senatorial impeachment hearings against President Andrew Johnson.  He served as Massachusetts Governor from 1883-1884 and died in Washington DC in 1893.</note>
  <bibl>Butler, Benjamin Franklin.  Biographical Directory of the United States Congress.  Last Accessed February 3, 2015 http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=b001174</bibl>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n85363511</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003753">
  <persName key="ENT.000003753">
    <addName type="honorific">Baron</addName>
    <forename type="first">George</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Gordon</forename>
    <surname type="last">Byron</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1788">1788</birth>
  <death when="1824">1824</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">Poem by Byron quoted in "The Triumph" cartoon (12050)</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003679">
  <persName key="ENT.000003679">
    <forename type="first">Julius</forename>
    <surname type="last">Caesar</surname>
  </persName>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">mentioned in 12338; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79021400.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003693">
  <persName key="ENT.000003693">
    <forename type="first">John</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Caldwell</forename>
    <surname type="last">Calhoun</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1782">1782</birth>
  <death when="1850">1850</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>John C. Calhoun was the South’s most vocal champion of state’s rights and most recognized symbol of the Old South. Born in Abbeville, in the South Carolina Piedmont, in 1782, Calhoun attended Yale and Litchfield Law School in Connecticut, and returned to his native South Carolina, where he briefly practiced law and then entered politics. After a term in the state legislature, Calhoun was elected to Congress as a Democratic Republican in 1811. He resigned in 1817 to become secretary of war for President James Monroe (1817-25), was elected vice president of the United States in 1824 with President John Quincy Adams and then in 1824 with President Andrew Jackson. He served as Jackson’s vice president from 1824 until December 28, 1832, when he resigned after winning election to the US Senate to fill a vacancy. Reelected in 1834 and 1840, he served in the Senate until March 1843. From 1844 to 1845 he served as secretary of state under President John Tyler, when he was again elected to fill a vacancy in the US Senate. He remained in the Senate until his death on March 31, 1850. Calhoun badly wanted, but never achieved, the presidency, despite three strong attempts. </p>
                
                <p>When Calhoun first entered national politics in 1811, he was a leading supporter of strong government, supporting a national road system, the second Bank of the United States, a strong military, and a protective tariff. In the 1830s, however, Calhoun became an extreme proponent of state’s rights and a strict construction of the Constitution. In 1831 he began publically defending nullification, the right of any state to nullify—or declare unconstitutional—objectionable federal legislation; Congress would then need to amend the Constitution to reinstate the nullified law. The tariff was the immediate object of the nullification debate, but Calhoun and other nullifiers were more concerned about protecting southern slavery. Most state’s rights advocated did not embrace Calhoun’s doctrine. By 1832, President Jackson broke with his vice president over such policy issues as well as over Calhoun’s role in the Eaton affair, in which several cabinet members and their wives ostracized Peggy Eaton, the new wife of John Eaton, secretary of war, for alleged adultery with Eaton while she was married to another man.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl><hi rendition="#italics">Biographical Dictionary of the United States Congress.</hi> “Calhoun, John Caldwell, (1782-1850).” Accessed  Apr. 28, 2015. <ref target="http://guide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=c000044">Link</ref></bibl>
                
 <bibl><hi rendition="#italics">Encyclopædia Britannica. Encylcopædia Britannica Online.</hi> “John C. Calhoun.” Accessed Apr. 28, 2015.  <hi rendition="#italics">Link</hi></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 11751; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79137102.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003771">
  <persName key="ENT.000003771">
    <forename type="first">Charles</forename>
    <surname type="last">Pratt</surname>
    <addName type="alt">Candor</addName>
    <addName type="alt">Lord Camden</addName>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1714">1714</birth>
  <death when="1794">1794</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 12017; bio at http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n86018348.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003336">
  <persName key="ENT.000003336">
    <forename type="first">James</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Donald</forename>
    <surname type="last">Cameron</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1833">1833</birth>
  <death when="1918">1918</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">James Donald Cameron was a US Republican Senator, Secretary of War, and Republican National Committee Chairman.  Cameron was born in Middletown, PA on May 14, 1833 and was the son of Simon Cameron, a prominent Republican politician and the Secretary of War in President Lincoln’s Cabinet.  After graduating from Princeton College in 1852, he worked for the family businesses, including banking and the North Central Railroad.  In 1866 he helped his father win a seat in the US Senate, and later in 1876, campaigned for Ulysses S. Grant.  When Grant won the presidential election, he appointed Cameron Secretary of War.  Cameron served for one year (1876-1877).  He served in the US Senate from 1877-1897 and served as the Republican National Committee Chairman from 1879-1880.  He died in his home in Lancaster County Pennsylvania on August 30, 1918.</note>
  <bibl> <bibl>"Cameron, James Donald.  Biographical Directory of the United States Congress."  Last Accessed February 3, 2015.  <ref target="http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=c000065"></ref>Link</bibl>
<bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). <hi rendition="#italics"> Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age</hi>. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe.</bibl>
</bibl>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n86114833.html ; depicted in 11585-Bc612P567_1_TEI.xml</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003337">
  <persName key="ENT.000003337">
    <forename type="first">Simon</forename>
    <surname type="last">Cameron</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1799">1799</birth>
  <death when="1889">1889</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Simon Cameron was born on March 8, 1799 in Pennsylvania and was the father of James Donald Cameron, (Secretary of War during the Grant Administration).  At seventeen years old Simon Cameron became an editor for the newspaper <hi rendition="#italics">Northumberland Gazette </hi>and later a newspaper owner and editor.  In 1822 was appointed to the post of State Printer and later became an influential politician whose support convinced Democrats to nominate Martin Van Buren as the 1832 vice presidential candidate.   In addition to his work as a politician, Cameron was a successful businessman who earned his fortune in the banking and railroad industries.  In 1845 he successfully ran for the US Senate and later, in 1861, became Abraham Lincoln’s secretary of war.  He served a ten month term, resigned in 1862 due to corruption allegations, and was appointed by Lincoln to serve as the ambassador to Russia.   In 1863 Cameron resigned, ran unsuccessfully for the US Senate, and was accused of bribing politicians in order to sway the election.   Cameron supported Lincoln’s re-election, and in return, Lincoln appointed  politicians loyal to Cameron to serve in Pennsylvania.  Consequently, Cameron’s political influence increased and he soon became the leader of Pennsylvania’s political machine.   Simon Cameron died on June 26, 1899 at his home in Pennsylvania.</p></note>
  <bibl> <bibl>"Cameron, Simon.  Biographical Directory of the United States Congress."  Last Accessed February 3, 2015.  <ref target="http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=c000068">Link</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl>"Simon Cameron.  Pennsylvania Historical and Museum Commission."  Last Accessed February 3, 2015.  <ref target="http://www.ddap.pa.gov/portal/server.pt/community/people/4277/cameron,_simon/443541">Link</ref>
                </bibl>
                
                <bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). <hi rendition="#italics"> Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age</hi>. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe.</bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 11585-Bc612P567_1_TEI.xml according to LOC, but I don't know which one is he -SN see: http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/2005696340/ ; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n86114834.html ; father of James Donald Cameron</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003338">
  <persName key="ENT.000003338">
    <forename type="first">Joseph</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Gurney</forename>
    <surname type="last">Cannon</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1836">1836</birth>
  <death when="1926">1926</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 1782-3313_b2f8_1_TEI.xml ; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50051508.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000000910">
  <persName key="ENT.000000910">
    <forename type="first">Lewis</forename>
    <surname type="last">Cass</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1782">1782</birth>
  <death when="1866">1866</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 11730 http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50034113.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003664">
  <persName key="ENT.000003664">
    <forename type="first">Charles</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Francis</forename>
    <surname type="last">Murphy</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1858">1858</birth>
  <death when="1924">1924</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000000848">
  <persName key="ENT.000000848">
    <forename type="first">William</forename>
    <surname type="last">Charles</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1776">1776</birth>
  <death when="1820">1820</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>William Charles, born in Edinburgh, Scotland, in 1776, is best known for his prolific political etchings, often embellished with aquatint, celebrating American military victories during the War of 1812. Historians Stephen Hess and Milton Kaplan deem him “the first major American cartoonist to work on American soil.”</p>
<p>Little is known about his professional training, but Charles had his own printing shop in London by at least 1803, out of which his earliest known prints, cartoons commenting on the Napoleonic Wars, were published. He moved back to Scotland and established a business called “Charles’s Emporium of Art and Fancy’s Produce” in Edinburgh sometime between February and July 1804. Charles emigrated to New York around 1806, possibly as a result of having raised the ire of British church authorities he had lampooned in his caricatures. There he published numerous political cartoons, etched plates for the <hi rendition="#italics">American Magazine of Wit</hi>, and published at least two illustrated children’s books: <hi rendition="#italics">Pompey the Little Who Was Tied to the Kettle</hi> and <hi rendition="#italics">The Comic Adventures of Old Mother Hubbard and Her Dog</hi>. He moved to Philadelphia at some point between 1808 and 1814; he is listed in city directories and in the account books of Philadelphia publisher and economist Matthew Carey from at least 1808.</p>
<p>The War of 1812 represented Charles’s professional heyday; his  numerous political cartoons published in Philadelphia between 1812 and 1815 are his best-known works. At some point in or around 1813, Charles partnered with Samuel Kennedy, a Philadelphia carver, gilder, and looking-glass maker. The two collaborated on a handful of cartoons that commented on the war. For many of these prints, Kennedy seems to have been the primary artist and Charles the etcher and/or publisher. The pair also planned to publish a monthly folio of cartoons but were unable to raise the necessary funds.</p>
<p>After the War of 1812 ended, Charles largely did commercial engraving and publishing (bank notes, illustrated plates for reference books, and book illustrations) and produced some images of landscapes. He published few other political caricatures.</p>
<p>Charles died on August 9, 1820; on a journey to Boston to promote his toy books, he fell overboard into the Delaware River and drowned. He left behind a wife, Mary Charles, who published children’s books out of a shop in Philadelphia until her death in 1823.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>Stephen Hess and Milton Kaplan, <hi rendition="#italics">The Ungentlemanly Art: A History of American Political Cartoons</hi> (New York: Macmillan, 1968).</bibl>
<bibl>Lorraine Welling Lanmon, “American Caricature in the English Tradition: The Personal and Political Satires of William Charles,” <hi rendition="#italics">Winterthur Portfolio</hi> 11 (1976): 1-51.</bibl>
<bibl>Lorraine Dwelling Lanmon, “William Charles and His War of 1812 Caricatures,” in <hi rendition="#italics">Philadelphia Printmaking: American Prints before 1860</hi>, edited by Robert F. Looney (West Chester, PA: Tinicum Press, 1977), 91-109.</bibl>
<bibl><hi rendition="#italics">Made in America: Printmaking 1760-1860</hi> (Philadelphia: Library Company of Philadelphia, 1973), 18-19.</bibl>
<bibl>William Murrell, <hi rendition="#italics">A History of American Graphic Humor</hi>, vol. 1 (New York: Whitney Museum of American Art, 1933), 79-95.</bibl></bibl>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003542">
  <persName key="ENT.000003542">
    <addName type="honorific">Queen</addName>
    <forename type="first">Charlotte</forename>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1744">1744</birth>
  <death when="1818">1818</death>
  <sex>Female</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000000132">
  <persName key="ENT.000000132">
    <forename type="first">Edward Williams</forename>
    <surname type="last">Clay</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1799">1799</birth>
  <death when="1857">1857</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000002230">
  <persName key="ENT.000002230">
    <forename type="first">Henry</forename>
    <surname type="last">Clay</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1777">1777</birth>
  <death when="1852">1852</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003339">
  <persName key="ENT.000003339">
    <forename type="first">Stephen </forename>
    <forename type="middle">Grover</forename>
    <surname type="last">Cleveland</surname>
    <addName type="alt">Cleveland, Stephen Grover, 1837-1908</addName>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1837">1837</birth>
  <death when="1908">1908</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">only pres to serve 2 nonconsecutive terms ; depicted 11524-PG278_b5f2_1_TEI.xml ; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50029194.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003732">
  <persName key="ENT.000003732">
    <forename type="first">DeWitt</forename>
    <surname type="last">Clinton</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1769">1769</birth>
  <death when="1828">1828</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">DeWitt Clinton was a US senator from New York 1802-1803, mayor of New York City 1803-1815, and governor of New York 1817-1822 and 1825-1828. He may be depicted in the 1796 political cartoon "A Peek Into the Antifederal Club" as the man sitting on the floor singing to a doll; some historians identify this figure instead as George Clinton.</note>
  <bibl><bibl>"A Peep into the Antifederal Club - JCB Political Cartoons." Accessed May 12, 2015. <ref target="http://jcb.lunaimaging.com/luna/servlet/detail/JCBMAPS~2~2~656~100498:A-Peep-into-the-Antifederal-Club">Link</ref></bibl>
<bibl><hi rendition="#italics">Made in America: Printmaking, 1760-1860</hi> (Philadelphia: Library Company of Philadelphia, 1973), 11-12</bibl></bibl>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003731">
  <persName key="ENT.000003731">
    <forename type="first">George</forename>
    <surname type="last">Clinton</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1739">1739</birth>
  <death when="1812">1812</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">George Clinton was governor of New York from 1777-1795 and from 1801-1804; he also served as the first elected vice president of the United States (1805-1812) under Thomas Jefferson and James Madison. He may be depicted in the 1796 political cartoon "A Peek Into the Antifederal Club" as the man sitting on the floor singing to a doll; some historians identify this figure instead as DeWitt Clinton.</note>
  <bibl><bibl>"A Peep into the Antifederal Club - JCB Political Cartoons." Accessed May 12, 2015. <ref target="http://jcb.lunaimaging.com/luna/servlet/detail/JCBMAPS~2~2~656~100498:A-Peep-into-the-Antifederal-Club">Link</ref></bibl>
<bibl><hi rendition="#italics">Made in America: Printmaking, 1760-1860</hi> (Philadelphia: Library Company of Philadelphia, 1973), 11-12</bibl></bibl>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003727">
  <persName key="ENT.000003727">
    <forename type="first">William</forename>
    <surname type="last">Coleman</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1766">1766</birth>
  <death when="1829">1829</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">First editor of the <hi rendition="#italics">New York Evening Post</hi></note>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n86104944.html; depicted in 11824</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003552">
  <persName key="ENT.000003552">
    <forename type="first">Roscoe</forename>
    <surname type="last">Conkling</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1829">1829</birth>
  <death when="1888">1888</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">  <p>Roscoe Conkling was a congressman, politician, and leader of the Stalwart faction of the Republican Party.  He was born on October 30, 1829 in New York, studied at the Auburn Academy, and joined the bar in 1850.  He was elected to serve in the US House of Representatives in 1859 and later became a US Senator (1867-1881).   He helped draft the Electoral Commission Act of 1877 and the 14th and 15th amendments.  He supported and helped pass Reconstruction legislation and the Civil Rights Act of 1875. He was nominated in 1873 by Ulysses S. Grant to the post of chief justice of the Supreme Court, but declined the offer.  In 1876 he unsuccessfully sought the Republican presidential nomination.  By 1880 Conkling had become the leader of the Stalwart Faction of the Republican Party.  The Stalwarts staunchly supported Ulysses S. Grant in his bid for a presidential third term.  Due to divisions within the party, however, Republicans placed James A. Garfield on the ticket.  Conkling resigned from the Senate in 1881, returned to his law practice in New York City, and died on April 18, 1888.</p>
                </note>
  <bibl> <bibl>"Conkling, Roscoe.  Biographical Directory of the United States Congress."  Last Accessed February 3, 2015.  <ref target="http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=c000681">Link</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). <hi rendition="#italics"> Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age</hi>. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe.</bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n85363319.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003783">
  <persName key="ENT.000003783">
    <forename type="first">Richard</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Barrett</forename>
    <surname type="last">Connolly</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1810">1810</birth>
  <death when="1880">1880</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">Richard B. Connolly, aka "Slippery Dick," was the unofficial chief financial officer of the infamous "Tweed Ring." Connolly was comptroller of New York City from 1867 until his resignation on November 18, 1871. Shortly after his resignation, he was arrested an indicted of 15 misdemeanor counts. After being released on bail, he fled the United States and eventually died in Marseilles, France. Connolly was born in Ireland and came to New York City as a young man. He also served as Clerk of New York County from 1853 to 1858 and as a member of the NY State Senate from 1860 to 1863.</note>
  <bibl><bibl>John Adler, with Draper Hill, <hi rendition="#italics">Doomed by Cartoon: How Cartoonist Thomas Nast the “The New-York Times” Brought down Boss Tweed and His Ring of Thieves</hi> (Garden City, New York: Morgan James, 2008)</bibl>
<bibl>"At Three Score and Ten: Richard B. Connolly's Death at Marseilles," <hi rendition="#italics">New York Times</hi> obituary, June 1, 1880.</bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 12273</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003633">
  <persName key="ENT.000003633">
    <forename type="first">Tennessee</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Celeste</forename>
    <surname type="last">Claflin</surname>
    <addName type="alt">Tennessee Claflin Cook</addName>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1845">1845</birth>
  <death when="1923">1923</death>
  <sex>Female</sex>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80109890.html; depicted in 11747</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003572">
  <persName key="ENT.000003572">
    <forename type="first">Alonzo</forename>
    <forename type="middle">B</forename>
    <surname type="last">Cornell</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1832">1832</birth>
  <death when="1904">1904</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Alonzo Cornell was born on January 22, 1832 in Ithaca, New York and became a politician, successful businessman, and the 13th Governor of New York.  His father Ezra Cornell, was the founder of Cornell University.</p>
<p>Cornell helped his father found the Western Union Telegraph Company, and later served as the company’s director.  He became the New York Republican State Central Committee Chairman in 1870 and served until 1878.  In 1876 he was appointed by Rutherford B. Hayes to serve as Surveyor of the Port of New York.  Because of a political dispute, Hayes removed him from the position two years later.  In 1878 Cornell became New York State Governor, beating his democratic incumbent opponent, Lucius Robinson.  As governor, Cornell established a state board of health and a state railroad commission.  After serving only one term, Cornell left politics and returned to business.  He died on October 15, 1904.</p></note>
  <bibl>  <bibl>“Alonzo B. Cornell, Hallofgovernors.ny.gov,” accessed February 11, 2015. <ref target="http://hallofgovernors.ny.gov/AlonzoCornell">Link</ref></bibl>
                <bibl>“Cornell, Alonzo Barton, House Divided,” accessed February 11, 2015. <ref target="http://hd.housedivided.dickinson.edu/node/5481">Link</ref></bibl>
                <bibl>“Alonzo Barton Cornell, National Governors’ Association” accessed February 11, 2015. <ref target="http://www.nga.org/cms/home/governors/past-governors-bios/page_new_york/col2-content/main-content-list/title_cornell_alonzo.html"></ref>Link</bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no98021391</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003713">
  <persName key="ENT.000003713">
    <forename type="first">Samuel</forename>
    <surname type="last">Cox</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1824">1824</birth>
  <death when="1889">1889</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50018799.html&#13;
depicted in hint cartoon #12154</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003340">
  <persName key="ENT.000003340">
    <forename type="first">George</forename>
    <forename type="middle">William</forename>
    <surname type="last">Curtis</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1824">1824</birth>
  <death when="1892">1892</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>George William Curtis was a journalist and editor.  He was born on February 24, 1824 in Providence, RI, attended private school in New York, and traveled throughout Europe, Egypt, and Syria in the 1840s.  Upon his return to the US, he wrote for and helped George Palmer Putnam found <hi rendition="#italics">Putman’s Magazine</hi>.  Shortly thereafter, he began writing for the <hi rendition="#italics">Tribune and Harper’s Weekly</hi>, a popular New York political magazine.  He served as the editor of <hi rendition="#italics">Harper’s Weekly</hi> from 1863 to 1892.  In 1864 he served as a delegate to the Republican National Convention where he supported Lincoln, and even wrote the letter notifying the incumbent president of his re-nomination.   Curtis was politically active, and a Mugwump who believed in civil service, education, and trade reforms.  During the Grant administration he became Chairman of the Civil Service Reform Commission and later the president of the National Civil Service Reform League and the New York Civil Service Reform Association.  He died in Staten Island on August 31, 1892.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>"George William Curtis Papers Finding Aid. Staten Island Museum."  Last Accessed February 3, 2015.  <ref target="http://www.statenislandmuseum.org/images/uploads/collections/Curtis_(George_William)_Papers_Finding_Aids.pdf">Link</ref></bibl>
                
<bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe.</bibl>
</bibl>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50018719.html ; depicted in 11585-Bc612P567_1_TEI.xml</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003549">
  <persName key="ENT.000003549">
    <forename type="first">Otho</forename>
    <surname type="last">Cushing</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1841">1841</birth>
  <death when="1942">1942</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n95000553.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003716">
  <persName key="ENT.000003716">
    <forename type="first">Louis</forename>
    <surname type="last">Dalrymple</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1866">1866</birth>
  <death when="1905">1905</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">cartoonist for Puck.  artist of hint cartoon #12311&#13;
http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n95000561.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003594">
  <persName key="ENT.000003594">
    <forename type="first">Charles</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Anderson</forename>
    <surname type="last">Dana</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1819">1819</birth>
  <death when="1897">1897</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Charles Anderson Dana was born on August 8, 1819 in Hinsdale, New Hampshire and became the editor of the <hi rendition="#italics">New York Sun</hi>.  In 1839 he enrolled at Havard College, but due to financial problems, was forced to leave school.  He later began writing for the <hi rendition="#italics">New York Tribune</hi>.  He became the managing editor for the <hi rendition="#italics">New York Tribune</hi> in 1849, but in 1862 was forced to resign because he did not get along with the editor-publisher Horace Greeley.   In 1868 Dana became an owner and editor of the <hi rendition="#italics">New York Sun</hi>.  Dana also authored several books including  <hi rendition="#italics">Recollections of the Civil War</hi> and <hi rendition="#italics">The Art of Newspaper Making</hi>.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>“Charles A. Dana  Biography - American Journalist” Encyclopedia Britannica, accessed February 10, 2015.  <ref target="http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/150676/Charles-A-Dana">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n85253013.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003703">
  <persName key="ENT.000003703">
    <forename type="first">David</forename>
    <surname type="last">Davis</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1815">1815</birth>
  <death when="1886">1886</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n86114096&#13;
Depicted in Hint cartoon 11834</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000001041">
  <persName key="ENT.000001041">
    <forename type="first">Jefferson</forename>
    <surname type="last">Davis</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1808">1808</birth>
  <death when="1889">1889</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Jefferson Davis was the president of the Confederate States of America, a position he took with some reluctance but in which he served for six years. Like Abraham Lincoln, Davis was born in Kentucky to a modest farming family. The Davis’s did own a few slaves, and when Jefferson was still very young the family moved to Louisiana Territory and then to Mississippi. Davis returned to Kentucky to attend Transylvania University, and then he studied at the US Military Academy at West Point from 1824 to 1828. After graduation he served in the infantry in the West. In 1835, he resigned from the military, married the daughter of Zachary Taylor, and moved to Mississippi, where his new wife soon died from malaria and he became a cotton planter along with his brother Joseph.</p>

<p>In the 1840s, Davis became active in politics, and in 1845 he both married Varina Howell and was elected to Congress. In politics, Davis became a strong advocate of territorial expansion and of states’ right to extend slavery to them. Davis left Congress to serve in the Mexican War, but returned to Congress when he was appointed to the Senate in 1847. He strongly opposed the Compromise of 1850. In 1851, Davis resigned from the Senate to run for governor of Mississippi. He lost that race but he returned to politics when he was appointed secretary of war by President Franklin Pierce. He served in that position until 1857, when he was again elected as a Democrat to the US Senate. Despite his strong state’s rights views, Davis hoped that the South could remain within the Union. Following Lincoln’s election, Davis did not immediately support secession. Because of his moderation in the secession crisis, he became an attractive candidate for the Confederacy’s presidency, since he was acceptable to the Upper South. Davis accepted his election to the presidency with some reluctance. He would have preferred to have a military command. </p>

<p>As Confederate president, Davis was an effective leader, building a strong central government in spite of his own, and the South’s, state’s rights convictions. Davis wielded strong executive power, instituting conscription, exerting considerable control over transportation infrastructure and the economy. He was also involved in military planning. A good administrative leader, Davis was not, however, an inspirational one, and the South suffered from problems of morale.</p>

<p>Jefferson Davis was captured on May 10, 1865, in Irwinville, Georgia, as he and his family fled Union troops. It was rumored that he was fled in woman’s dress, though he really only had thrown on his wife’s overcoat as he tried to escape approaching troops. He was jailed for two years at Fortress Monroe. He was indicted for treason but was paroled in 1867. He returned to Mississippi, where he wrote <hi rendition="#italics">The Rise and Fall of the Confederate Government</hi>. He died in New Orleans in 1889. In 1978, Davis’s citizenship was reinstated by a joint resolution of Congress.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>“Jefferson Davis.” <hi rendition="#italics">American National Biography</hi>.</bibl>
<bibl>“Davis, Jefferson, (1808-1889).” <hi rendition="#italics">Biographical Dictionary of the United States Congress</hi>, Accessed May 27, 2015.  <ref target="http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=D000113">Link</ref></bibl>
<bibl>“Jefferson Davis (1808-1889).” <hi rendition="#italics">Encyclopedia of Virginia</hi>, Accessed May 27, 2015. <ref target="http://encyclopediavirginia.org/Davis_Jefferson_1808-1889#start_entry">Link</ref></bibl>
<bibl>“Capture of Jefferson Davis.” <hi rendition="#italics">New Georgia Encyclopedia</hi>, Accessed May 27, 2015. <ref target="http://www.georgiaencyclopedia.org/articles/history-archaeology/capture-jefferson-davis">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79145410.html. Depicted in 11511, 2189; often depicted wearing ragged clothing in political cartoons--HINT project biographer might want to research/explain why</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003341">
  <persName key="ENT.000003341">
    <forename type="first">Henry</forename>
    <surname type="last">Dawkins</surname>
  </persName>
  <death when="1786">1786</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <bibl>http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n87947371.html</bibl>
  <note type="internal">cartoonist ; artist and engraver of 2562-Bb612L615_1_TEI.xml (Liberty Triumphant)</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000000436">
  <persName key="ENT.000000436">
    <forename type="first">John</forename>
    <forename type="middle">L.</forename>
    <surname type="last">De Mar</surname>
  </persName>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>John De Mar was a cartoonist for the <hi rendition="#italics">Philadelphia Record</hi>.  He was born in 1865 in Pennsylvania and died in 1926.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>Falk, Peter H, Audrey M Lewis, Georgia Kuchen, and Veronika Roessler. <hi rendition="#italics">Who Was Who in American Art, 1564-1975: 400 Years of Artists in America.</hi> Madison, CT: Sound View Press, 1999.</bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">cartoonist at the Philadelphia Record, early 1900s
artist 11513-3133_b2f8_1_TEI.xml 11514-3133_b2f8_1_TEI.xml 11522-3133_b2f8_1_TEI.xml; 1782-3313_b2f8_1_TEI.xml; mentioned in 11570-3313_b2f9_1_TEI.xml 

                    </note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003637">
  <persName key="ENT.000003637">
    <forename type="first">George</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Wallace</forename>
    <surname type="last">Delamater</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1849-03-31">1849-03-31</birth>
  <death when="1907-08-07">1907-08-07</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">Pennsylvania State Senator from 1887-1890; depicted in DAMS #11737, "The Silence of Matt Quay."
See http://politicalgraveyard.com/death/offices.html; https://books.google.com/books?id=h68bAQAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA10&amp;lpg=PA10&amp;dq=pa+senator+george+w.+delamater&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=FsL_qPMdN4&amp;sig=xFJCQ6KjdUFFkGITQSL6kxyW2GY&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=ejj_VNfBE8aZNpC6hJAM&amp;ved=0CCsQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false; http://www.historicpa.net/bios/2g/george-w-delamater.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003757">
  <persName key="ENT.000003757">
    <forename type="first">Amos</forename>
    <surname type="last">Doolittle</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1754">1754</birth>
  <death when="1832">1832</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">Early American cartoonist and engraver, based in New Haven, CT.</note>
  <bibl>William Murrell, <hi rendition="#italics">A History of American Graphic Humor</hi>, vol. 1, 1747-1865 (New York: Whitney Museum of American Art, 1933), 60-64</bibl>
  <note type="internal">Engraver of 11819</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003344">
  <persName key="ENT.000003344">
    <forename type="first">Stephen</forename>
    <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
    <surname type="last">Douglas</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1813">1813</birth>
  <death when="1861">1861</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 11561; 11562; 11563; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50027507.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000002166">
  <persName key="ENT.000002166">
    <forename type="first">Frederick</forename>
    <surname type="last">Douglass</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1818">1818</birth>
  <death when="1895">1895</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000002636">
  <persName key="ENT.000002636">
    <forename type="first">William</forename>
    <surname type="last">Duane</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1808">1808</birth>
  <death when="1882">1882</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in DAMS record # 1778</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003345">
  <persName key="ENT.000003345">
    <forename type="first">George</forename>
    <forename type="middle">F.</forename>
    <surname type="last">Edmunds</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1828">1828</birth>
  <death when="1919">1919</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>George Franklin Edmunds was a lawyer and Republican senator who was born on February 1, 1828 in Richmond, Vermont.  He studied law, and was admitted to the bar in 1849.  In 1854 he became a representative in the Vermont House of Representatives and later in 1856, the speaker of the Vermont House of Representatives.  He joined the US Senate in 1866 and continued to serve until 1891.  As Senator, he supported Reconstruction policies, was active in the impeachment of Andrew Johnson, and drafted the Tenure of Office Act in 1867.  He served as chairman of the Senate Judiciary Committee from 1872 to 1879 and again from 1882 to 1891.  He worked to pass legislation to outlaw Mormon polygamy and to regulate railroads, as well as, drafted and supported the 1877 Electoral Commission Act which resolved the presidential election dispute between Rutherford Hayes and Samuel Tilden.  He also helped draft the Sherman Anti-Trust Act.  After Edmunds resigned from the Senate, he continued to practice law and argued several cases before the Supreme Court, including the 1895 Pollock v. Farmers’ Loan and Trust Co. Case.  He died in Pasadena, California on February 27, 1919.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>"Edmunds, George Franklin.  Biographical Directory of the United States Congress."  Last Accessed February 3, 2015.  <ref target="http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=e000056">Link</ref></bibl>
                
<bibl>George Franklin Edmunds.  Encyclopedia Britannica Online.  Last Accessed February 3, 2015. <ref target="http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/179355/George-Franklin-Edmunds">Link</ref></bibl>
                
<bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe.</bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 11585-Bc612P567_1_TEI.xml ; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n88071154.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003553">
  <persName key="ENT.000003553">
    <forename type="first">William</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Hayden</forename>
    <surname type="last">English</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1822">1822</birth>
  <death when="1896">1896</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p> William Hayden English was a lawyer, historian, Democratic politician, and candidate for Vice President.  He was born on August 27, 1822 in Lexington, Indiana, studied at Hanover College, and was admitted to the Indiana bar in 1840.  In 1851 he was elected to the Indiana House of Representatives and served as speaker.  Two years later he became the Indiana State Representative in the US House of Representatives where he served until 1861.  After his retirement, he founded the First National Bank of Indianapolis and later became the chairman of the Indiana Democratic Central Committee.  In 1880, the Democrats nominated him as Winfield Scott Hancock’s vice presidential running-mate.  After losing the election to Republicans James A. Garfield and Chester Arthur, English served as the president of the Indiana Historical Society, published a book on the history of Indiana, and two other history books entitled <hi rendition="#italics">Conquest of the Country Northwest of the River Ohio, 1778-1783</hi> and <hi rendition="#italics">Life of General George Rogers Clark</hi>.  English died from complications due to heart disease on February 7, 1896.</p></note>
  <bibl> <bibl>“English, William Hayden - Biographical Information,” accessed February 4, 2015.  <ref target="http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=E000191">Link</ref> </bibl>

                <bibl>“IDOA: William H. English,” accessed February 4, 2015.  <ref target="http://www.in.gov/idoa/2791.htm">Link</ref></bibl>

<bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe.</bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n89611965.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003346">
  <persName key="ENT.000003346">
    <forename type="first">William</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Maxwell</forename>
    <surname type="last">Evarts</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1818">1818</birth>
  <death when="1901">1901</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">William Maxwell Evarts was a lawyer, politician, and Secretary of State.  He was born in Boston, Massachusetts on February 6, 1818.  He studied at Yale College and Harvard Law School and joined the bar in 1841.  He was the Assistant District Attorney of the southern district of New York from 1848-1853.  Evarts served as chief counsel during President Andrew Johnson’s impeachment trial and was later appointed Attorney General by Johnson.  Evarts remained in the post for one year from 1868 to 1869, and then returned to private practice, helped found the New York Bar Association, and served as its first president, 1870-1879.  In 1876 Evarts represented Benjamin Hayes before the Electoral Commission during the disputed election of 1876 between Hayes and Samuel J. Tilden.  Evarts later served as Secretary of State from 1877 to 1881 during President Hayes’ administration.  After leaving office, he was elected to the US Senate and served from 1885 to 1891 and died on February 28, 1901.   </note>
  <bibl><bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe. </bibl>

                <bibl>“Evarts, William Maxwell - Biographical Information,” accessed February 4, 2015. <ref target="http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=E000262">Link</ref> </bibl>
                
                <bibl>“William Maxwell Evarts - People - Department History - Office of the Historian,” accessed February 4, 2015, <ref target="https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/people/evarts-william-maxwell">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n84124640.html ; depicted in 11585-Bc612P567_1_TEI.xml</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003347">
  <persName key="ENT.000003347">
    <forename type="first">Edward</forename>
    <surname type="last">Everett</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1794">1794</birth>
  <death when="1865">1865</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 11561;  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n85158370.html. Constitutional Party vice presidential candidate in 1860.</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003348">
  <persName key="ENT.000003348">
    <forename type="first">Charles</forename>
    <surname type="last">Fairbanks</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1852">1852</birth>
  <death when="1918">1918</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 1782-3313_b2f8_1_TEI.xml ; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n86114870.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003696">
  <persName key="ENT.000003696">
    <forename type="first">David</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Glasgow</forename>
    <surname type="last">Farragut</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1801">1801</birth>
  <death when="1870">1870</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>David Glasgow Farragut was the first admiral of the United States. Farragut, born James Glasgow Farragut, was the son of a ferryboat operator and sailing master in the US Navy. James changed his name to David in 1814, in honor of David Porter Jr., who became young James’s guardian after his parents’ deaths. Farragut became a midshipman in 1810, at the age of nine. He served in the War of 1812 on the Essex, and at age twelve commanded the prize ship Alexander Barclay. After the war, Farragut served in the Mediterranean and the West Indies before marrying and settling in Norfolk, Virginia, where he lived until 1861. When Virginia seceded, Farragut left Norfolk, moving to Hastings-on-Hudson, New York, where he awaited orders. He was called to duty in December 1861 with orders to take New Orleans and open the Mississippi River up to Union traffic. In contrast to George McClellan, Farragut was willing to take risks if he thought the potential gains significant. He was successful in taking New Orleans and the Mississippi River forts by summer 1862 and he was made a rear admiral. By the end of 1862, he had closed every Gulf port except Mobile. After suffering some defeats in 1863, Farragut returned to New York. He was back in the Gulf in early 1864, however, where his target was Mobile. During a battle that August, Farragut reportedly ordered “Damn the torpedoes, full speed ahead” and succeeded in taking Mobile Bay, the first significant Union victory in nine months. On December 23, 1864, Lincoln signed a bill creating the office of vice admiral and nominated Farragut to it. Congress later created the rank of full admiral, specifically for Farragut, and he was appointed on July 26, 1866. After the war, Farragut toured Europe, promoting peaceful relations. After suffering from a heart attack from which he never fully recovered, he died at Portsmouth, New Hampshire in 1870.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>“Farragut, David Glasgow.” American National Biography.</bibl>
                
                <bibl>“David Glasgow Farragut.” Tennessee Encyclopedia of History and Culture. <ref target="http://tennesseeencyclopedia.net/entry.php?rec=456">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">mentioned in 11751; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50011924.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003558">
  <persName key="ENT.000003558">
    <forename type="first">James</forename>
    <surname type="last">Fisk </surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1835">1835</birth>
  <death when="1872">1872</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">James Fisk was born on April 1, 1834 in Bennington, Vermont.  He was a financier, stockbroker, and one of the robber barons.  He formed a brokerage firm in 1866.  A few years later, he and his business partner Jay Gould fought Cornelius Vanderbilt for control of the Erie Railroad.  During the Erie War Gould and Fisk inflated the value of the stocks and thus succeeded in gaining control of the Erie Railroad.  The pair bribed and created alliances with a number of judges, legislators, and politicians including Boss Tweed.  On September 24, 1869, their financial schemes and dishonesty led to the panic of Black Friday.  Fisk was married to Lucy Moore and his mistress was Josie Mansfield.  Mansfield later had an affair with Edward Stokes and the pair attempted to blackmail Fisk out of a large sum of money.  On January 6, 1872 an argument between Stokes and Fisk turned deadly when Stokes shot and killed Fisk.  </note>
  <bibl><bibl>Ellen Terrell, “Robber Barons: Gould and Fisk, Inside Adams: Science, Technology &amp; Business,” webpage, (September 26, 2012)." <ref target="http://blogs.loc.gov/inside_adams/2012/09/robber-barons-gould-and-fisk/">Link</ref></bibl>
                <bibl>“James Fisk | Biography - American Financier,<hi rendition="#italics">Encyclopedia Britannica</hi>." accessed January 21, 2015.  <ref target="http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/208740/James-Fisk">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80107292.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003349">
  <persName key="ENT.000003349">
    <forename type="first">Joseph</forename>
    <surname type="last">Foraker</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1846">1846</birth>
  <death when="1917">1917</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 1782-3313_b2f8_1_TEI.xml  ; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n92010125.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003601">
  <persName key="ENT.000003601">
    <forename type="first">Nathan</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Bedford</forename>
    <surname type="last">Forrest</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1821">1821</birth>
  <death when="1877">1877</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80015646.html; mentioned 11820</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003769">
  <persName key="ENT.000003769">
    <forename type="first">Charles</forename>
    <forename type="middle">James</forename>
    <surname type="last">Fox</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1749">1749</birth>
  <death when="1806">1806</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 12017</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003532">
  <persName key="ENT.000003532">
    <forename type="first">Joseph</forename>
    <surname type="last">Fox</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1710">1710</birth>
  <death when="1779">1779</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000000054">
  <persName key="ENT.000000054">
    <forename type="first">Benjamin</forename>
    <surname type="last">Franklin</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1706">1706</birth>
  <death when="1790">1790</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003706">
  <persName key="ENT.000003706">
    <surname type="last">Franz Joseph I</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1830">1830</birth>
  <death when="1916">1916</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003645">
  <persName key="ENT.000003645">
    <forename type="first">Hy</forename>
    <surname type="last">Gage</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1878">1878</birth>
  <death when="1971">1971</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003555">
  <persName key="ENT.000003555">
    <forename type="first">James</forename>
    <surname type="last">Garfield</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1831">1831</birth>
  <death when="1881">1881</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">James Abram Garfield was the 20th president of the United States and was assassinated 200 days into his presidency.  He was born on November 19, 1831 in Ohio, and lost his father when he was two years old.  He graduated in 1856 from Williams College, became a classics professor, and served as president of the Western Reserve Eclectic Institute.  He became a state senator in 1859 and later a major general in the Union Army.  He served nine consecutive terms in the US House of Representatives from 1863 to 1880.  In 1880 Republicans nominated Garfield as their presidential candidate.  He won a narrow victory against his Democratic opponent Winfield S. Hancock.  As president, Garfield fought for civil service reform and called for an investigation of the Post Office.  On July 2, 1881 Charles Guiteau shot the President in a Washington D.C Railway Station.  Garfield died eighty days later on September 19, 1881.</note>
  <bibl><bibl> “James Garfield,Whitehouse.gov." accessed January 21, 2015. <ref target="http://www.whitehouse.gov/1600/presidents/jamesgarfield">Link</ref></bibl>
                <bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). <hi rendition="#italics">Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age</hi>. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe. </bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50015182
</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003734">
  <persName key="ENT.000003734">
    <forename type="first">Edmond</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Charles</forename>
    <surname type="last">Genet</surname>
    <addName type="alt">Citizen Genet</addName>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1763">1763</birth>
  <death when="1834">1834</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50024348.html; depicted in 11579</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003392">
  <persName key="ENT.000003392">
    <forename type="first">George</forename>
    <surname type="last">III</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1738">1738</birth>
  <death when="1820">1820</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">King of Great Britain and Ireland, 1760-1801; king of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, 1801-1820.</note>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79061402.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003722">
  <persName key="ENT.000003722">
    <forename type="first">Henry</forename>
    <surname type="last">George</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1839">1839</birth>
  <death when="1897">1897</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79056213&#13;
depicted in hint cartoon #12371</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003351">
  <persName key="ENT.000003351">
    <forename type="first">Bernhard</forename>
    <surname type="last">Gillam</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1856">1856</birth>
  <death when="1896">1896</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Bernhard Gillam was born on April 28, 1856 in Banbury, Oxforshire in England and was a famous 19th century American cartoonist.  At the age of ten, Gillam’s family immigrated to the United States and settled in New York.  He studied engraving and worked as a cartoonist for <hi rendition="#italics">Leslie’s Weekly</hi>,  the <hi rendition="#italics">New York Graphic</hi>, and <hi rendition="#italics">Harper’s Weekly</hi>.  Joseph Keppler later hired Gillam to work for <hi rendition="#italics">Puck</hi>, a weekly humor magazine.  At <hi rendition="#italics">Puck</hi>, Gillam characterized a number of political figures including the 1884 presidential candidate James A. Blaine.   In 1886 Gillam became part owner of the humor magazine <hi rendition="#italics">Judge</hi> where he continued to poke fun at presidential candidates and their policies.  He died of typhoid fever on January 19, 1896 in Canajoharie, New York. </p></note>
  <bibl><bibl> “Bernhard Gillam | Biography - American Cartoonist,” <hi rendition="#italics">Encyclopedia Britannica</hi>, accessed January 21, 2015.  <ref target="http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/233731/Bernhard-Gillam">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n94122577.html ; cartoonist for Puck, among other publications. created 11585-Bc612P567_1_TEI.xml</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003689">
  <persName key="ENT.000003689">
    <forename type="first">F. Victor</forename>
    <surname type="last">Gillam</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1858">1858</birth>
  <death when="1920">1920</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">Artist for Hint cartoon #12384</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003559">
  <persName key="ENT.000003559">
    <forename type="first">Jay</forename>
    <surname type="last">Gould</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1836">1836</birth>
  <death when="1892">1892</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Jay Gould was born on May 27, 1836 in Roxbury, New York and was an American railroad financier and one of the “robber barons”.  He attended Hobart Academy and worked as a surveyor.  He later began dealing in railroad stocks, became business partners with James Fisk and Daniel Drew, and formed a Wall Street Brokerage House.  In 1868, Gould, Fisk, and Drew successfully gained control of the Erie Railroad from Cornelius Vanderbilt by inflating the value of the company’s stocks.  Gould and Fisk engaged in political bribery and formed a partnership with the infamous William “Boss” Tweed.</p>
                <p>On September 24, 1869, Gould and Fisk’s financial schemes led to the panic of “Black Friday” and Gould was forced to relinquish control of the Eerie Railroad.  In the 1870s Gould bought stock of railroads in the West and gained control of several railroad companies including the Union Pacific Railroad.  He also was owner of the Western Union Telegraph Company and the <hi rendition="#italics">New York World</hi> Newspaper.  He died in New York City on December 2, 1892 and left his $72 million fortune to his children. </p></note>
  <bibl><bibl> “Jay Gould | Biography - American Financier,” <hi rendition="#italics">Encyclopedia Britannica</hi>.  accessed January 21, 2015.  <ref target="http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/239993/Jay-Gould">Link</ref></bibl>
                
                <bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). <hi rendition="#italics">Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age</hi>. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe. </bibl>
                    
                <bibl>Terrell, Ellen “Robber Barons: Gould and Fisk | Inside Adams: Science, Technology &amp; Business,” webpage, (September 26, 2012). <ref target="http://blogs.loc.gov/inside_adams/2012/09/robber-barons-gould-and-fisk/">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50035745</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003642">
  <persName key="ENT.000003642">
    <forename type="first">Friedrich</forename>
    <surname type="last">Graetz</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1840">1840</birth>
  <death when="1913">1913</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Friedrich Graetz was a cartoonist.  He was born in Austria circa 1840 and died circa 1913.  He  worked for Kikeriki in Vienna from 1872 until 1875.  He was a cartoonist for <hi rendition="#italics">Puck</hi> from 1882-1885.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>Kahn, Michael A, Richard Samuel West, Bill Watterson, and Dean Mullaney. <hi rendition="#italics">What Fools These Mortals Be!: The Story of Puck: America’s First and Most Influential Magazine of Color Political Cartoons</hi>, 2014.</bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  
    http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n94122601
</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003772">
  <persName key="ENT.000003772">
    <forename type="first">Augustus</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Henry</forename>
    <surname type="last">Fitzroy</surname>
    <addName type="alt">Duke of Grafton</addName>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1735">1735</birth>
  <death when="1811">1811</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">Prime Minister of Great Britain, 1769-1770</note>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 12017; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n87869447.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000000941">
  <persName key="ENT.000000941">
    <forename type="first">Ulysses</forename>
    <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
    <surname type="last">Grant</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1822">1822</birth>
  <death when="1885">1885</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Ulysses Simpson Grant was a Union General and the 18th President of the United States.  He served two consecutive terms as president,1869-1876.</p>
                
                <p>He was born in Point Pleasant, Ohio on April 27, 1822.  He graduated from West Point in 1843 and later became one of the most distinguished generals in the Union Army. In 1868 he was nominated to run as the Republican presidential nominee.  He won a sizeable victory over his Democratic opponent Horatio Seymour.  Grant served during Reconstruction and used the army to suppress violence perpetrated by the Ku Klux Klan.  Grant initially maintained a peace policy towards Native Americans which he eventually was forced to abandon due to the increasing violence between Native Americans and settlers.  Grant was plagued by accusations of corruption and bribery because he often accepted lavish gifts, was photographed with the infamous Jay Gould and Jay Fisk, and appointed his family members to serve in government positions.  In fact, the term “Grantism” was used to signify corruption.  Consequently, Grant was unable to secure a third term as president. </p>
                
                <p>After leaving office, Grant went bankrupt and developed throat cancer.  In order to overcome his financial difficulties, he wrote his <hi rendition="#italics">Personal Memoirs</hi>  which eventually earned over $400,000.  He died on July 23, 1885, a few days after he finished writing.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). <hi rendition="#italics">Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age</hi>. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe. </bibl>
                
                <bibl>“Ulysses S. Grant" <hi rendition="#italics">Whitehouse.gov</hi>, accessed February 4, 2015.  <ref target="http://www.whitehouse.gov/1600/presidents/ulyssessgrant">Link</ref>
                </bibl></bibl>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003352">
  <persName key="ENT.000003352">
    <forename type="first">Horace</forename>
    <surname type="last">Greeley</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1811">1811</birth>
  <death when="1872">1872</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 11561-3133_b4f11_1_TEI.xml; 11564-3133_b4f7_1_TEI.xml ; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80045878.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003350">
  <persName key="ENT.000003350">
    <forename type="first">Jean-Léon</forename>
    <surname type="last">Gérôme</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1824">1824</birth>
  <death when="1904">1904</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">Jean-Léon Gérôme was born on May 11, 1824 in Vesoul, France and was a 19th century French artist.  He was a student of Paul Delaroche and many of his paintings explored Greco-Roman themes and classical mythology.  His paintings were inspired by his travels to Egypt, the Holy Land, and Asia Minor.  In addition to being a successful painter, Gérôme was a sculptor and a teacher.</note>
  <bibl><bibl>“Jean-Leon Gerome, Biography - French Artist, Encyclopedia Britannica." accessed January 21, 2015.  <ref target="http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/231830/Jean-Leon-Gerome">Link</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl>“The Spectacular Art of Jean-Léon Gérôme, The J. Paul Getty Museum." accessed January 21, 2015. <ref target="http://www.getty.edu/art/exhibitions/gerome/">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">NOTE: LOC does not hyphenate his first name, although most other sources do. Need to make a final decision about this. http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50016499.html &#13;
&#13;
mentioned in 11585-Bc612P567_1_TEI.xml; painted Phryne Before the Aeropagus</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003782">
  <persName key="ENT.000003782">
    <forename type="first">Abraham</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Oakey</forename>
    <surname type="last">Hall</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1826">1826</birth>
  <death when="1898">1898</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">Mayor of New York City from 1868 to 1872, A. Oakey Hall was an ally of William M. "Boss" Tweed. Mayor Hall was indicted for corruption twice, eventually going into exile in London. He later returned to the United States and died in New York in 1898. Prior to becoming mayor, Hall was district attorney of New York City.</note>
  <bibl><bibl>John Adler, with Draper Hill, <hi rendition="#italics">Doomed by Cartoon: How Cartoonist Thomas Nast the “The New-York Times” Brought down Boss Tweed and His Ring of Thieves</hi> (Garden City, New York: Morgan James, 2008)</bibl>
<bibl>Encyclopedia of New York City. <ref target="http://www.virtualny.cuny.edu/EncyNYC/A_oakey_hall.html">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 12273</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003746">
  <persName key="ENT.000003746">
    <forename type="first">Alexander</forename>
    <surname type="last">Hamilton</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1757">1757</birth>
  <death when="1804">1804</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">First US Secretary of the Treasury, 1789-1795</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003603">
  <persName key="ENT.000003603">
    <forename type="first">Wade</forename>
    <surname type="last">Hampton</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1818">1818</birth>
  <death when="1902">1902</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr91026933.html; mentioned in 11820 (quoted); bio at http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wade_Hampton_III</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003565">
  <persName key="ENT.000003565">
    <forename type="first">Winfield</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Scott</forename>
    <surname type="last">Hancock</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1824">1824</birth>
  <death when="1886">1886</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Winfield Scott Hancock was born in Pennsylvania on February 14, 1824 and died on February 9, 1886.  He was a highly respected general and, in 1800, became the Democratic presidential candidate.</p>
                <p>He graduated from West Point in 1844 and fought in the Mexican War from 1846 to 1848.  During the Civil War, he was appointed brigadier general.  He served with distinction at several important Civil War battles including Antietam, Fredericksburg, and Gettysburg.  After the war he was appointed major general and commanded the Central Military Department and the Department of Louisiana and Texas.  His views and policies concerning Reconstruction made him well respected within the Democratic Party, and in 1880 he became their presidential nominee.  He narrowly lost the election to James A. Garfield.  Hancock died on February 9, 1886 in New York City.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>“Winfield Scott Hancock , Biography ,United States Military Officer, Encyclopedia Britannica,” accessed February 11, 2015.  <ref target="http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/254062/Winfield-Scott-Hancock">Link</ref></bibl>
                
                <bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). <hi rendition="#italics">Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age</hi>. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe. </bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n87918075</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000001948">
  <persName key="ENT.000001948">
    <forename type="first">Benjamin</forename>
    <surname type="last">Harrison</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1833">1833</birth>
  <death when="1901">1901</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">Benjamin Harrison was the 23rd President of the United States.  He was born on August 20, 1833 in North Bend, Ohio and later practiced law.  He served in the Civil War and became a colonel.  In 1876, he unsuccessfully ran for governor of Indiana, but, four years later, was elected to serve in the US Senate.  In 1884 he lost the Republican presidential nomination to James Blaine and then in 1886 lost reelection to the Senate.  Two years later, however, he ran for president and launched a well organized and successful “front-porch” campaign in which he did not travel, but gave numerous speeches to visiting supporters.  He narrowly defeated the democratic incumbent Grover Cleveland, becoming the 23rd President of the United States.  At 5 feet 6 inches tall, Harrison became one the shortest US presidents, and democrats nicknamed him “Little Ben.”  As president, Harrison hosted the first Pan American Congress in 1889 and helped establish what would later become the Pan American Union.  He put forth legislation in Congress for the annexation of Hawaii which ultimately failed, signed the Sherman Anti-Trust law, and bolstered the American navy.  He ran for second term, but lost to Cleveland.  He died on March 13, 1901 in Indianapolis.</note>
  <bibl><bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). <hi rendition="#italics">Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age</hi>. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe. </bibl>
                <bibl>“Benjamin Harrison ,Whitehouse.gov,” accessed February 11, 2015.  <ref target="http://www.whitehouse.gov/1600/presidents/benjaminharrison">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50026594</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003685">
  <persName key="ENT.000003685">
    <forename type="first">William</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Francis</forename>
    <surname type="last">Harrity</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1850">1850</birth>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2005080164</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003607">
  <persName key="ENT.000003607">
    <forename type="first">Wencel</forename>
    <surname type="last">Hartman</surname>
  </persName>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003766">
  <persName key="ENT.000003766">
    <forename type="first">Hastings</forename>
    <surname type="last">Daniel</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1849">1849</birth>
  <death when="1903">1903</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n89649153&#13;
&#13;
depicted in HINT cartoon #11940 and 12020</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003567">
  <persName key="ENT.000003567">
    <forename type="first">Rutherford</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Birchard</forename>
    <surname type="last">Hayes</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1822">1822</birth>
  <death when="1893">1893</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Rutherford Hayes was the nineteenth President of the United States and the first US president to graduate from law school.</p>
                <p>Hayes was born in Ohio and was raised by a single mother. His father died ten weeks before Hayes’ birth.  During the Civil War, he served as major general for the Union Army was wounded in battle five times, but continued to serve. Because of his bravery in battle, he quickly earned a reputation as war hero and, in 1864, was elected to serve in the United States House of Representatives.  He served from 1865-1867 and later became the Governor of Ohio from 1868-1872 and 1876-1877.  </p>
                <p>In 1876, Hayes became the Republican presidential nominee, defeating popular republican politicians such as James G. Blaine and Roscoe Conkling.  His Democratic opponent, Samuel Tilden of New York, was a formidable opponent, excellent campaigner, and well-known reformer.  </p>
                <p>The 1876 presidential election became one of the most contested in US history. The votes were so close that both candidates could claim victory in Florida, South Carolina, Louisiana, and Oregon.  In order to decide the election, Congress organized a special electoral commission.  The fifteen member commission awarded the presidency to Hayes which led some to question the legitimacy of his presidency. Some Democrats nicknamed Hayes “Rutherfraud” and “His Fraudulency.”</p>
                <p>Hayes sought to strengthen the presidency and to end the practice of political patronage.  His civil service reforms put him at constant odds with Senator Roscoe Conkling of New York. He served only one term and did not seek re-election in 1880.  He died in 1893.</p>
</note>
  <bibl><bibl>“American President: Rutherford Birchard Hayes: A Life in Brief.” <hi rendition="#italics">University of Virginia Miller Center</hi>, Accessed June 4, 2015.  <ref target="http://millercenter.org/academic/americanpresident/hayes/essays/biography/1">Link</ref></bibl>
                <bibl>“Rutherford Birchard Hayes,  Presidents of the United States (POTUS).” <hi rendition="#italics">Ipl2</hi>, Accessed June 4, 2015. <ref target="http://www.ipl.org/div/potus/rbhayes.html">Link</ref></bibl>
                <bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). <hi rendition="#italics">Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age</hi>. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe.</bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50025146
in cartoon 1801 "let us have peace"</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003768">
  <persName key="ENT.000003768">
    <forename type="first">George</forename>
    <surname type="last">Hayley</surname>
  </persName>
  <death when="1781">1781</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">Depicted in 12017; bio at http://www.historyofparliamentonline.org/volume/1754-1790/member/hayley-george-1781</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003605">
  <persName key="ENT.000003605">
    <forename type="first">William</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Randolph</forename>
    <surname type="last">Hearst</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1863">1863</birth>
  <death when="1951">1951</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>William Randolph Hearst was a journalist, editor, and newspaper publisher.</p>
                <p>He was born on April 29, 1863 in California.  He attended Harvard College for two years and was expelled for bad behavior.  In 1887, he purchased the <hi rendition="#italics">San Francisco Examiner</hi>.  In 1895, he bought the struggling <hi rendition="#italics">New York Evening Journal</hi> and dramatically increased its circulation by hiring skilled journalists and lowering production costs.  Hearst used sensationalist news stories to boost newspaper sales.  In 1898, Hearst accused Spain of the sinking the <hi rendition="#italics">USS Maine</hi> off the coast of Cuba.  Although he did not have any real evidence for his claims against Spain, Hearst’s editorials enraged the American public and helped bolster support for American military involvement in the Cuban Revolution. </p> 
                <p>Hearst served in Congress (1903-1907) and unsuccessfully ran for the Democratic Party nomination in 1904.  At the height of his career, he owned 28 newspapers and 18 magazines, as well as, several movie production and radio companies.  He died on August 14, 1951 in California.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). <hi rendition="#italics">Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age</hi>. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe.</bibl>
                <bibl>“William Randolph Hearst.” <hi rendition="#italics">Encyclopedia Britannica Online</hi>. Accessed June 30, 2015. <ref target="http://www.britannica.com/biography/William-Randolph-Hearst">Link</ref></bibl>
                </bibl>
  <note type="internal">LOC 
    http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80004058
</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003569">
  <persName key="ENT.000003569">
    <forename type="first">Abram</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Stevens</forename>
    <surname type="last">Hewitt</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1822">1822</birth>
  <death when="1903">1903</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Abram Stevens Hewitt served five terms in the United States Congress, and one term as mayor of New York.
He was born in Haverstraw, New York in 1822 and attended Columbia College where he studied law. Shortly after, he became an iron manufacturer when he entered into business with his brother-in-law and formed Copper, Hewitt, &amp; Company. Hewitt served in Congress from 1875-1886.  As a congressman, he fought for tariff reform and served as the Democratic Committee chairman during the disputed presidential election of 1876 in which Democratic candidate Samuel Tilden lost to Rutherford B. Hayes.  In 1883, alongside New York senators William Robinson and Samuel Cox, Hewitt petitioned the President Chester A. Arthur to intervene on behalf of Patrick O’Donnell, a United States citizen who on trial in the United Kingdom for murder.  O’Donnell was found guilty and executed in London.</p>
<p>In 1886 Hewitt became mayor of New York City and tried to end the political influence of Tammany Hall.  He angered many Irish-Americans in New York for his immigration policies and his refusal to allow the Irish flag to be flown during the St. Patrick’s Day Parade.  Hewitt served only one term as mayor.  He died on January 18, 1903 in New York City.</p>
</note>
  <bibl><bibl>“Hewitt, Abram Stevens.”  <hi rendition="#italics">Biographical Directory of the United States Congress</hi>, Accessed June 4, 2015.  <ref target="http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=h000552">Link</ref></bibl>
<bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). <hi rendition="#italics">Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age</hi>. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe.</bibl> </bibl>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n86012017</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003726">
  <persName key="ENT.000003726">
    <forename type="first">David</forename>
    <surname type="last">Hosack</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1769">1769</birth>
  <death when="1835">1835</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n84804805.html; depicted in 11824 (one of the doctors)</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003735">
  <persName key="ENT.000003735">
    <forename type="first">James</forename>
    <surname type="last">Hutchinson</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1752">1752</birth>
  <death when="1793">1793</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">Dr. James Hutchinson was a Pennsylvania physician and surgeon, active in Revolutionary politics. He was friends with Benjamin Franklin, a supporter of Pennsylvania's 1776 Constitution, an Anti-Federalist, and a founder of Pennsylvania's Democratic Society. He may be depicted in the 1796 cartoon "A Peep into the Antifederalist Club" as the fat man drinking wine and cursing government.</note>
  <bibl><bibl>"James Hutchinson (1752-1793)," Penn University Archives and Records Center, accessed May 12, 2015. <ref target="http://www.archives.upenn.edu/people/1700s/hutchinson_jas.html">Link</ref></bibl>
<bibl>James C. Kelly and B. S. Lovell, "Thomas Jefferson: His Friends and Foes," <hi rendition="#italics">Virginia Magazine of History and Biography</hi> 101 (1993): 145.</bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr92034134.html; depicted in 11579. See also http://www.archives.upenn.edu/people/1700s/hutchinson_jas.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000002863">
  <persName key="ENT.000002863">
    <forename type="first">Anthony</forename>
    <surname type="last">Imbert</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1794">1794</birth>
  <death when="1834">1834</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Anthony Imbert is credited with producing the first lithographed political cartoon in America, <hi rendition="#italics">A New Map of the United States with the Additional Territories on an Improved Plan</hi> (1829). He was a French immigrant, believed to be born in Calais in 1794 or 1795 and to have served as an officer in the French navy during the Napoleonic Wars, during which time he was captured by the British and imprisoned between 1810 and 1814. At some point he immigrated to New York; city directories identifying him as a “painter” place him in the city by at least 1825. In 1825 he began his own lithography firm and soon gained renown for producing the plates for <hi rendition="#italics">Memoir</hi>, a commemorative book by Cadwallader D. Colden celebrating the completion of the Erie Canal. The 35 plates in <hi rendition="#italics">Memoir</hi>showed a variety of new lithographic techniques, and the book’s text proclaimed Imbert’s relatively new lithography business “the most prominent in New York,” which was very likely an exaggeration. Imbert became well known as a lithographer of landscapes, and flourished as the Hudson River School style and interest in New York scenes grew.</p>
<p>Imbert began lithographing music scores in 1827 and caricatures and satirical images in 1828; between 1828 and his death in 1834 he issued 19 cartoons, more than double that of any other publisher in the country.</p>
</note>
  <bibl><bibl>John Carbonell, “Anthony Imbert: New York’s Pioneer Lithographer,” in <hi rendition="#italics">Prints and Printmakers of New York State, 1825-1940</hi>, edited by David Tatham (Syracuse, NY: Syracuse University Press, 1986), 11-41.</bibl>
<bibl>William Murrell, <hi rendition="#italics">A History of American Graphic Humor</hi>, vol. 1, 1747-1865 (New York: Whitney Museum of American Art, 1933), 115-116.</bibl>
</bibl>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr90027492.html. </note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000002223">
  <persName key="ENT.000002223">
    <forename type="first">Andrew</forename>
    <surname type="last">Jackson</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1767">1767</birth>
  <death when="1845">1845</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Andrew Jackson was the military hero and seventh president of the United States. Jackson was born in western South Carolina to a recently widowed mother with two young sons. By age fourteen, Jackson had lost his brothers and mother as well. Despite this inauspicious beginning, Jackson became a successful lawyer and politician in Tennessee, where he had settled in 1788. Jackson served in the convention that drafted Tennessee’s constitution, and then, once Tennessee was admitted to statehood, he became the state’s sole representative to the US House of Representatives in 1796. In 1797 he was elected to the US Senate. After a short, undistinguished congressional career, Jackson resigned from the Senate to serve on the Superior Court of Tennessee. 
</p>
<p>Jackson’s military career included command of Tennessee forces in the Creek War of 1813, which led to his commission as major general in the US Army in 1814. He is best known for his victory of the British in the Battle of New Orleans at the conclusion of the War of 1812. This victory made Jackson a national hero. Jackson’s soldiers named him “Old Hickory” because of his strength during hardship. In 1818 he led an expedition that captured Florida, and then in 1821 he served as governor of the new territory. He resigned that post in 1821 and returned to Tennessee, where the state legislature nominated him for president in 1822.</p>

<p>Jackson was one of four candidates for president in 1824. Jackson won a plurality of the popular vote, but because he did not have a majority, the election was decided by the House of Representatives, which selected John Quincy Adams, who then named fourth-place finisher Henry Clay as secretary of state in what Jackson labeled a “corrupt bargain.” With that, Jackson’s 1828 campaign for the presidency began and the Jacksonian Democratic Party was born. The 1828 campaign between Andrew Jackson and John Quincy Adams was one of the nation’s nastiest. Jackson won by a wide margin.</p>

<p>Jackson was a champion of the common man and of majority rule, and used his veto to strike at what he considered to be special interests. He also was a strong nationalist and rejected Vice President John Calhoun’s belief that states could nullify federal legislation they disliked. Calhoun and Jackson broke over nullification and other issues and Martin Van Buren ran with Jackson for vice president in 1832. Recharter of the powerful Second Bank of the United States became the primary issue during the 1832 presidential campaign between Jackson and Henry Clay. In July 1832, Jackson had vetoed a bill to recharter the bank sponsored by Clay. Jackson then defeated Clay in the presidential election and in 1833 he ordered that government funds be moved from the Bank of the United States and placed in selected state banks. Jackson’s adversaries depicted him as a tyrant, labeling him “King Andrew.” No doubt, Jackson was a divisive figure in American politics. By the end of this presidency, the clear two party system, Whigs and Democrats, was in place.</p>

<p>Jackson returned to Tennessee in 1837, where he died in 1845.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>“Andrew Jackson.” <hi rendition="#italics">Tennessee Encyclopedia of History and Culture</hi>. <ref target="http://tennesseeencyclopedia.net/entry.php?rec=695">Link</ref></bibl>

<bibl>“Jackson, Andrew.” <hi rendition="#italics">American National Biography</hi>.</bibl>

                <bibl>“Jackson, Andrew.” <hi rendition="#italics">Biographical Directory of the United States Congress</hi>. <ref target="http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=j000005">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">Andrew Jackson is referred to as "Old Hickory" in cartoon with DAMS #5545.  His biography should include a brief explanation of the origin of this nickname.</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003684">
  <persName key="ENT.000003684">
    <forename type="first">James</forename>
    <surname type="last">Elverson</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1838">1838</birth>
  <death when="1911">1911</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Publisher for the <hi rendition="#italics">Philadelphia Inquirer</hi>.   Elverson was born in England and immigrated to the United States in 1817. He purchased the newspaper in 1889. </p> </note>
  <bibl>    <bibl>“The Gazette Times - Google News Archive Search.” Accessed April 15, 2015. <ref target="https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1126&amp;dat=19110211&amp;id=VcIwAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=HWYDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4550,5496469&amp;hl=en">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">Phila Inquirer publisher.</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003533">
  <persName key="ENT.000003533">
    <forename type="first">Abel</forename>
    <surname type="last">James</surname>
  </persName>
  <death when="1790">1790</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000000045">
  <persName key="ENT.000000045">
    <forename type="first">Thomas</forename>
    <surname type="last">Jefferson</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1743">1743</birth>
  <death when="1826">1826</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">may be depicted in 11579 (man standing on table)</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003563">
  <persName key="ENT.000003563">
    <forename type="first">Marshall</forename>
    <surname type="last">Jewell</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1825">1825</birth>
  <death when="1883">1883</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Marshall Jewell was a businessman, Republican Governor of Connecticut, and Minister to Russia.</p>
                <p>Jewell was born in 1825 in New Hampshire.  He owned a profitable tanning business which he inherited from his father. He entered politics in the 1860s and unsuccessfully ran for the US Senate in 1867.  The following year he was elected as the Governor of Connecticut and served two terms from 1869-1873.  In 1873, he served seven months as Minister to Russia during President Ulysses S. Grant’s administration.  He became postmaster general from 1874-1876 and Republican National Committee Chairman from 1880-1883.  Jewell died in Connecticut on February 10, 1883 from pneumonia.</p></note>
  <bibl>  <bibl>“Marshall Jewell (1825–1883).” <hi rendition="#italics">Cedar Hill Cemetery Foundation</hi>, Accessed June 4, 2015. <ref target="http://cedarhillfoundation.org/notable-residents/marshall-jewell/">Link</ref></bibl>
                
                <bibl>“Marshall Jewell (1874–1876).” <hi rendition="#italics">University of Virginia Miller Center</hi>, Accessed  June 4, 2015. <ref target="http://millercenter.org/president/grant/essays/cabinet/321">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr2001043325.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003564">
  <persName key="ENT.000003564">
    <forename type="first">John</forename>
    <surname type="last">Kelly</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1822">1822</birth>
  <death when="1886">1886</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>John Kelly was a businessman, Democratic politician, and Tammany Hall leader. He was born in 1822 in New York City and was the son of Irish-Catholic immigrates.</p>
<p>As a young man, Kelly was forced to quit school and support his family when his father died. He worked as an apprentice and later opened his own profitable business.  He completed his education by attending night school and in 1855 was elected to the US House of Representatives.  In 1859 he became city and county sheriff.  He unsuccessfully ran for mayor in 1868 and became leader of Tammany Hall in 1873.  He Kelly died in 1886 in New York City.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>“John Kelly, Elections 1880 Biographies.” <hi rendition="#italics">HarpWeek</hi>, Accessed June 5, 2015. <ref target= "http://elections.harpweek.com/1880/bio-1880-Full.asp?UniqueID=7&amp;Year=1880">Link</ref></bibl>

                <bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). <hi rendition="#italics">Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age</hi>. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe.</bibl> </bibl>
  <note type="internal">In HINT cartoon 1801</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003356">
  <persName key="ENT.000003356">
    <forename type="first">Andrew</forename>
    <surname type="last">Johnson</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1808">1808</birth>
  <death when="1875">1875</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>
Andrew Johnson was the seventeenth president of the United States, taking office after Abraham Lincoln’s assassination in April 1865. Johnson was a southern Democrat, born in North Carolina and living most of his life in East Tennessee. Johnson grew up in a poor family, lost his father at an early age, and was apprenticed to a tailor, and then ran away. He settled in Greeneville, Tennessee, where he set up a tailor shop, married, raised a family, and entered local politics. In 1835 he was elected to the Tennessee legislature, lost that seat in 1837, and then regained it in 1839. In 1843 he was elected to the US House of Representatives as a Jacksonian Democrat.  He served in the House for ten years, where he was a sponsor of the homestead bill, which provided western settlers with public land. This support alienated many southern conservatives since this measure could weaken slavery. Johnson was not abolitionist, however. Indeed, he owned several slaves and was a strong believer in white supremacy and state’s rights. When gerrymandered out of his House seat in 1853, Johnson ran for governor of Tennessee instead, and won. In 1857 he was chosen US Senator. In the Senate he continued his advocacy for the homestead bill. </p>

<p>In 1860, Johnson hoped to run for the presidency on the Democratic ticket. He was unsuccessful in securing the nomination, and when the party split, he endorsed the proslavery ticket of John Breckenridge and Joseph Lane. Following Abraham Lincoln’s election, however, Johnson remained a strong Unionist and opposed secession. He remained in the Senate during the secession crisis, even after Tennessee seceded from the Union—though East Tennessee remained Unionist. This action made Johnson a hero in the North. In March 1862, after the fall of Nashville, Lincoln appointed Johnson military governor of Tennessee.
</p>
<p>In 1864, in an effort to attract war Democrats to the Lincoln ticket, the National Union Part nominated Johnson for vice president. He served as vice president for just over a month before Lincoln was assassinated and Johnson assumed the presidency. Because he believed that the Southern states had never actually seceded and in state’s rights, he initiated a Reconstruction policy that angered Northern Radical Republicans. He pardoned nearly all Southerners who would take an oath of allegiance, requiring only Southern leaders and men of wealth to obtain special presidential pardons. He also did not insist that Southern states enfranchise freedmen. These policies set up a battle with the Congress. Johnson vetoed several measures, including, in February 1866, the Freedman’s Bureau bill, and in March 1866, a civil rights bill. Congress overrode the veto of the Civil Rights Act and passed a new Freedman’s Bureau bill in June 1866, which Johnson was not able to veto. In fall 1866 Radical Republicans won in the congressional elections, further weakening Johnson. In 1867, he attempted to settle remaining claims with Great Britain, including the <hi rendition="#italics">Alabama</hi> claims for damages to North from British built ships serving the Confederacy, but his efforts were rejected by the Senate. In March 1867, Congress enacted the Tenure of Office Act, which required Senate approval for dismissal of presidential appointees, and also began their own Reconstruction program. They also began efforts to impeach Johnson. After one failed attempt, Johnson was impeached for violations of the Tenure of Office Act in February 1868. The Senate then acquitted him by one vote in May 1868. In March 1869, Johnson left the presidency and returned to Tennessee. In 1875 he was returned to the US Senate. He died a few months later in Carter’s Station, Tennessee.
</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>“Johnson, Andrew.” <hi rendition="#italics">American National Biography</hi></bibl>.

                <bibl>“Andrew Johnson.” <hi rendition="#italics">WhiteHouse.gov</hi>. <ref target="https://www.whitehouse.gov/1600/presidents/andrewjohnson">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">depicted 11512-3133_b1f32_1_TEI.xml (meteors at washington); 11572-3133_b3f18_1_TEI.xml (bagatelle) ; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79056304.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000000443">
  <persName key="ENT.000000443">
    <forename type="first">Herbert</forename>
    <surname type="last">Johnson</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1878">1878</birth>
  <death when="1946">1946</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003704">
  <persName key="ENT.000003704">
    <forename type="first">John</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Percival</forename>
    <surname type="last">Jones</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1829">1829</birth>
  <death when="1912">1912</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">Depicted in Hint cartoon 11834
LOC:  
    http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n86834912
</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003764">
  <persName key="ENT.000003764">
    <forename type="first">Charles</forename>
    <forename type="middle">John</forename>
    <surname type="last">Kean</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1811">1811</birth>
  <death when="1868">1868</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">Mentioned in 8306 (title)</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003357">
  <persName key="ENT.000003357">
    <forename type="first">John</forename>
    <surname type="last">Kearsley</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1684">1684</birth>
  <death when="1772">1772</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 2562-Bb612L615_1_TEI.xml (Liberty Triumphant) ; http://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=gr&amp;GRid=8160303 ; E. P. Richardson, "Four American Political Prints," American Art Journal 6, no. 2 (37-38) ; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr89012469.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003702">
  <persName key="ENT.000003702">
    <forename type="first">Joseph</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Warren</forename>
    <surname type="last">Keifer</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1836">1836</birth>
  <death when="1932">1932</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr94020631&#13;
Depicted in Hint cartoon 11834</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003164">
  <persName key="ENT.000003164">
    <forename type="first">George</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Frederick</forename>
    <surname type="last">Keller</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1846">1846</birth>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>George Frederick Keller was born in 1846 in Prussia and immigrated to the United States.  He settled in San Francisco where he worked as an apprentice for a lithographer.  He later partnered with F.M. Griswold to open a short-lived lithography business.  Keller worked for the <hi rendition="#italics">Wasp</hi> from 1876-1883.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>West, Richard Samuel. 2004. <hi rendition="#italics">The San Francisco Wasp: an Illustrated History</hi>. Easthampton, Mass: Periodyssey Press.</bibl></bibl>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000001353">
  <persName key="ENT.000001353">
    <forename type="first">Fanny</forename>
    <surname type="last">Kemble</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1809">1809</birth>
  <death when="1893">1893</death>
  <sex>Female</sex>
  <note type="biography">British actress and author, lampooned in early American political cartoons for her critical remarks on American manners.</note>
  <bibl>William Murrell, <hi rendition="#italics">A History of American Graphic Humor</hi>, vol. 1, 1747-1865 (New York: Whitney Museum of American Art, 1933), 138</bibl>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003761">
  <persName key="ENT.000003761">
    <forename type="first">Amos</forename>
    <surname type="last">Kendall</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1789">1789</birth>
  <death when="1869">1869</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">Mentioned in DAMS record # 1778. http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n85829991.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003758">
  <persName key="ENT.000003758">
    <forename type="first">Samuel</forename>
    <surname type="last">Kennedy</surname>
  </persName>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">Artist of 11825, with William Charles</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000000379">
  <persName key="ENT.000000379">
    <forename type="first">Joseph</forename>
    <surname type="last">Keppler</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1838">1838</birth>
  <death when="1894">1894</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Joseph Keppler was a cartoonist and founder of<hi rendition="#italics"> Puck</hi>.</p>
<p>Keppler was born in Austria on February 1, 1838 and was the son of Johann and Josepha Keppler.  After the Revolution of 1848 in Austria, Keppler’s father was forced to leave the country because of his political beliefs and fled to the United States.  Joseph Keppler remained in Vienna with his mother and three younger siblings and attended the Academy of Fine Arts and the Elementary Drawing and Modeling School.  When he was seventeen years old, he traveled throughout Europe, earning a modest living as a painter.  He joined a traveling theatrical company, designed their sets, performed on stage, and spent the next several years traveling.  In 1864, he married Minna Rubens and sought more stable employment.  He worked for time as a cartoonist for the humor magazine <hi rendition="#italics">Kikeriki</hi>.  In 1867, he immigrated to the United States.  He founded two short-lived magazines including a German language weekly and then moved to New York in 1875 to work as an artist for <hi rendition="#italics">Frank Leslie’s Illustrated Newspaper</hi>.   In 1876, he founded <hi rendition="#italics">Puck</hi>, a German language humor magazine, and a year later, began an English version which continued publication until 1918.  Puck stood out from other 19th century American magazines because of its large size and its color lithographs.  Keppler hired talented cartoonists such as Frederick Opper, Bernard Gillam, and James A. Wales.   The magazine covered topics such as immigration, political scandals, and presidential elections and its cartoons were heavily influenced by contemporary and classical art and literature.  Keppler died in New York in 1894.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>Hess, Stephen and Milton Kaplan. <hi rendition="#italics">The Ungentlemanly Art:   A History of American Political Cartoons</hi>.  New York: Macmillan, 1968.</bibl>

<bibl>West, Richard Samuel. <hi rendition="#italics">Satire On Stone: The Political Cartoons of Joseph Keppler.</hi> Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1988.</bibl>

<bibl>“Joseph Keppler.” <hi rendition="#italics">Encyclopedia Britannica Online</hi>.  Accessed June 9, 2015. <ref target="http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/315289/Joseph-Keppler">Link</ref>
</bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n87932523.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003358">
  <persName key="ENT.000003358">
    <forename type="first">Philander</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Chase</forename>
    <surname type="last">Knox</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1853">1853</birth>
  <death when="1921">1921</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted 11525-3133_b2f8_1_TEI.xml; 1782-3313_b2f8_1 ; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n86053399.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000002824">
  <persName key="ENT.000002824">
    <forename type="first">Robert E. (Robert Edward)</forename>
    <surname type="last">Lee</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1807">1807</birth>
  <death when="1870">1870</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">mentioned in 11756</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003644">
  <persName key="ENT.000003644">
    <surname type="last">Leo XIII</surname>
    <addName type="alt">Pecci, Gioacchino Vincenzo, 1810-1903</addName>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1810">1810</birth>
  <death when="1903">1903</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Gioacchino Vincenzo Raffaele Luigi Pecci was born on March 2, 1810 in Carpineto, a town near Rome.  He was ordained on December 31, 1837.  In February 1838, he was appointed legate to Benevento, a small papal province with widespread corruption and poverty.  Three years later he was appointed to serve as legate of Spoleto, but at the last minute was sent to Perugia where he worked to help the poor and to end corruption.  In 1846 he was appointed Archbishop of Perugia where he served until 1877.  In 1878, following the death of Pope Pius IX, he was elected to the papacy.  He died at the age of 93 in Rome on July 20, 1903. </p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>“Catholic Encyclopedia: Pope Leo XIII.” <hi rendition="#italics">New Advent</hi>. Accessed June 8, 2015. <ref target="http://newadvent.org/cathen/09169a.htm">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n82060350. depicted in hint cartoon 1368</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000000447">
  <persName key="ENT.000000447">
    <forename type="first">Abraham</forename>
    <surname type="last">Lincoln</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1809">1809</birth>
  <death when="1865">1865</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Abraham Lincoln was elected sixteenth present of the United States in 1860, leading to the secession of the Southern states and the American Civil War. Lincoln was born to poor parents in Kentucky in 1809, spent some of his childhood in Indiana, then moved with his family to Illinois in the 1830s. As a young man, Lincoln earned some money splitting rails for other farmers, earning him the nickname the “Rail Splitter” later in life. In 1831 he settled in New Salem, Illinois, where he worked several jobs, joined a debating society, and became interested in politics. In 1834 he won election to the Illinois legislature as a Whig. While in the legislature, Lincoln studied law and obtained his license and began his legal practice. He retired from the legislature in 1841 and continued his legal practice. In 1842, he married Mary Todd, with whom he had four sons. In 1846, Lincoln achieved his ambition to serve in Congress, and he served in Congress from 1847 to 1849. He then returned to his legal practice in Springfield, Illinois. In 1854, passage of the Kansas-Nebraska Act propelled Lincoln back into politics. Lincoln strongly opposed of the extension of slavery into the western territories and he ran for the state legislature on a platform that opposed the act. In February 1855, however, he resigned from the legislature to become the Whig candidate for the US Senate but he failed to secure that seat. In 1858, the Republican Party nominated Lincoln its candidate for US Senate against Democrat Stephen Douglas. The famous Lincoln-Douglas debates over the extension of slavery brought Lincoln to national attention—though the state legislature reappointed Douglas to the Senate.
</p>
<p>When it came time to nominate a candidate for president in 1860, Lincoln emerged from the Republican National Convention in Chicago as the Republican nominee, beating out leading candidate William H. Seward of New York. The four-way election, with the Democrats split between northern and southern wings and a remnant of the Whig Party reorganizing as the Constitutional Union Party, allowed Lincoln to win the presidency with only 40 percent of the popular vote. Lincoln’s election precipitated the secession of the Southern states in the winter of 1860-61. Within weeks of Lincoln’s open rebellion began with the firing on Fort Sumter by Confederate soldiers. Originally a war to preserve the Union, by 1862, Lincoln was under pressure make the abolition of slavery a war aim. Instead, Lincoln moved to end slavery in those Confederate states still in rebellion as a military tactic. After issuing a draft proclamation in September 1862, Lincoln issued the final Emancipation Proclamation on January 1, 1863.</p>

<p>While waging war against the Southern states, Lincoln also faced a tough battle within his party and his administration. Disagreements over prosecution of the war and its aftermath led to a contentious Republican nominating convention in 1864. Lincoln won the nomination, and the election, defeating his former general, George McClellan, who ran on the Democratic ticket. Lincoln lived to see the end of the war, but not the enactment of his Reconstruction policies. He was shot at while watching a comedy at Ford’s Theatre in Washington, DC, on April 14, 1865, and he died the following morning.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>“Lincoln, Abraham.” <hi rendition="#italics">American National Biography</hi>.</bibl>

                <bibl>“Abraham Lincoln.” <hi rendition="#italics">WhiteHouse.gov</hi>. <ref target="https://www.whitehouse.gov/1600/presidents/abrahamlincoln">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 11562, 11564, 11563, 11511, 2189, 996</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000002461">
  <persName key="ENT.000002461">
    <forename type="first">Robert</forename>
    <forename type="middle">R.</forename>
    <surname type="last">Livingston</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1746">1746</birth>
  <death when="1813">1813</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">Robert R. Livingston was a diplomat, lawyer, and statesman who helped draft the Declaration of Independence. He was the US secretary of foreign affairs from 1781 to 1783. He may be pictured in the 1796 political cartoon "A Peep into the Antifederal Club" as the tiny, doll-like figure perched on the knee of either George or DeWitt Clinton.</note>
  <bibl><bibl>"A Peep into the Antifederal Club - JCB Political Cartoons." Accessed May 12, 2015. <ref target="http://jcb.lunaimaging.com/luna/servlet/detail/JCBMAPS~2~2~656~100498:A-Peep-into-the-Antifederal-Club">Link</ref></bibl>
<bibl><hi rendition="#italics">Made in America: Printmaking, 1760-1860</hi> (Philadelphia: Library Company of Philadelphia, 1973), 11-12</bibl></bibl>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003362">
  <persName key="ENT.000003362">
    <forename type="first">John</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Alexander</forename>
    <surname type="last">Logan</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1826">1826</birth>
  <death when="1886">1886</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>
John Alexander Logan was a lawyer, Republican politician and soldier.</p>
<p>Logan was born in 1826 in Illinois.  He fought in the Mexican War as a lieutenant and later became a lawyer.  In 1852, he was elected to the Illinois House of Representatives and later, in 1859, to the United States House of Representatives.  He served until 1862 and then joined the Union Army.  He served as a brigadier general and was later appointed major general of Volunteers.  He became a US Senator and served from 1871 to 1877 and 1879 to 1886.  In 1884, he became James Blaine’s vice presidential running mate and lost the election to the Democrats Grover Cleveland and Thomas A. Hendricks.  Logan died two years later and is buried in Washington, D.C.</p>
</note>
  <bibl><bibl>“Logan, John Alexander.”  <hi rendition="#italics">Biographical Directory of the United States Congress</hi>, Accessed June 5, 2015.  <ref target="http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=l000403">Link</ref></bibl>
                <bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). <hi rendition="#italics">Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age</hi>. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe.</bibl> </bibl>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 11585-Bc612P567_1_TEI.xml ; &#13;
http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79072806</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003363">
  <persName key="ENT.000003363">
    <forename type="first">Joseph</forename>
    <surname type="last">Loring</surname>
  </persName>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">mentioned in 2562-Bb612L615_1_TEI.xml (Liberty Triumphant)&#13;
http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr2007000099.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003641">
  <persName key="ENT.000003641">
    <forename type="first">James</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Russell</forename>
    <surname type="last">Lowell</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1819">1819</birth>
  <death when="1891">1891</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">
<p>James Russell Lowell was an American poet and diplomat.</p>
<p>Lowell was born in 1819 in Cambridge, Massachusetts and studied law at Harvard University.  In 1845 he wrote a series of essays against slavery and later published the Biglow Papers, a satirical collection of poems against slavery and the Mexican War.  His other famous works include The Vision of Sir Launfal and A Fable for Critics.  In 1877 President Rutherford B. Hayes appointed Lowell Minister to Spain.  Three years later, he was appointed Ambassador to Great Britain and served from 1880 to 1885.  He died in 1891.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>“James Russell Lowell, Biography, American Poet and Critic” <hi rendition="#italics">Britannica.com</hi>, Accessed June 5, 2015.  <ref target="http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/349823/James-Russell-Lowell"></ref></bibl>

<bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). <hi rendition="#italics">Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age</hi>. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe.</bibl> </bibl>
  <note type="internal">LOC: http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79076124


</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000002471">
  <persName key="ENT.000002471">
    <forename type="first">James</forename>
    <surname type="last">Madison</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1751">1751</birth>
  <death when="1836">1836</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80067022.html; depicted in 8532;&#13;
fourth president of the United States (1809-1817). Not to be confused with James Madison (1749-1812), who was a bishop.</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000001003">
  <persName key="ENT.000001003">
    <forename type="first">John</forename>
    <forename type="middle">L.</forename>
    <surname type="last">Magee</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1820">1820</birth>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">Artist/publisher of lithographs and political cartoons. Bio at http://lcpdams.librarycompany.org:8881/R/?func=dbin-jump-full&amp;object_id=79511&amp;local_base=GEN01; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n85352336.html.</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003654">
  <persName key="ENT.000003654">
    <addName type="honorific">Major</addName>
    <forename type="first">Barclay Harding</forename>
    <surname type="last">Warburton</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1866">1866</birth>
  <death when="1954">1954</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">Publisher of Evening Telegraph (Phila.)</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003721">
  <persName key="ENT.000003721">
    <forename type="first">William</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Learned</forename>
    <surname type="last">Marcy</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1756">1756</birth>
  <death when="1857">1857</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n86111463.html; depicted in 11730</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000000259">
  <persName key="ENT.000000259">
    <forename type="first">David</forename>
    <surname type="last">Martin</surname>
  </persName>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003719">
  <persName key="ENT.000003719">
    <forename type="first">James Campbell</forename>
    <surname type="last">Matthews</surname>
  </persName>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in hint cartoon #12376. </note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003364">
  <persName key="ENT.000003364">
    <forename type="first">Louis</forename>
    <surname type="last">Maurer</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1832">1832</birth>
  <death when="1932">1932</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">lithographer for Currier &amp; Ives, http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_Maurer; responsible for 11561 (The Political Gymnasium); 11564l (Cat out of the bag); 11563 (National Game); http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr00026936.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000001783">
  <persName key="ENT.000001783">
    <forename type="first">George</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Brinton</forename>
    <surname type="last">McClellan</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1826">1826</birth>
  <death when="1885">1885</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>
George Brinton McClellan was a Civil War general and presidential candidate. He was beloved by his troops but exasperating to President Lincoln, and he is ultimately remembered more for his failures than for his successes. George McClellan was born in 1826 in Philadelphia, where he studied law at the University of Pennsylvania before giving up the law to pursue a career in the military. McClellan secured an appointment to West Point and graduated second in his class in 1846. McClellan served in the Mexican War and on various western army expeditions. He was viewed as a rising star, but he left the army in 1857 to become superintendent of the Illinois Central Railroad. McClellan, a former Whig, became a Democrat by 1858, and he supported Stephen Douglas against Abraham Lincoln in the US Senate race and again in the 1860 presidential election. By 1861, his love of the military drew him back to the army. In April he was appointed commander of the Ohio troops. By July, Lincoln gave McClellan command of the Union troops in Washington, DC, and in August he formed the Army of the Potomac and in November was named general-in-chief of the Union armies. McClellan, known as the “Young Napoleon,” soon won the affection of his men, but he soon began to frustrate Lincoln. McClellan’s extreme caution or lack of nerve led him to forestall providing Lincoln with any war plans or to commit his troops to action. By March 1862, Lincoln relieved McClellan of the office of general-in-chief, and the following fall he removed McClellan from command of the Army of the Potomac and transferred him to Trenton, New Jersey.</p>

<p>In 1864, McClellan sought, and won, the Democratic nomination for president. The nominating convention, however, was dominated by peace Democrats, who adopted a platform declaring the war a failure. McClellan tried to distance himself from this platform by declaring his intention of continuing the war until the Union was restored. McClellan lost the election in a landslide, in part because of significant Union victories in the months leading up to the election, and in part because the Democrats were viewed as the party of disunity. McClellan then traveled to Europe, where he lived for three years before returning to New Jersey to pursing engineering work. He was elected governor of New Jersey in 1877 and served one term. He died at his home in Orange, New Jersey, in 1885.</p>
</note>
  <bibl><bibl>“McClellan, George B.” <hi rendition="#italics">American National Biography</hi>.</bibl>

                <bibl>Clemens, Tom. “George B. McClellan (1826-1885).” <hi rendition="#italics">Encyclopedia of Virginia</hi>. <ref target="http://www.encyclopediavirginia.org/mcclellan_george_b_1826-1885">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50014834.html. Depicted in 2189</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003723">
  <persName key="ENT.000003723">
    <forename type="first">Edward </forename>
    <surname type="last">McGlynn</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1837">1837</birth>
  <death when="1900">1900</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in hint cartoon #12371&#13;
http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no97050463</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003750">
  <persName key="ENT.000003750">
    <forename type="first">James</forename>
    <surname type="last">McNichol</surname>
  </persName>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in hint cartoon 12233</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003367">
  <persName key="ENT.000003367">
    <forename type="first">Warner</forename>
    <surname type="last">Miller</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1838">1838</birth>
  <death when="1918">1918</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Warner Miller was a businessman and Republican Senator.</p>
                <p>Miller was born in Hannibal, New York on August 12, 1838.  After graduating from Union College in 1860, he worked as a professor of Latin and Greek at the Fort Edward Collegiate Institute.  He served in the Civil War, was promoted to lieutenant, and was taken prisoner by the Confederate forces during the Battle of Winchester.  After serving in the military, he founded the Warner Miller and Company paper mill where he developed new techniques for the manufacturing of paper.</p> 
                <p>He served in the New York State Assembly (1873-1876) and the United States House of Representatives (1879-1881).  He became a US Senator in 1881 and served until 1887.  In 1888, he ran for Governor of New York and lost to Davis Bennett Hill.  Miller died on March 12, 1918.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>“The Election Case of Elbridge G. Lapham and Warner Miller of New York (1881).” <hi rendition="#italics">United States Senate</hi>. Accessed June 22, 2015. <ref target="http://www.senate.gov/artandhistory/history/common/contested_elections/073Lapham_Miller.htm">Link</ref></bibl>
                
                <bibl>“Miller, Warner.” <hi rendition="#italics">Biographical Directory of the United States Congress</hi>. Accessed June 22, 2015. <ref target="http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=m000760">Link</ref></bibl>
                
                <bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). <hi rendition="#italics">Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age</hi>. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe.</bibl>
</bibl>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no95043103 ; depicted in 11585-Bc612P567_1_TEI.xml</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003623">
  <persName key="ENT.000003623">
    <forename type="first">John</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Ames</forename>
    <surname type="last">Mitchell</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1845">1845</birth>
  <death when="1918">1918</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003725">
  <persName key="ENT.000003725">
    <forename type="first">Samuel</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Latham</forename>
    <surname type="last">Mitchill</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1764">1764</birth>
  <death when="1831">1831</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n82268189.html; depicted in 11824 (one of the doctors, not clear which)</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003368">
  <persName key="ENT.000003368">
    <forename type="first">Rachel</forename>
    <surname type="last">Moloshok</surname>
  </persName>
  <note type="internal">HINT project staff</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003369">
  <persName key="ENT.000003369">
    <forename type="first">Fred</forename>
    <surname type="last">Morgan</surname>
  </persName>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">Philadelphia Inquirer cartoonist ; artist of 11565-3133_b2f9_1_TEI.xml&#13;
&#13;
LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79060685</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000000168">
  <persName key="ENT.000000168">
    <forename type="first">Robert</forename>
    <surname type="last">Morris</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1734">1734</birth>
  <death when="1806">1806</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">Philadelphia merchant, Revolutionary War financier, and founder of the Bank of North America.  A signer of the Declaration of Independence, Robert Morris also served a Pennsylvania delegate to both Continental Congresses, as well as the first United States Senator from Pennsylvania.</note>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 11731</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003759">
  <persName key="ENT.000003759">
    <forename type="first">Napoleon</forename>
    <surname type="last">Bonaparte</surname>
    <addName type="alt">Napoleon I</addName>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1769">1769</birth>
  <death when="1821">1821</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003678">
  <persName key="ENT.000003678">
    <forename type="first">Louis-Napoléon</forename>
    <surname type="last">Bonaparte</surname>
    <addName type="alt">Napoleon III</addName>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1803">1803</birth>
  <death when="1873">1873</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79071059.html; depicted in 12338</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000000251">
  <persName key="ENT.000000251">
    <forename type="first">Thomas</forename>
    <surname type="last">Nast</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1840">1840</birth>
  <death when="1902">1902</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Thomas Nast was perhaps the greatest American political cartoonist of the nineteenth century. He is credited shifting the focus on cartooning from text to imagery and with popularizing the symbols of the donkey and the elephant for the Democratic and Republican Parties. He also is responsible for our modern image of Santa Claus. Thomas Nast was born in Bavaria in 1840 and moved to New York City with his parents in 1846. There Nast studied art, and in 1855 he was hired as a staff artist for <hi rendition="#italics">Frank Leslie’s Illustrated Newspaper</hi>. Three years later he became a freelance artist for <hi rendition="#italics">Harper’s Weekly</hi> and <hi rendition="#italics">New York Illustrated News</hi>. In 1860, Nast traveled to Europe, where he covered subjects such as Garibaldi’s campaigns in Italy and English boxing. He returned to New York in 1861, where he married Sarah Edwards and sketched for the <hi rendition="#italics">Illustrated News</hi> and <hi rendition="#italics">Leslie’s</hi> before rejoining <hi rendition="#italics">Harper’s Weekly</hi> in 1862. During the Civil War, Nast’s most influential work captured the political issues dividing the nation and used domestic scenes to bolster the Union cause. After the war, Nast used his pen to comment on Reconstruction, black rights, and party politics. In the 1870s, he used his cartoons fight the corruption of New York’s Boss Tweed and Tammany Hall. In politics, Nast was a Republican, and he supported the Grant administration and the need for federal intervention in the South. Nash was at the peak of his popularity and power during the postwar years. His influence declined in the latter years of the nineteenth century. He left <hi rendition="#italics">Harper’s Weekly</hi> in 1886 and failed in his attempt to establish his own journal. In 1902, Theodore Roosevelt appointed him a consul to Ecuador, where he succumbed to yellow fever in that same year.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>“Nast, Thomas.” <hi rendition="#italics">American National Biography</hi>.</bibl>
                
               <bibl>Lewin, J. G., and P. J. Huff. <hi rendition="#italics">Lines of Contention: Political Cartoons of the Civil War</hi>.  New York: HarperCollins Publishers, 2007. p. 199</bibl></bibl>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003547">
  <persName key="ENT.000003547">
    <forename type="first">Charles</forename>
    <surname type="last">Nelan</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1858">1858</birth>
  <death when="1904">1904</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003371">
  <persName key="ENT.000003371">
    <forename type="first">Sarah</forename>
    <surname type="last">Newhouse</surname>
  </persName>
  <note type="internal">HINT project staff</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003733">
  <persName key="ENT.000003733">
    <addName type="honorific">Commodore</addName>
    <forename type="first">James</forename>
    <surname type="last">Nicholson</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1737">1737</birth>
  <death when="1804">1804</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr94002178.html; depicted in 11579</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003535">
  <persName key="ENT.000003535">
    <forename type="first">Mordecai</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Manuel</forename>
    <surname type="last">Noah</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1785">1785</birth>
  <death when="1851">1851</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003372">
  <persName key="ENT.000003372">
    <addName type="honorific">Lord</addName>
    <forename type="first">Frederick</forename>
    <surname type="last">North</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1732">1732</birth>
  <death when="1792">1792</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 2562-Bb612L615_1_TEI.xml (Liberty Triumphant) ; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79056537.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003714">
  <persName key="ENT.000003714">
    <forename type="first">Patrick</forename>
    <surname type="last">O'Donnell</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1835">1835</birth>
  <death when="1883">1883</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in hint cartoon #12154</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003656">
  <persName key="ENT.000003656">
    <forename type="first">Ole</forename>
    <surname type="last">May</surname>
  </persName>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">artist of "Out with them all" political cartoon #6807</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003616">
  <persName key="ENT.000003616">
    <forename type="first">Frederick</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Burr</forename>
    <surname type="last">Opper</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1857">1857</birth>
  <death when="1937">1937</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Frederick Burr Opper was an American cartoonist.  He was born on January 2, 1857 in Madison, Ohio.  He dropped out of school when he was fourteen years old and worked as a printer’s apprentice for the <hi rendition="#italics">Madison Gazette</hi>.  He moved to New York City at the age of sixteen and soon began working for <hi rendition="#italics">Wild Oats</hi>.  He then worked for three years at <hi rendition="#italics">Leslie’s Magazine</hi> as a correspondent and cartoonist.  In 1880, Keppler hired him as a cartoonist for <hi rendition="#italics">Puck</hi>.  He remained on staff for almost twenty years.  In 1898, Opper began working as a cartoonist for William Randolph Hearst’s <hi rendition="#italics">New York Journal</hi>.   While working for Hearst, Opper created several popular and long running comic strip series including <hi rendition="#italics">Happy Hooligan</hi> and <hi rendition="#italics">Alphonse and Gastone</hi>.  He retired in 1934 due to vision problems.  He died in New York on August 27, 1937.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>“Biography of Opper.” <hi rendition="#italics">Ohio State University, Opper Project</hi>. Accessed June 10, 2015. <ref target="http://hti.osu.edu/opper/opper-biography">Link</ref></bibl>
                             
<bibl>“Frederick Burr Opper Caricature Biography.” <hi rendition="#italics">Smithsonian Libraries</hi>. Accessed June 10, 2015. <ref target="http://www.sil.si.edu/ondisplay/caricatures/bio_opper.htm">Link</ref></bibl>

<bibl>“Frederick Burr Opper, 1857-1937.” <hi rendition="#italics">Ohio State University, Billy Ireland Cartoon Library and Museum</hi>. Accessed June 10, 2015. <ref target="http://cartoons.osu.edu/digital_albums/newspaperartists/opper/Opper_bio.html">Link</ref></bibl>
<bibl>West, Richard Samuel. <hi rendition="#italics">Satire On Stone: The Political Cartoons of Joseph Keppler</hi>. Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1988.</bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n85247604</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000000869">
  <persName key="ENT.000000869">
    <surname type="last">Thomas Paine</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1737">1737</birth>
  <death when="1809">1809</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79021666.html; depicted in 11731</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000002957">
  <persName key="ENT.000002957">
    <forename type="first">Charles</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Stewart</forename>
    <surname type="last">Parnell</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1846">1846</birth>
  <death when="1891">1891</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">Mentioned in cartoon 12155</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003724">
  <persName key="ENT.000003724">
    <forename type="first">Felix</forename>
    <surname type="last">Pascalis</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1762">1762</birth>
  <death when="1833">1833</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n85253104.html; depicted in 11824 (French doctor)</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003755">
  <persName key="ENT.000003755">
    <forename type="first">Robert</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Emory</forename>
    <surname type="last">Pattison</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1850">1850</birth>
  <death when="1904">1904</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in HINT cartoon #12030&#13;
LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2002039948</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000002593">
  <persName key="ENT.000002593">
    <forename type="first">Israel</forename>
    <surname type="last">Pemberton</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1715">1715</birth>
  <death when="1779">1779</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003373">
  <persName key="ENT.000003373">
    <forename type="first">George</forename>
    <surname type="last">Pendleton</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1825">1825</birth>
  <death when="1889">1889</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 11572 and 11756; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n86812256.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000000166">
  <persName key="ENT.000000166">
    <forename type="first">William</forename>
    <surname type="last">Penn</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1644">1644</birth>
  <death when="1718">1718</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in hint cartoon #12232</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000000557">
  <persName key="ENT.000000557">
    <forename type="first">Samuel</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Whitaker</forename>
    <surname type="last">Pennypacker</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1843">1843</birth>
  <death when="1916">1916</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Samuel Pennypacker was the 23rd Governor of Pennsylvania.</p>
                <p>Pennypacker was born on April 9, 1843 in Phoenixville, Pennsylvania.  He attended Grovemont Seminary and was accepted into Yale University.  His grandfather decided not to pay his tuition until he got some experience in the workforce.  In 1862 Pennypacker became a teacher at Mont Clare in Montgomery County, and the following year, enlisted in the 26th Pennsylvania Emergency Regiment.  After fighting in the militia, he returned to his studies and attended law school at the University of Pennsylvania.  In 1870 he married Virginia Earle Broomall.</p>
                <p>He served on the Philadelphia Board of Education in 1885 and later became the judge of the Court of Common Pleas of Philadelphia.  In 1900 he became the president of the Historical Society of Pennsylvania.  He defeated Robert Pattison for the office of Governor of Pennsylvania and served from 1903-1907.  As Governor, Pennypacker signed legislation to create the Pennsylvania State Archives and the State Museum of Pennsylvania.  The Child Labor Act of 1905 was also passed during his governorship.  Pennypacker also helped pass the controversial Newspaper Libel Act of 1903 which was repealed in 1907.</p>
                <p>Samuel Pennypacker died on September 2, 1916.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>“Samuel Pennypacker.” <hi rendition="#italics">Pennsylvania Historical and Museum Commission</hi>. Accessed June 30, 2015. <ref target="http://www.portal.state.pa.us/portal/server.pt/community/1879-1951/4284/samuel_whitaker_pennypacker/469087">Link</ref></bibl>
                
                <bibl>“Samuel Whitaker Pennypacker.” <hi rendition="#italics">Pennsylvania Capitol Preservation Committee</hi>. Accessed June 30, 2015. <ref target="http://cpc.state.pa.us/history/notable/samuel-whitaker-pennypacker.cfm">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n85199995.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000002704">
  <persName key="ENT.000002704">
    <forename type="first">Boies</forename>
    <surname type="last">Penrose</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1860">1860</birth>
  <death when="1921">1921</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003543">
  <persName key="ENT.000003543">
    <forename type="first">Oliver</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Hazard</forename>
    <surname type="last">Perry</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1785">1785</birth>
  <death when="1819">1819</death>
  <note type="internal">referenced in 11812.xml</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003374">
  <persName key="ENT.000003374">
    <forename type="first">Phrynē</forename>
  </persName>
  <sex>Female</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Phryne was a 4th century BC Greek courtesan whose real name was Mnesarete.  It is believed that she received the nickname Phryne, the ancient greek word for toad, because of her pale complexion.</p>
                <p>She had an affair with the artist Praxiteles who was so inspired by her beauty that he sculpted two statues of her.   One of the statues was displayed at the Temple of Apollo at Delphi and the other was sent to the city of her birth.  It’s also believed that she also modeled for Praxiteles’ sculpture “Cnidian Aphrodite” and Apelles’ painting “Aphrodite Anadyomene.” </p>
                <p>Circa 347 Phryne was accused of blasphemy and was brought to court. Hypereides, her lawyer, feared she would be convicted and so brought her before the tribunal and removed her robes. Phryne’s beauty overwhelmed the tribunal and they acquitted her.  In the nineteenth-century, French artist Jean-Léon Gerôme recreated the famous the court scene in the painting <hi rendition="#italics">Phryne before the Areopagus</hi>.</p>
                </note>
  <bibl><bibl>“Frine.” <hi rendition="#italics">Treccani</hi>. Accessed June 11, 2015. <ref target="http://www.treccani.it/enciclopedia/frine_(Enciclopedia-Italiana)/">Link</ref></bibl>
                <bibl>“Phryne.” <hi rendition="#italics">Encyclopedia Britannica Online</hi>. Accessed June 11, 2015.  <ref target= "http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/458409/Phryne">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">real name Mnēsarétē ; mentioned/referenced in 11585-Bc612P567_1_TEI.xml&#13;
&#13;
http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2001153414</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003720">
  <persName key="ENT.000003720">
    <forename type="first">Franklin</forename>
    <surname type="last">Pierce</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1804">1804</birth>
  <death when="1869">1869</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50018658.html; depicted in 11730</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003770">
  <persName key="ENT.000003770">
    <forename type="first">William</forename>
    <surname type="last">Pitt</surname>
    <addName type="alt">1st Lord of Chatham</addName>
    <addName type="alt">William Pitt the Elder</addName>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1708">1708</birth>
  <death when="1778">1778</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">Prime Minister of Great Britain, 1766-1768</note>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 12017</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003375">
  <persName key="ENT.000003375">
    <surname type="last">Poplicola</surname>
  </persName>
  <note type="biography">In 1773, King's College president Myles Cooper and tutor John Vardill wrote three letters, signed "Poplicola," to the editor of <hi rendition="#italics">Rivington's New-York Gazetteer</hi> defending the British colonial government in North America and the East India Company. "Poplicola" is lampooned in the circa 1774 political cartoon <ref target="2562">Liberty Triumphant: or the Downfall of Oppression</ref>.</note>
  <bibl>E. P. Richardson, "Four American Political Prints," <hi rendition="#italics">American Art Journal</hi> 6 (1974):38.</bibl>
  <note type="internal">Pen name associated with three editorials in Rivington's New York Gazetteer (November 18, December 2, and December 23, 1773) that took a pro-government, pro-East India Company stance during uproar over the Tea Act in America. Depicted in 2562-Bb612L615_1_TEI.xml (Liberty Triumphant). Looks like Poplicola was pen name of co-authored piece. Use article printouts in cartoon folder.

                    </note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003744">
  <persName key="ENT.000003744">
    <forename type="first">William</forename>
    <surname type="last">Poyntell</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1756">1756</birth>
  <death when="1811">1811</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">Philadelphia bookseller and printer, born in England. After immigrating to Philadelphia, he established a printing office notable for publishing the first American editions of the works of Horace, Virgil, and Ovid, among other classics. He also served as a member of the Philadelphia Select Council. He died in Philadelphia on September 10, 1811, at age 56.</note>
  <bibl><bibl>Obituary in <hi rendition="#italics">The Gentlemen’s Magazine and Historical Chronicle</hi>, vol. 82, part 2 (1812): 294-295.</bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n88115514.html; publisher of "The Siege of Zion" (11731)</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003760">
  <persName key="ENT.000003760">
    <forename type="first">William</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Ballard</forename>
    <surname type="last">Preston</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1805">1805</birth>
  <death when="1862">1862</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">Depicted in DAMS record #1778. Bio at http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=P000518</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003534">
  <persName key="ENT.000003534">
    <addName type="honorific">Sir</addName>
    <forename type="first">John</forename>
    <surname type="last">Pringle</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1707">1707</birth>
  <death when="1782">1782</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003548">
  <persName key="ENT.000003548">
    <forename type="first">J.S. (John S.)</forename>
    <surname type="last">Pughe</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1870">1870</birth>
  <death when="1909">1909</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>John Samuel Pughe was a cartoonist for the <hi rendition="#italics">New York World</hi> and <hi rendition="#italics">Puck</hi>.  He was born in Wales on June 3, 1870.  Two years after his birth, his family immigrated to the United States.  He attended public school in New York and later studied at Cooper Union.  He died on April 19, 1909 in New Jersey.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>Kahn, Michael A, Richard Samuel West, Bill Watterson, and Dean Mullaney. <hi rendition="#italics">What Fools These Mortals Be!: The Story of Puck: America’s First and Most Influential Magazine of Color Political Cartoons</hi>, 2014.</bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n95000431.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003609">
  <persName key="ENT.000003609">
    <forename type="first">Joseph</forename>
    <surname type="last">Pulitzer</surname>
    <addName type="alt">Politzer, József</addName>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1847">1847</birth>
  <death when="1911">1911</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003606">
  <persName key="ENT.000003606">
    <forename type="first">Frederick</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Taylor</forename>
    <surname type="last">Pusey</surname>
  </persName>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000001953">
  <persName key="ENT.000001953">
    <forename type="first">Matthew</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Stanley</forename>
    <surname type="last">Quay</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1833-09-30">1833-09-30</birth>
  <death when="1904-05-28">1904-05-28</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">Appears in DAMS #11737, "The Silence of Matt Quay."</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003376">
  <persName key="ENT.000003376">
    <forename type="first">Henry</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Jarvis</forename>
    <surname type="last">Raymond</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1820">1820</birth>
  <death when="1869">1869</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 11564; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n86111499.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003377">
  <persName key="ENT.000003377">
    <forename type="first">Whitelaw</forename>
    <surname type="last">Reid</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1837">1837</birth>
  <death when="1912">1912</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Whitelaw Reid was a journalist, politician, and editor and publisher of the <hi rendition="#italics">New York Tribune</hi> (1873-1912), and ambassador to Great Britain.</p>
                <p>Reid was born on October 27, 1837 in Ohio.  He joined the <hi rendition="#italics">Cincinnati Gazette</hi> in 1862 and served as a war correspondent during the Civil War.  He worked at the <hi rendition="#italics">Gazette</hi> until 1868 and also served as librarian of the House of Representatives (1863-1866).  In 1868, Horace Greeley, one of the nation’s most famous newspaper editors, hired him to work for the <hi rendition="#italics">New York Tribune</hi>.  In 1872, Reid managed Greeley’s presidential campaign.  Greeley lost the election and died a few weeks later.  Reid bought the <hi rendition="#italics">Tribune</hi> in 1873, and under his leadership, the newspaper became one of the most widely circulated and respected dailies in the country. </p> 
               <p> Reid served as ambassador to France from 1889-1892.  In 1892, he became President Benjamin Harrison’s running mate during the 1892 election.  Harrison and Reid lost the election to Democrat and former president, Grover Cleveland. President Theodore Roosevelt later appointed him to serve as ambassador to Great Britain.  Reid died on December 15, 1912 in England.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). <hi rendition="#italics">Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age</hi>. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe.</bibl> 
                
 <bibl>“Whitelaw Reid, American Journalist and Politician.” <hi rendition="#italics">Encyclopedia Britannica Online</hi>. Accessed June 8, 2015. <ref target="http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/496470/Whitelaw-Reid">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 11585-Bc612P567_1_TEI.xml ; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50050931.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003749">
  <persName key="ENT.000003749">
    <forename type="first">John</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Edgar</forename>
    <surname type="last">Reyburn</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1845">1845</birth>
  <death when="1914">1914</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2010065016&#13;
&#13;
depicted in hint cartoon 12233</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003359">
  <persName key="ENT.000003359">
    <forename type="first">Charles</forename>
    <surname type="last">Lennox</surname>
    <addName type="alt">Duke of Richmond</addName>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1735">1735</birth>
  <death when="1806">1806</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 2562-Bb612L615_1_TEI.xml (Liberty Triumphant) ; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n86104945.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003477">
  <persName key="ENT.000003477">
    <forename type="first">David</forename>
    <surname type="last">Rittenhouse</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1732">1732</birth>
  <death when="1796">1796</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">David Rittenhouse was a renowned American astronomer, inventor, clockmaker, mathematician, surveyor, scientific instrument craftsman and public official. The 1796 political cartoon "A Peep Into the Antifederal Club" depicts him peering through a telescope and wishing aloud for "such a government as [they] have on Saturn," reflecting his interest in astronomy and his leadership of the Philadelphia Democratic Society.</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003378">
  <persName key="ENT.000003378">
    <forename type="first">William</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Henry</forename>
    <surname type="last">Robertson</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1823">1823</birth>
  <death when="1898">1898</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>William Henry Robertson was a lawyer and politician.</p>
      <p>Robertson was born in Bedford, New York on October 10, 1823.  He practiced law in New York. Robertson became a member of the NY State Assembly in 1849 and 1850.  He served in the State senate (1854-1855; 1872 -1881; 1888-1891) and the United States Congress (1867-1869), and ran unsuccessfully for the governorship of New York in 1872.  In 1881, President James A. Garfield appointed Robertson to the position of Collector of the Port of New York.  Robertson died in Katonah, New York on December 6, 1898.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>“Robertson, William Henry.” <hi rendition="#italics">Biographical Directory of the United States Congress</hi>. Accessed June 23, 2015. <ref target="http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=R000328">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 11585-Bc612P567_1_TEI.xml ; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2009045320.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003701">
  <persName key="ENT.000003701">
    <forename type="first">George</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Maxwell</forename>
    <surname type="last">Robeson</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1829">1829</birth>
  <death when="1897">1897</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">Depicted in Hint cartoon 11834&#13;
http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n85250958</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003705">
  <persName key="ENT.000003705">
    <forename type="first">Lucius</forename>
    <surname type="last">Robinson</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1810">1810</birth>
  <death when="1891">1891</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003712">
  <persName key="ENT.000003712">
    <forename type="first">William</forename>
    <surname type="last">Robinson</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1814">1814</birth>
  <death when="1892">1892</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in hint cartoon 12154&#13;
LOC:http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n86025981.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003651">
  <persName key="ENT.000003651">
    <forename type="first">John</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Davison</forename>
    <surname type="last">Rockefeller</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1839">1839</birth>
  <death when="1937">1937</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>John Davison Rockefeller was a wealthy American business tycoon, philanthropist, and founder of Standard Oil.</p>  
<p>Rockefeller was born on July 8, 1839 in New York.  His father, William Avery Rockefeller, was a snake-oil salesman who sold treatments which he claimed would cure serious illnesses.   His mother, Eliza Davison, was a devout Baptist who instilled in her children a strong work ethic.</p>
               <p> At the age of sixteen on September 26, 1855, Rockefeller got his first job as an assistant bookkeeper with Hew &amp; Tuttle.  His employers were immediately impressed with his work and began giving him greater responsibilities.  In 1859, Rockefeller decided to open his own business and partnered with Maurice Clark to form the produce commission business, Clark &amp; Rockefeller.  They sold hay, grain, and other goods and over the next several years, yielded large profits. </p>
                <p>In 1870, he partnered with his brother and several others to form Standard Oil.  In 1870, Standard Oil accounted for 10% of the nation’s oil industry. By 1882, the company had grown and became the Standard Oil Trust.  By the 1890s, Standard Oil controlled more than three quarters of the US oil market.  On May 15, 1911 the United States Supreme Court declared Standard Oil in violation of the Sherman Anti-Trust Act and ordered its dissolution. </p> 
                <p>Rockefeller was also a philanthropist who donated hundreds of millions of dollars.  He helped found the University of Chicago, the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, and the Rockefeller Foundation.  He died on May 23, 1937.</p></note>
  <bibl> <bibl>“JDR Sr. Biographical Sketch.” <hi rendition="#italics">The Rockefeller Archive Center</hi>. Accessed June 30, 2015. <ref target="http://www.rockarch.org/bio/jdrsr.php">Link</ref></bibl>
                    
                    <bibl>“John D. Rockefeller, Senior.” <hi rendition="#italics">The Rockefellers. WGBH American Experience, PBS</hi>. Accessed June 30, 2015. <ref target="http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/americanexperience/features/biography/rockefellers-john/">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79095196</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003785">
  <persName key="ENT.000003785">
    <forename type="first">Robert</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Barnwell</forename>
    <surname type="last">Roosevelt</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1829">1829</birth>
  <death when="1906">1906</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">Fish commissioner of the State of New York 1868-1888; editor of the "New York Citizen"; US Representative from New York 1871-1873; minister to the Hague 1888-1890; treasurer of the Democratic National Committee, 1892; member of the Board of Aldermen of New York City. Also uncle of Theodore Roosevelt and editor of the <hi rendition="#italics">New York Citizen</hi>.</note>
  <bibl>Biographical Directory of the United States Congress <ref target="http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=R000428">Link</ref></bibl>
  <note type="internal">mentioned in 12273</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000002738">
  <persName key="ENT.000002738">
    <forename type="first">Theodore</forename>
    <surname type="last">Roosevelt</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1858">1858</birth>
  <death when="1919">1919</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Theodore Roosevelt was the 26th President of the United States.</p>
                <p>Roosevelt was born on October 27, 1858 in New York City and was the second child of Martha Bulloch Roosevelt and Theodore Roosevelt, Sr.  At a young age, Roosevelt developed bronchial asthma, a condition that was so severe, he almost died.  He had poor vision and at the age of fourteen began wearing glasses.  Despite his medical conditions, Roosevelt was a curious and energetic young boy.  He was interested in natural history, collected insects, and performed taxidermy on birds and other small creatures. When he was only nine years old he wrote a natural history paper entitled “The Natural History of Insects.”  Roosevelt’s poor health began to improve at the age of twelve when his father built him a gymnasium in the family home.  He lifted weights and learned how to box.  Roosevelt’s parents sought to expand their children’s world view and hired tutors to teach the children French, German, and Latin.  The family spent a year in Europe and the Middle East.  Roosevelt was mostly home schooled as a child, and in 1876 enrolled at Harvard College.  On October 27, 1880 Roosevelt married Alice Hathaway Lee.  Alice died on February 14, 1884, two days after giving birth to their daughter Alice.  His mother passed away from typhoid fever the same day.  Roosevelt was distraught and sent his daughter away to live with one of his sisters.</p>  
                <p>In 1886, he unsuccessfully ran for mayor of New York.  On December 2, 1886 he married his second wife, Edith Kermit Carow.  From 1895-1897, he served as the head of the New York City Board of Police Commissioners.  In 1897, he was appointed assistant secretary of the navy.  In 1898, he became a military hero when he led the Rough Riders Regiment to victory at the battle of San Juan Hill in Cuba during the Spanish-American War. He served as the governor of New York from 1899 to 1901.  He became vice president in 1901 and President on September 14, 1901 after President McKinley’s assassination.  At the age of 42, he became the youngest president in American history.  He served from 1901-1909.</p>
                <p>Roosevelt’s administration began what would be later known as the progressive era.  As president, he enacted numerous reforms, expanded the powers of the executive office, and became known as the great “trust buster” who broke up Standard Oil and filed forty anti-trust lawsuits.  During the anthracite coal strike, he became the first president to use his powers to negotiate and settle a labor dispute.  He expanded trade, built the Panama Canal, increased US military power and presence in the Western hemisphere, and was an imperialist who supported American expansionism.  He established the Forest Service, created five national parks, and signed legislation to preserve millions of acres of land. </p> 
                <p>In 1908, he decided not to run for re-election to a third term.  Instead, he supported and helped William Howard Taft win the presidency.  However, Roosevelt soon began to disagree with the policies of the Taft administration and decided to run against Taft in 1912.  Roosevelt formed the Bull Moose party.  Roosevelt and Taft lost to Woodrow Wilson.</p>
                <p>Roosevelt died on January 6, 1919.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>Donald, Aida DiPace. <hi rendition="#italics">Lion in the White House: A Life of Theodore Roosevelt</hi>. New York: Basic Books, 2007.</bibl>

<bibl>“The President. “ <hi rendition="#italics">Theodore Roosevelt Association</hi>. Accessed June 8, 2015. <ref target="http://www.theodoreroosevelt.org/site/c.elKSIdOWIiJ8H/b.8344377/k.8A97/The_President.htm">Link</ref></bibl>

                <bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). <hi rendition="#italics">Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age</hi>. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe.</bibl> 

<bibl>“Theodore Roosevelt.”  <hi rendition="#italics">Whitehouse.gov</hi>. Accessed June 8, 2015. <ref target="https://www.whitehouse.gov/1600/presidents/theodoreroosevelt">Link</ref></bibl>

<bibl>“TR Center - Theodore Roosevelt Center Home.” <hi rendition="#italics">Theodore Roosevelt Center at Dickinson State University</hi>. Accessed June 22, 2015. <ref target="http://www.theodorerooseveltcenter.org/">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79027239</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003562">
  <persName key="ENT.000003562">
    <forename type="first">John</forename>
    <forename type="middle">T.</forename>
    <surname type="last">Ruoff</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1832">1832</birth>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">John T. Ruoff has been identified as the New York publisher of the cartoon “Southern Ass-Stock Crazy” by several print dealers, though not by the Library of Congress. A John T. Ruoff, bookkeeper, is listed in the 1860 federal census, living in Hoboken, New Jersey. This is likely the <p>John T. Ruoff has been identified as the New York publisher of the cartoon “Southern Ass-Stock Crazy” by several print dealers, though not by the Library of Congress. A John T. Ruoff, bookkeeper, is listed in the 1860 federal census, living in Hoboken, New Jersey. This is likely the John T. Ruoff identified by print dealers, since, in addition to his wife and two young children, Ruoff had two lithographers, Lewis Newmaker and Otto Wagner, living in his household. Ruoff was age twenty-eight in 1860 and the census gives his birthplace as Nuremberg. In 1870 he appears as John F. Ruoff and is living in Putnam, Connecticut, where he worked in a woolen mill. He does not appear in the 1880 federal census.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>US Census, 1860, 1870.</bibl>
                </bibl>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000000478">
  <persName key="ENT.000000478">
    <forename type="first">Benjamin</forename>
    <surname type="last">Rush</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1746">1746</birth>
  <death when="1813">1813</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">Born in Byberry, Pennsylvania, Dr. Benjamin Rush was an influential physician, educator, politician, and humanitarian. He was a professor of chemistry and medicine at the College of Philadelphia and later the University of Pennsylvania, a member of the Continental Congress, signer of the Declaration of Independence, surgeon general of the Continental Army,  and founder of Dickinson College. </note>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50000649.html; depicted in 11731</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003687">
  <persName key="ENT.000003687">
    <forename type="first">Wilhelm</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Conrad</forename>
    <surname type="last">Röntgen</surname>
    <addName type="alt">Roentgen, Wilhelm, 1845-1923</addName>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1845">1845</birth>
  <death when="1923">1923</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50046876</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003762">
  <persName key="ENT.000003762">
    <forename type="first">J. Allan</forename>
    <surname type="last">Schaadt</surname>
  </persName>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">Philadelphia Times cartoonist.  artist for hint cartoon #12020</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003379">
  <persName key="ENT.000003379">
    <forename type="first">Carl</forename>
    <surname type="last">Schurz</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1829">1829</birth>
  <death when="1906">1906</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Carl Schurz was a journalist and politician.</p>
      <p>Schurz was born in Liblar, Germany on March 2, 1829.  After taking part in the failed revolution of 1848, he was forced to leave his homeland in order to escape imprisonment.  He immigrated to the United States in 1852 and practiced law in Milwaukee, Wisconsin.  During the Civil War, he fought in the Union Army.  In 1866, he became editor of the <hi rendition="#italics">Detroit Post</hi>, as well as, a German language newspaper.  He served in the United States Senate from 1869 to 1875.  In 1877, President Rutherford B. Hayes appointed him Secretary of the Interior.  He served until 1881.  Schurz was editor of the <hi rendition="#italics">New York Evening Post</hi> (1881-1884) and President of the National Civil Service Reform League (1892-1901).  He died on May 14, 1906.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>“Carl Schurz.” <hi rendition="#italics">Encyclopedia Britannica Online</hi>. Accessed June 23, 2015. <ref target="http://www.britannica.com/biography/Carl-Schurz">Link</ref></bibl>
      
      <bibl>“Schurz, Carl.” Biographical Directory of the United States Congress. Accessed June 23, 2015. <ref target="http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=s000151">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50003179.html ; depicted in 11585-Bc612P567_1_TEI.xml</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003747">
  <persName key="ENT.000003747">
    <forename type="first">Winfield</forename>
    <surname type="last">Scott</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1786">1786</birth>
  <death when="1866">1866</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">Nicknamed "Old Fuss and Feathers" and "Grand Old Man of the Army," Winfield Scott was a long-serving US Army general. He was considered as a Whig Party presidential candidate in 1840 and 1848 but was not nominated; in 1852, he was nominated and ran, unsuccessfully, against Democrat Franklin Pierce.</note>
  <note type="internal">Possibly depicted in 12278 (may be Zachary Taylor instead); LOC http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79059770.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003283">
  <persName key="ENT.000003283">
    <forename type="first">William</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Henry</forename>
    <surname type="last">Seward</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1801">1801</birth>
  <death when="1872">1872</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 11564</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003537">
  <persName key="ENT.000003537">
    <forename type="first">William</forename>
    <surname type="last">Shakespeare</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1564">1564</birth>
  <death when="1616">1616</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">referenced in 11508; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n78095332.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003695">
  <persName key="ENT.000003695">
    <forename type="first">Philip</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Henry</forename>
    <surname type="last">Sheridan</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1831">1831</birth>
  <death when="1888">1888</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Philip Henry Sheridan was born to an Irish laborer and his wife who migrated from Ireland to Somerset, Ohio, with a brief stay in Albany, New York, in 1830–31. It is not clear exactly where Philip was born. In Ohio, Sheridan received a rudimentary education and then worked as a bookkeeper in a dry goods store before winning an appointment to the US Military Academy at West Point in 1848. After graduation, Sheridan served on frontier duty in the West, until he was ordered to Missouri in September 1861 to join a new infantry unit under General Halleck. Sheridan was made chief commissary and quartermaster for the Army of the Southwest Missouri District. While he excelled in this position, he longed to command troops in the field. He finally secured such a command in spring 1862 when he was offered the position of commander of the volunteer Second Michigan Cavalry. From there, Sheridan quickly moved up, winning the admiration of his troops and superiors alike. He was promoted to brigadier general of US Volunteers by mid-1862. His battlefield courage and skills were admired by General U. S. Grant, who appointed Sheridan chief of cavalry in early 1864. Now brigadier general, US Army, in May 1864 Sheridan led his cavalry to Richmond, where he defeated Confederate cavalry forces under Jeb Stuart, further earning him the Grant’s respect. A year later, in April 1865, Sheridan’s cavalry played an important role in Lee’s surrender at Appomattox, though Sheridan himself was disappointed that he was not given the opportunity to crush the Confederate troops and instead they were allowed to negotiate their surrender.</p> 
                
                <p>After the Civil War, Sheridan was sent to New Orleans, where he commanded the Military Division of the Gulf and then was briefly military governor of Louisiana and Texas. In 1867, Sheridan returned to the West, where, except for a two-year hiatus when he served as an official observer of the Franco-Prussian War, he directed several campaigns against the Plains Indians. In 1883, Sheridan was named general in chief of the US Army. Sheridan published his memoirs in 1888. In that same year, he suffered a series of heart attacks, and he died at his summer cottage in Nonquitt, Massachusetts.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>“Sheridan, Philip Henry.” <hi rendition="#italics">American National Biography</hi>.</bibl>
                
                <bibl>Philip Henry Sheridan Papers, 1853–1888, Finding Aid. Library of Congress.  <ref target="http://findingaids.loc.gov/db/search/xq/searchMfer02.xq?_id=loc.mss.eadmss.ms006029&amp;_faSection=overview&amp;_faSubsection=bioghist&amp;_dmdid=d31112e19">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">mentioned in 11751; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79061256.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003380">
  <persName key="ENT.000003380">
    <forename type="first">John</forename>
    <surname type="last">Sherman</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1823">1823</birth>
  <death when="1900">1900</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>John Sherman was born on May 10, 1823 in Ohio and was the brother of William Tecumseh Sherman.  He studied law and was admitted to the bar in 1844.  He represented Ohio in the US House of Representatives from 1855 to 1861.  Sherman became a US Senator in 1861 and served until 1877.  As Senator, he supported the passage of the National Bank Act and the Legal Tender Act which helped finance the war effort.  He also helped draft the Reconstruction Act of 1867, supported the Fifteenth Amendment, and voted to impeach Andrew Johnson.  In 1877, Sherman left the Senate to serve as Secretary of the Treasury during the Hayes’ administration.  He left Hayes’ cabinet in 1881 and returned to the United States Senate where he remained until 1897.  As Senator, he authored the Sherman Anti-Trust Act which limited the power of monopolies.   Although he was an influential and well respected politician, Sherman lost his bid to become the Republican presidential nominee three times (1880, 1884, and 1888).  In 1897, President McKinley appointed him Secretary of State, but, due to failing health, he resigned after serving only one year.  Sherman died on October 22, 1900.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>Schlup, L. C., &amp; Ryan, J. G. (2003). <hi rendition="#italics">Historical dictionary of the Gilded Age</hi>. Armonk, N.Y.: M.E. Sharpe.</bibl> 
      
      <bibl>“Sherman, John.” <hi rendition="#italics">Biographical Directory of the United States Congress</hi>. Accessed June 23, 2015. <ref target="http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=s000346">Link</ref></bibl>
      
      <bibl>“John Sherman.” <hi rendition="#italics">Ohio History Central</hi>. Accessed June 24, 2015. <ref target="http://www.ohiohistorycentral.org/w/John_Sherman">Link</ref></bibl>
      <bibl>“John Sherman.” <hi rendition="#italics">United States Department of State, Office of the Historian</hi>. Accessed June 23, 2015. <ref target="https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/people/sherman-john">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 11585-Bc612P567_1_TEI.xml ; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50023075</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003694">
  <persName key="ENT.000003694">
    <forename type="first">William</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Tecumseh</forename>
    <surname type="last">Sherman</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1820">1820</birth>
  <death when="1891">1891</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>William Tecumseh Sherman was one of the Union’s most famous generals, best known for his efforts to demoralize the South through the destruction of property, epitomized in his March through Georgia in the fall of 1864. Sherman was born in Lancaster, Ohio, in 1820, to a prominent state judge, one of 11 children. The death of his father in 1829, however, left his family destitute, and William became the ward of Ohio lawyer and politician Thomas Ewing. In 1836, Sherman entered the US Military Academy, where he excelled. After his graduation in 1840, he served mostly in the South, including in the Seminole War. During the Mexican War, he was stationed in California, where he saw no combat. He returned east in 1850, where he married Ewing’s daughter, Ellen Ewing. He left the military at her insistence in 1853. From 1853 until 1861, Sherman worked as a banker and businessman in various locations. By 1859, Sherman was eager to reenter the army and was able to secure the position of superintendent of the Louisiana Military Seminary, where he served until February 1861, when he left when Louisiana seceded from the Union. A few months later he became a colonel in the regular army. Sherman performed valiantly at Shiloh and served as military governor of Memphis in 1862, where he came to recognize the important role that civilians—and morale—played in the war. In 1863, Sherman participated in the Vicksburg campaign and was promoted to brigadier general. That fall, Sherman was named commander of the Department of the Army of the Tennessee. Sherman first implemented his strategy to break the South through the widespread destruction of property in the Meridian Campaign of early 1864, leaving behind a path of destruction from Jackson to Meridian, Mississippi. In March 1864, Sherman became commander of the Military Division of the Mississippi and in charge of all military operations in the West. Sherman began his famous March through Georgia on September 1, 1864, following the fall of Atlanta, reaching Savannah on December 21.</p>                 
                <p>Despite his devastating approach to war, Sherman advocated a lenient peace, and in April 1865 he negotiated such a peace with Confederate general Joseph Johnston. A nation recently traumatized by Lincoln’s assassination, however, forced him to renegotiate the peace treaty. After the war, Sherman remained in the army, and when Grant was elected president, Sherman became commanding general. Sherman retired in 1883 and later settled in New York City, where he died in 1891.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>“Sherman, William Tecumseh.” <hi rendition="#italics">American National Biography</hi>.</bibl>
                
                <bibl>William T. Sherman Family Papers, Finding Aid. University of Notre Dame Archives. Notre Dame, Indiana.  <ref target="http://archives.nd.edu/findaids/ead/xml/shr.xml">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">mentioned in 11751; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80013437.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003587">
  <persName key="ENT.000003587">
    <forename type="first">H.</forename>
    <forename type="middle">N.</forename>
    <surname type="last">Smith</surname>
  </persName>
  <note type="biography"><p>H. N. Smith is the donor of the cartoon “Southern Ass-Stock Crazy” to the Historical Society of Pennsylvania. No further information has been uncovered.</p></note>
  <note type="internal">This is a person whose name was handwritten on a cartoon featured in the HINT project.  No further information is known about this entity.</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003631">
  <persName key="ENT.000003631">
    <forename type="first">Henry</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Louis</forename>
    <surname type="last">Stephens</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1824">1824</birth>
  <death when="1882">1882</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50022429.html; artist of 11747</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003686">
  <persName key="ENT.000003686">
    <forename type="first">Adlai</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Ewing</forename>
    <surname type="last">Stevenson</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1835">1835</birth>
  <death when="1914">1914</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n88159812
in cartoon "Bad Case of Chill"12174</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003383">
  <persName key="ENT.000003383">
    <forename type="first">Charles</forename>
    <surname type="last">Sumner</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1811">1811</birth>
  <death when="1874">1874</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 11564-3133_b4f7_1_TEI.xml ; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n81057079.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003579">
  <persName key="ENT.000003579">
    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
    <forename type="middle">C.</forename>
    <surname type="last">Swayze</surname>
  </persName>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003784">
  <persName key="ENT.000003784">
    <forename type="first">Peter</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Barr</forename>
    <surname type="last">Sweeny</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1825">1825</birth>
  <death when="1911">1911</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">Peter B. Sweeney was known as the "Brains" of New York City's infamous "Tweed Ring." He was appointed city chamberlain (treasurer) in 1866 and was instrumental in nominating and securing the election of Mayor A. Oakey Hall, a Tweed ally, in 1868. Sweeny was named director of the city's parks department in 1870. In 1871, as the corruption of the Tweed Ring was exposed, Sweeney resigned his municipal positions and fled to France. He paid a $400,000 settlement to avoid prosecution and retired permanently from public life.</note>
  <bibl><bibl>John Adler, with Draper Hill, <hi rendition="#italics">Doomed by Cartoon: How Cartoonist Thomas Nast the “The New-York Times” Brought down Boss Tweed and His Ring of Thieves</hi> (Garden City, New York: Morgan James, 2008)</bibl>
<bibl>Biography at HarpWeek.com. <ref target="http://elections.harpweek.com/1872/bio-1872-Full.asp?UniqueID=29&amp;Year=1872">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 12273</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000002466">
  <persName key="ENT.000002466">
    <forename type="first">Charles</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Henry</forename>
    <surname type="last">Sykes</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1882">1882</birth>
  <death when="1942">1942</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Charles Henry Sykes was an American cartoonist.  He was born on November 12, 1882 in Alabama.  He attended the Drexel Institute of Art, Science, and Industry.  He worked as a cartoonist for the <hi rendition="#italics">North American</hi>, <hi rendition="#italics">Evening Public Ledger</hi>, and the <hi rendition="#italics">New York Evening Post</hi>.  He was also an editorial cartoonist for <hi rendition="#italics">Life</hi> magazine from 1922-1928.  He died in 1942.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>“Sykes Editorial Cartoon Collection.” <hi rendition="#italics">Virginia Commonwealth University Libraries Digital Collections</hi>. Accessed July 1, 2015. <ref target="http://dig.library.vcu.edu/cdm/landingpage/collection/syk">Link</ref></bibl>
                
               <bibl>“A Guide to the Charles Henry Sykes Cartoon Collection, Late 1930s to Early 1940s Sykes, Charles Henry, Cartoon Collection M 169.” <hi rendition="#italics">Virginia Heritage Guides to Manuscript and Archival Collections in Virginia</hi>. Accessed July 1, 2015. <ref target="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=vcu-cab/vircu00110.xml;query=;">Link</ref></bibl>
                
               <bibl>“Charles H. Sykes Papers 3656.” Finding Aid. <hi rendition="#italics">Historical Society of Pennsylvania</hi>. <ref target="http://www2.hsp.org/collections/manuscripts/s/Sykes3656.html">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003384">
  <persName key="ENT.000003384">
    <forename type="first">William</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Howard</forename>
    <surname type="last">Taft</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1857">1857</birth>
  <death when="1930">1930</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>William Howard Taft was the 27th President of the United States.</p>
                <p>Taft was born on September 15, 1857.  He graduated from Yale University second in his class and attended the University of Cincinnati law school.  He became judge of the Cincinnati Superior Court, US solicitor general, and a member of the Sixth US Circuit Court of Appeals.  President McKinley appointed him Governor-General of the Philippines in 1900.  In 1904, he became President Roosevelt’s Secretary of War.</p>  
                <p>Roosevelt decided he would not seek re-election in 1908 and choose Taft as his successor.  Taft defeated Democratic candidate William Jennings Bryan and became the 27th President.  Although President Taft broke up twice as many trusts as Roosevelt, he was perceived as a disappointment to many progressives.  Roosevelt quarreled with Taft and accused him of abandoning the ideals of the progressive movement.  In 1912, Roosevelt formed the Progressive or “Bull Moose” Party and ran against Taft.  The split in the Republican Party helped Woodrow Wilson to win the White House.</p>
                <p>After leaving Washington, Taft became a Professor at Yale University, and later a Chief Justice of the United States.  He died on March 8, 1931.  </p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>“William Howard Taft: A Life in Brief.”  <hi rendition="#italics">Miller Center</hi>.  Accessed June 30, 2015.  <ref target="http://millercenter.org/president/taft/essays/biography/1">Link</ref></bibl>
                
                <bibl>“William Howard Taft.” <hi rendition="#italics">Whitehouse.gov</hi>. Accessed June 30, 2015. <ref target="https://www.whitehouse.gov/1600/presidents/williamhowardtaft">Link</ref></bibl>
                
                <bibl>“William Howard Taft.” <hi rendition="#italics">WGBH American Experience PBS</hi>. Accessed June 30, 2015. <ref target="http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/americanexperience/features/biography/presidents-taft/">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 1782-3313_b2f8_1_TEI.xml; 11565-3133_b2f9_1_TEI.xml &#13;
&#13;
mentioned in 11570-3313_b2f9_1_TEI.xml &#13;
&#13;
LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79022244&#13;
&#13;
http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79022244.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000000383">
  <persName key="ENT.000000383">
    <forename type="first">Charles Jay</forename>
    <surname type="last">Taylor</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1855">1855</birth>
  <death when="1929">1929</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">artist for Puck.  hint cartoon #11484&#13;
LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n95002542</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003169">
  <persName key="ENT.000003169">
    <forename type="first">Zachary</forename>
    <surname type="last">Taylor</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1784">1784</birth>
  <death when="1850">1850</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Zachary Taylor (November 24, 1784-July 9, 1850) was the 12th President of the United States, serving from March 1849 until his death in July 1850. Prior to his presidency, Taylor was a career officer in the United States Army, rising to the rank of major general. His status as a national hero as a result of his victories in the Mexican-American War won him election to the White House despite his vague political beliefs. His top priority as president was preserving the Union, but he died sixteen months into his term, before making any progress on the status of slavery, which had been inflaming tensions in Congress.</p>
                <p>Taylor was born to a prominent family of planters who migrated westward from Virginia to Kentucky in his youth. He was commissioned as an officer in the U.S. Army in 1808 and made a name for himself as a captain in the War of 1812. He climbed the ranks establishing military forts along the Mississippi River and entered the Black Hawk War as a colonel in 1832. His success in the Second Seminole War attracted national attention and earned him the nickname "Old Rough and Ready".</p>
                <p>In 1845, as the annexation of Texas was underway, President James K. Polk dispatched Taylor to the Rio Grande area in anticipation of a potential battle with Mexico over the disputed Texas-Mexico border. The Mexican–American War broke out in May 1846, and Taylor led American troops to victory in a series of battles culminating in the Battle of Palo Alto and the Battle of Monterrey. He became a national hero, and political clubs sprung up to draw him into the upcoming 1848 presidential election.</p>
                <p>The Whig Party convinced the reluctant Taylor to lead their ticket, despite his unclear platform and lack of interest in politics. He won the election alongside U.S. Representative Millard Fillmore of New York, defeating Democratic candidate Lewis Cass. As president, Taylor kept his distance from Congress and his cabinet, even as partisan tensions threatened to divide the Union. Debate over the slave status of the large territories claimed in the war led to threats of secession from Southerners. Despite being a Southerner and a slaveholder himself, Taylor did not push for the expansion of slavery. To avoid the question, he urged settlers in New Mexico and California to bypass the territorial stage and draft constitutions for statehood, setting the stage for the Compromise of 1850. Taylor died suddenly of a stomach-related illness in July 1850, ensuring he would have little impact on the sectional divide that led to civil war a decade later.</p></note>
  <note type="internal">Copied HINT project biography from preexisting description, written by Allison Chomet (RM 5/20/15). May be depicted in 12278 (could be Winfield Scott instead). LOC: http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50008436.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003590">
  <persName key="ENT.000003590">
    <forename type="first">John</forename>
    <surname type="last">Tenniel</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1820">1820</birth>
  <death when="1914">1914</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Sir John Tenniel was a cartoonist and illustrator, born in London, England, in 1820. Tenniel was educated at the Royal Academy and at the Clipstone Street Life Academy, in London. He became a cartoonist for the illustrated, satirical magazine, <hi rendition="#italics">Punch</hi>, or the <hi rendition="#italics">London Charivari</hi>, in 1850, became a junior partner with John Leech in 1861, and succeeded Leech as chief cartoonist in 1864. <hi rendition="#italics">Punch</hi> published more than 2,500 of his cartoons between 1851 and 1901, when he retired. Tenniel was also a prolific and notable illustrator, best known for his illustrations of Lewis Carroll’s <hi rendition="#italics">Alice’s Adventures in Wonderlan</hi>d (1865) and <hi rendition="#italics">Through the Looking-Glass</hi> and <hi rendition="#italics">What Alive Found There</hi> (1872). Tenniel was knighted in 1893 upon the recommendation of William Gladstone, a favorite subject of Tenniel’s cartoons. Tenniel died in London, in1914, just a few days short of his ninety-fourth birthday.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>“Tenniel, John.” <hi rendition="#italics">Benezit Dictionary of Artists. Oxford Art Online.</hi> Oxford University Press.  <ref target="http://proxy.library.upenn.edu:2663/subscriber/article/benezit/B00180912">Link</ref></bibl>
                <bibl>“Tenniel, John.” <hi rendition="#italics">Grove Art Online. Oxford Art Online.</hi> Oxford University Press.  <ref target="http://proxy.library.upenn.edu:2663/subscriber/article/grove/art/T083805">Link</ref></bibl>
                <bibl>“Tenniel, Sir John.” <hi rendition="#italics">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</hi>.</bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79058883.html. Artist of 11511</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003385">
  <persName key="ENT.000003385">
    <forename type="first">Allen</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Granberry</forename>
    <surname type="last">Thurman</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1813">1813</birth>
  <death when="1895">1895</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">Cleveland's running mate in 1888 ; depicted in 11524-PG278_b5f2_1_TEI.xml ; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n85808912.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003566">
  <persName key="ENT.000003566">
    <forename type="first">Samuel</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Jones</forename>
    <surname type="last">Tilden</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1814">1814</birth>
  <death when="1886">1886</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Samuel Jones Tilden was born in 1814 in New York.  He studied law in New York and was admitted to the bar in 1841.   He soon became a successful lawyer and political leader.  In 1874 he was elected to serve as Governor of New York.  As governor, he fought corruption and broke up the “Canal Ring,” a scheme involving illegal contracts for work on the State’s canal system.  He also helped bring about the downfall of the infamous William “Boss” Tweed.</p>
<p>In 1876, Tilden became the Democratic nominee for president.  He ran against Republican Rutherford B. Hayes in what would become the most contested election in US history.  The election results in Florida, Louisiana, South Carolina, and Oregon were unclear, and so Congress assembled an Electoral Commission to decide who would win the disputed electoral college votes.  It is believed that Republicans and Southern Democrats made a deal in which they would support Hayes for president if he withdrew federal troops from the South and ended Reconstruction.  Although Tilden won the popular vote, Rutherford Hayes became president.  Tilden died on August 4, 1886.</p>
</note>
  <bibl><bibl>“Samuel J. Tilden.” <hi rendition="#italics">Encyclopedia Britannica Online</hi>. Accessed June 11, 2015. <ref target="http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/595754/Samuel-J-Tilden">Link</ref></bibl>
                
                
                <bibl>“Samuel Tilden Biography.” <hi rendition="#italics">Gateway National Recreation Area (U.S. National Park Service)</hi>. Accessed June 11, 2015. <ref target="http://www.nps.gov/gate/learn/historyculture/samuel-tilden-biography.htm">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50013053</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000000403">
  <persName key="ENT.000000403">
    <forename type="first">Morris</forename>
    <forename type="middle">H.</forename>
    <surname type="last">Traubel</surname>
    <addName type="alt">M. H. Traubel</addName>
    <addName type="alt">Martin H. Traubel</addName>
    <addName type="alt">Mauritz H. Traubel</addName>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1820">1820</birth>
  <death when="1897">1897</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">Morris H. Traubel (also credited as Mauritz or Martin H. Traubel) was born in Germany, where he studied lithography. By the early 1850s, he had immigrated to Philadelphia, where he briefly partnered with Edward Schnabel, Theodore Leonhardt, and John F. Finkeldey to form a printing business called the Lithographic Institute. Traubel subsequently started his own printing firm in Philadelphia, where he continued to live and work until his death in 1897.</note>
  <bibl>Biography at Department of Special Collections, University of Pennsylvania Library. <ref target="http://www.library.upenn.edu/collections/rbm/keffer/traubel.html">Link</ref></bibl>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003765">
  <persName key="ENT.000003765">
    <forename type="first">Frances</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Milton</forename>
    <surname type="last">Trollope</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1780">1780</birth>
  <death when="1863">1863</death>
  <sex>Female</sex>
  <note type="biography">English novelist and writer whose first book, <hi rendition="#italics">Domestic Manners of the Americans</hi> (1832) ignited controversy in the United States.</note>
  <note type="internal">Mentioned in 8306</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003386">
  <persName key="ENT.000003386">
    <forename type="first">William</forename>
    <surname type="last">Tryon</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1729">1729</birth>
  <death when="1788">1788</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">mentioned in 2562-Bb612L615_1_TEI.xml (Liberty Triumphant) ; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n81027825.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003638">
  <persName key="ENT.000003638">
    <forename type="first">William</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Marcy</forename>
    <surname type="last">Tweed</surname>
    <addName type="alt">Tweed, Boss, 1823-1878</addName>
    <addName type="alt">Tweed, William Magear, 1823-1878</addName>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1823-04-03">1823-04-03</birth>
  <death when="1878-04-12">1878-04-12</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">Depicted as a lizard in "The Silence of Matt Quay," DAMS #11737</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003709">
  <persName key="ENT.000003709">
    <surname type="last">Umberto I, King of Italy</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1844">1844</birth>
  <death when="1900">1900</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80125834&#13;
depicted in Hint cartoon #12151</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003387">
  <persName key="ENT.000003387">
    <surname type="last">Unknown</surname>
  </persName>
  <note type="internal">Needed for digital history projects, which may have an unknown entity who is not an artist.</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000000553">
  <persName key="ENT.000000553">
    <surname type="last">Unknown Artist</surname>
  </persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003308">
  <persName key="ENT.000003308">
    <forename type="first">Martin</forename>
    <surname type="last">Van Buren</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1782">1782</birth>
  <death when="1862">1862</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">Martin Van Buren (December 5, 1782 – July 24, 1862) was the eighth President of the United States (1837–1841). Before his presidency, he was the eighth Vice President (1833–1837) and the tenth secretary of state (1829–1831), both under Andrew Jackson.
Van Buren was a key organizer of the Democratic Party, a dominant figure in the Second Party System, and the first president not of British or Irish descent—his family was Dutch. He was the first president to have been born a United States citizen, since all of his predecessors were born British subjects before the American Revolution. He is the only president not to have spoken English as his first language, having grown up speaking Dutch, and the first president from New York.
As Andrew Jackson's Secretary of State and then Vice President, Van Buren was a key figure in building the organizational structure for Jacksonian democracy, particularly in New York. As president, he did not want the United States to annex Texas, an act which John Tyler would achieve eight years after Van Buren's initial rejection. Between the bloodless Aroostook War and the Caroline Affair, relations with Britain and its colonies in Canada also proved to be strained.
His administration was largely characterized by the economic hardship of his time, the Panic of 1837. He was scapegoated for the depression and called "Martin Van Ruin" by political opponents. Van Buren was voted out of office after four years, losing to Whig candidate William Henry Harrison. In the 1848 election Van Buren ran unsuccessfully for president on a third-party ticket, the Free Soil Party. Van Buren died fourteen years later at the age of seventy-nine.</note>
  <note type="internal">Used Allison Chomet's description for HINT project description--RM 5/27/15</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003634">
  <persName key="ENT.000003634">
    <forename type="first">Cornelius</forename>
    <surname type="last">Vanderbilt</surname>
    <addName type="alt">Commodore Vanderbilt</addName>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1794">1794</birth>
  <death when="1877">1877</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Cornelius Vanderbilt was a successful steamship and railroad tycoon, one of the wealthiest men of the Gilded Age. Vanderbilt was born on Staten Island, one of many children of a modest farming family. To supplement the family income, Cornelius’s father, also Cornelius, ferried produce to Manhattan. Young Cornelius much preferred sailing to school or farming, and by the age of sixteen he had established his own ferry service, a business that expanded during the War of 1812. In 1813, Vanderbilt married his cousin, Sophia Johnson, and together the couple had thirteen children. Throughout the early years of the nineteenth-century, Vanderbilt expanded his boating enterprises and his fortune, entering the steamboat business by 1818 when he went to work for Thomas Gibbons running a service between New York and New Jersey and settling his family in New Brunswick, New Jersey, where Sophia ran a successful tavern. In 1829, with a capital of $30,000, he ventured out on his own to ply the Hudson River and Long Island Sound, competing successfully with steamboat established lines. By the late 1830s he was known as “Commodore” Vanderbilt and had a fortune of $1 million. In 1840, the Vanderbilts moved to a new mansion next to the old family farm on Staten Island. In the later 1840s, the family moved to Manhattan. It was during the 1840s, too, that Vanderbilt entered the railroad business, buying stock in several Long Island and New Jersey lines. In 1857 he became the director of the New York and Harlem Railroad, and he continued his acquisitions into the 1860s and 1870s. By 1865 he held a controlling interest in the Hudson River Railroad and was elected president. After a rate war with the New York Central Railroad, Vanderbilt acquired large quantities of its stock and became its director in 1867. In that same year he consolidated  the New York Central and the Hudson River Railroad, with himself as president. Sophia Vanderbilt died in 1868. The bereaved widower soon remarried, marrying a woman named Frank Crawford in August 1869. In 1871, Vanderbilt—at the instigation of his new wife—donated $1 million to found Vanderbilt University in Nashville, Tennessee. He also completed construction of Grand Central Depot in New York. By late 1876, Vanderbilt, now in his eighties, suffered a prolonged illness. He died at his New York City home on January 4, 1877, leaving a fortune of $100 million, mostly to his son William.</p></note>
  <bibl> <bibl>“Vanderbilt, Cornelius.” American National Biography.</bibl>
                
                <bibl><hi rendition="#italics">New York Times</hi>. “Cornelius Vanderbilt.” January 5, 1877.</bibl>
                
                <bibl><hi rendition="#italics">New York Times</hi>. “Cornelius Vanderbilt. A Long and Useful Life Ended.” January 5, 1877.</bibl>
                
                <bibl><hi rendition="#italics">New York Times</hi>. “Commodore Vanderbilt’s Life.” January 5, 1877.</bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50045037.html; depicted in 11747. Note/annotation from 11747: Cornelius ("Commodore") Vanderbilt made his fortune in the railroad business and in 1872, when this cartoon was published, was the richest man in America. His strong interest in spiritualism put him in touch with sisters <persName key="ENT.000002960">Victoria Woodhull</persName> and <persName key="ENT.000003633">Tennessee Claflin</persName>, who became his advisors. He provided silent financial backing for at least two historic firsts: the establishment of Woodhull and Claflin's brokerage firm, which made them the first women stock brokers, and Woodhull's presidential campaign, in which she became the first woman to run for president.</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003710">
  <persName key="ENT.000003710">
    <surname type="last">Victoria, Queen of Great Britain</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1819">1819</birth>
  <death when="1901">1901</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in Hint cartoon #12151&#13;
http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79017983</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003630">
  <persName key="ENT.000003630">
    <forename type="first">James</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Albert</forename>
    <surname type="last">Wales</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1852">1852</birth>
  <death when="1886">1886</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"> <p>James Albert Wales was an American cartoonist.  He was born on August 20, 1852 in Clyde, Ohio.  He attended public school in Ohio and later traveled to London and Paris to study art.  He worked for an engraver in Toledo before moving to Cleveland to work as a cartoonist for the <hi rendition="#italics">Cleveland Ledger</hi>.  He became chief cartoonist for <hi rendition="#italics">Leslie’s Ilustrated Newspaper</hi>.  In 1879, Joseph Keppler hired him to work as a cartoonist at Puck.  In 1881, he had a disagreement with Joseph Keppler, left the magazine, and founded <hi rendition="#italics">Judge</hi>.  Wales sold <hi rendition="#italics">Judge</hi> in 1885 to William J. Arkell and went back to work for Keppler at <hi rendition="#italics">Puck</hi>.  He died at the age of 34 of a drug overdose.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>Hess, Stephen and Milton Kaplan. <hi rendition="#italics">The Ungentlemanly Art: A History of American Political Cartoons</hi>.  New York: Macmillan, 1968.</bibl>
                
                <bibl>Kahn, Michael A, Richard Samuel West, Bill Watterson, and Dean Mullaney. <hi rendition="#italics">What Fools These Mortals Be!: The Story of Puck: America’s First and Most Influential Magazine of Color Political Cartoons</hi>, 2014.</bibl>       
                <bibl>West, Richard Samuel. <hi rendition="#italics">Satire On Stone: The Political Cartoons of Joseph Keppler</hi>. Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1988.</bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n95002906</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003711">
  <persName key="ENT.000003711">
    <forename type="first">Solly</forename>
    <surname type="last">Walter</surname>
  </persName>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">Artist for Wasp.  Artist for Hint cartoon #11685</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003366">
  <persName key="ENT.000003366">
    <forename type="first">Thomas</forename>
    <forename type="middle">B.</forename>
    <surname type="last">Wanamaker</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1865">1865</birth>
  <death when="1908">1908</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">publisher of North American newspaper.  Purchased paper in 1899.</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003754">
  <persName key="ENT.000003754">
    <forename type="first">Charles</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Franklin</forename>
    <surname type="last">Warwick</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1852">1852</birth>
  <death when="1913">1913</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">Philadelphia mayor.  depicted in hint cartoon #12157&#13;
http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2004025594</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000000167">
  <persName key="ENT.000000167">
    <forename type="first">George</forename>
    <surname type="last">Washington</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1732">1732</birth>
  <death when="1799">1799</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003700">
  <persName key="ENT.000003700">
    <forename type="first">Henry</forename>
    <surname type="last">Watterson</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1840">1840</birth>
  <death when="1921">1921</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50043700&#13;
&#13;
Depicted in Hint cartoon #11834</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003390">
  <persName key="ENT.000003390">
    <forename type="first">James</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Watson</forename>
    <surname type="last">Webb</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1802">1802</birth>
  <death when="1884">1884</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 11561, 11508 ; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr89007202.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000001368">
  <persName key="ENT.000001368">
    <forename type="first">Daniel</forename>
    <surname type="last">Webster</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1782">1782</birth>
  <death when="1852">1852</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003571">
  <persName key="ENT.000003571">
    <forename type="first">Theodoric</forename>
    <forename type="middle">R</forename>
    <surname type="last">Westbrook</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1821">1821</birth>
  <death when="1885">1885</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Theodoric Westbrook was a congressman and New York Supreme Court Justice.</p>
      <p>Westbrook was born on November 20, 1882 in New York.  He graduated from Rutgers College in 1838, studied law, and was admitted to the bar in 1843.  He practiced in Kingston, Ulster County, NY.  Westbrook became a member of the US House of Representatives in 1853 and served only one term (1853-1855).  In 1873, Westbrook became a Justice of the New York Supreme Court.</p>  
      <p>Westbrook was accused of using his judicial powers to help Jay Gould acquire the Manhattan Elevated Railway Company.  A special committee of the NY State Assembly investigated the accusations and found Westbrook innocent of the corruption charges.   It was rumored that the committee members had accepted bribes, and, thus, Westbrook’s reputation was forever tarnished.  He died on October 6, 1885.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>“Found Dead in His Room:  Judge T.R. Westbrook Stricken with Heart Disease.” <hi rendition="#italics">NY Times Online</hi>.   Accessed June 24, 2015. <ref target="http://query.nytimes.com/mem/archive-free/pdf?res=9C03E5DE173AEF33A25754C0A9669D94649FD7CF">Link</ref></bibl>
      <bibl>“Westbrook, Theodoric Romeyn.” <hi rendition="#italics">Biographical Directory of the United States Congress</hi>. Accessed June 24, 2015. <ref target="http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=W000307">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no98076093.html. depicted in hint cartoon "deadly upas tree of wall street"
</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003767">
  <persName key="ENT.000003767">
    <forename type="first">John</forename>
    <surname type="last">Wilkes</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1725">1725</birth>
  <death when="1797">1797</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 12017</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003665">
  <persName key="ENT.000003665">
    <forename type="first">William</forename>
    <surname type="last">Barnes</surname>
    <addName type="alt">Bill Barnes</addName>
  </persName>
  <sex>Male</sex>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003708">
  <persName key="ENT.000003708">
    <surname type="last">William I, German Emperor</surname>
    <addName type="alt">Wilhelm I, German Emperor, 1797-1888</addName>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1797">1797</birth>
  <death when="1888">1888</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80149385&#13;
depicted in hint cartoon #12151</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003666">
  <persName key="ENT.000003666">
    <surname type="last">William II</surname>
    <addName type="alt">Wilhelm II, German Emperor, 1859-1941</addName>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1859">1859</birth>
  <death when="1941">1941</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>William II was born on January 27, 1859 in Berlin and was the last German emperor and King of Prussia.  His full name in German was Friedrich Wilhelm Viktor Albert.  He was the oldest son of Crown Prince Frederick and Victoria, the daughter of Great Britain’s Queen Victoria. In 1888, at the age of 29, he became the Kaiser or German emperor and two years later, forced the resignation of the chancellor, Otto von Bismarck.  William II strengthened the navy and military and strongly promoted German colonial expansion.</p>
                <p>In 1914 Archduke Franz Ferdinand, heir to the Austro-Hungarian Empire, was assassinated in Sarajevo by a Bosnian Serb Gavrilo Princip.  In response, William II encouraged Austria to use its military might to strike against Serbia and assured Austria that Germany would support them in the event of war.  On July 28, 1914 Austria declared war on Serbia.  Soon after, the Triple Entente or Allies (Russia, United Kingdom, and France) entered into war against the Central powers of Austria and Germany.  The United States Congress declared war on Germany on April 6, 1917.</p>
                <p>At the conclusion of World War I, William II abdicated the throne and fled to the Netherlands.  The Allies unsuccessfully tried to extradite him and to put him on trial for war crimes.  He died on June 4, 1941.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>“William II  Emperor of Germany.” <hi rendition="#italics">Encyclopedia Britannica Online</hi>. Accessed June 30, 2015. <ref target="http://www.britannica.com/biography/William-II-emperor-of-Germany">Link</ref></bibl>
                
                <bibl>“Wilhelm II (1859 - 1941).” BBC History, Historic Figures. Accessed June 30, 2015. <ref target="http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/historic_figures/wilhelm_kaiser_ii.shtml">Link</ref></bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50018122</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003730">
  <persName key="ENT.000003730">
    <forename type="first">John</forename>
    <forename type="middle">C.</forename>
    <surname type="last">Williams</surname>
  </persName>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">In August 1820, newspapers reported the story of "John C. Williams," a drunk man, claiming to be from Philadelphia, who was falsely diagnosed with yellow fever by doctors in New York. Williams's story is parodied in the circa 1820 political cartoon "A Case of Infectious Fever."</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003391">
  <persName key="ENT.000003391">
    <forename type="first">Orville</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Peter</forename>
    <surname type="last">Williams</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1876">1876</birth>
  <death when="1944">1944</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">artist of 11567-3133_b2f9_1_TEI.xml &#13;
&#13;
http://strippersguide.blogspot.com/2012/11/ink-slinger-profiles-op-williams.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003084">
  <persName key="ENT.000003084">
    <forename type="first">Woodrow</forename>
    <surname type="last">Wilson</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1856">1856</birth>
  <death when="1924">1924</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Woodrow Wilson was the twenty-eighth President of the United States.</p>
                <p>Wilson was born on December 28, 1856 in Virginia.  After graduating from Princeton University in 1879, Wilson studied law at the University of Virginia (1879-1873) and earned a Ph.D. in 1885 from Johns Hopkins University.  He became a professor and taught at Bryn Mawr College and Wesleyan University.  He married Ellen Louise Axson in 1885 and had three children.  She died in 1914.  Wilson later married Edith Bolling Galt in 1915. </p>
                <p>In 1890, Wilson began working at Princeton University as a professor.  Twelve years later, in 1902, he became President of Princeton University and put forth a $12.5 million program that would forever transform Princeton University.   In 1910, United States Senator, James Smith, Jr. and New York editor George Harvey convinced Wilson to run for governor of New Jersey on the democratic ticket.  He won the election and served one term.</p>  
                <p>In 1912 Wilson was nominated as the Democratic candidate for the office of President of the United States.  He ran against the Republican incumbent, William Howard Taft and the Progressive Party candidate, Theodore Roosevelt.  The split in the Republican Party vote helped Wilson to win the election.  He served two terms.  As president, Wilson worked with Congress to pass several social and economic reforms such as the Federal Reserve Act, the Child Labor Reform Act, and the 19th amendment which granted women the right to vote.  Wilson led the nation during World War I and tried to establish the League of Nations.  He suffered a stroke in 1919 and died on February 3, 1924.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl> “Woodrow Wilson.” <hi rendition="#italics">The White House</hi>. Accessed June 25, 2015. <ref target="https://www.whitehouse.gov/1600/presidents/woodrowwilson">Link</ref></bibl>
                
                <bibl>“Woodrow Wilson Biography.” <hi rendition="#italics">Woodrow Wilson Presidential Library and Museum</hi>. Accessed June 25, 2015. <ref target="http://www.woodrowwilson.org/about/biography">Link</ref></bibl>
                
                <bibl>“Woodrow Wilson- A Portrait.” <hi rendition="#italics">PBS American Experience</hi>. Accessed June 25, 2015. <ref target="http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/amex/wilson/portrait/index.html">Link</ref></bibl>
                
                <bibl>“Wilson, Woodrow.” <hi rendition="#italics">Princeton University</hi>. Accessed June 25, 2015. <ref target="http://etcweb.princeton.edu/CampusWWW/Companion/wilson_woodrow.html">Link</ref></bibl>
</bibl>
  <note type="internal">LOC:  http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79046299</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000002960">
  <persName key="ENT.000002960">
    <forename type="first">Victoria</forename>
    <forename type="middle">Claflin</forename>
    <surname type="last">Woodhull</surname>
    <addName type="alt">Victoria California Claflin</addName>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1838">1838</birth>
  <death when="1927">1927</death>
  <sex>Female</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Victoria Claflin Woodhull was perhaps the most sensational woman of early 1870s America. Born in 1838 in Homer, Ohio, Victoria was the seventh of ten children of Reuben and Roxanna Claflin. She experienced a poor and rootless childhood. At an early age she, with her younger sister Tennessee, became interested in spiritualism, and the sisters helped support their family with their psychic remedies for medical problems. Victoria married Canning Woodhull, a physician, in 1853, and had two children with him. She divorced Canning in 1865, who had become a drunkard and had drifted away, and in 1866 at least secured a marriage license to marry her lover, Col. James Harvey Blood, a Civil War veteran who had been one of her patients (no record of an actual ceremony exists). Woodhull, Blood, Tennessee Claflin, and other members of the Claflin family moved to New York City in 1868, where the sisters arranged a meeting with Cornelius Vanderbilt, the wealthy financier who shared their interest in spiritualism. Vanderbilt became the sisters’ financial advisor, and after some financial successes in late 1869, they launched their brokerage house in January 1870, becoming the first female stock brokers in the United States. Vanderbilt was almost certainly the silent partner in their firm, Woodhull, Claflin &amp; Co.</p>
                
                <p>By this time, Woodhull had also become involved in a number of reform causes, embracing Stephen Pearl Andrews’s idea of “Pantarchy,” which advocated a state in which property was commonly owned and free love replaced monogamous marriage. On April 2, 1870, Woodhull declared her candidacy for the presidency through a letter published in the <hi rendition="#italics">New York Herald</hi>. In May, she and Tennessee launched their own newspaper, <hi rendition="#italics">Woodhull &amp; Claflin’s Weekly</hi>, edited largely by Andrews and Blood. The paper combined columns on radical reform ideals along with financial news and muckraking journalism. By 1871, Woodhull became involved in the woman suffrage movement and was embraced by leaders such as Elizabeth Cady Stanton and Susan B. Anthony. In January 1871 she became the first woman to testify before a congressional committee, speaking on behalf of the suffrage issue, arguing that women already had the right to vote under the Fourteenth Amendment. Suffrage leaders later distanced themselves from Woodhull, because of her radical views and controversial personal life. . In 1872, Woodhull was nominated for president by the newly organized Equal Rights Party, after losing the support of the National Woman Suffrage Association and its proposed People’s Party. By late 1872, Woodhull’s star was beginning to fall. She spent election day in jail for publishing and circulating through the mails, in violation of the Comstock Act, details of the beloved minister Henry Ward Beecher’s extramarital affair with Elizabeth Tilton in order to pressure Beecher to endorse free love. The backlash to her role in the Beecher scandal and to her own controversial lifestyle further isolated Woodhull. By 1876, she reversed her position on free love and distanced herself from spiritualism. She divorced Blood for adultery, and in 1877 left for England with Tennessee, her children, and other members of her family. There she married banker John Biddulph Martin in 1883 and lived a relatively conventional life. She published a journal on eugenics, lectured, and cultivated a respectable image. She died in Tewksbury in 1927.</p></note>
  <bibl><bibl>“Woodhull, Victoria Claflin.” <hi rendition="#italics">American National Biography</hi>.</bibl>
                
                <bibl>“Woodhull, Victoria Claflin.” <hi rendition="#italics">Notable American Women</hi>.</bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">depicted in 11747</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003536">
  <persName key="ENT.000003536">
    <forename type="first">Silas</forename>
    <surname type="last">Wright</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1795">1795</birth>
  <death when="1847">1847</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="internal">May be depicted in 11508; http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n88130501.html</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003756">
  <persName key="ENT.000003756">
    <forename type="first">Brigham</forename>
    <surname type="last">Young</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1801">1801</birth>
  <death when="1877">1877</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography">Brigham Young was the second president of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints from December 27, 1847, and governor of Utah Territory from 1849. He was born in Vermont in 1801 joined the LDS church in 1832, and led the Mormon exodus from Illinois to Utah beginning in 1846.</note>
  <bibl>Biography at Library of Congress Name Authority File. <ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50013614.html">Link</ref></bibl>
  <note type="internal">Short bio at http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50013614.html. Depicted in 11823</note>
</person>
<person xml:id="ENT.000003652">
  <persName key="ENT.000003652">
    <forename type="first">Marius</forename>
    <surname type="last">de Zayas</surname>
  </persName>
  <birth when="1880">1880</birth>
  <death when="1961">1961</death>
  <sex>Male</sex>
  <note type="biography"><p>Marius de Zayas was an artist, illustrator and gallery owner.  He was born on March 13, 1880 in Veracruz, Mexico.  He began his career working at his father’s newspaper as an illustrator.  In 1906 he began working at <hi rendition="#italics">El Diario</hi>, a newspaper critical of the policies of President Porfirio Diaz.  He soon fled to the United States and settled in New York City.  He worked for the <hi rendition="#italics">New York Evening World</hi> as a cartoonist.  Alfred Stieglitz displayed De Zayas’s artwork in his gallery in 1909 and 1910.  In 1910 he traveled to Paris where he became inspired by the artwork of Francis Picabia.  De Zayas opened an art gallery in New York City in 1915.  After closing the gallery in 1921, he moved to Europe where he spent the next two decades organizing modern art shows.  He died on January 10, 1961.</p> </note>
  <bibl><bibl>“De Zaya, Marius.” <hi rendition="#italics">Oxford Art Online</hi>. Accessed July 1, 2015. <ref target="http://www.oxfordartonline.com/public/page/GAO_free_article_DeZayas">Link</ref></bibl>
                
                <bibl>Kahn, Michael A, Richard Samuel West, Bill Watterson, and Dean Mullaney. <hi rendition="#italics">What Fools These Mortals Be!: The Story of Puck: America’s First and Most Influential Magazine of Color Political Cartoons</hi>, 2014.</bibl></bibl>
  <note type="internal">http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n81138346&#13;
HINT 12239 artist</note>
</person>
                </listPerson>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
